MARCUS: This is Yav
[? Weiss. ?]
I'll try to keep everything
very brief.
As we get established.
So Yov's been doing quite a lot
of work with responsive
images of late.
He's heavily involved
in the responsive
images community group.
Then we have Peter Miller.
So Peter Miller is a developer
who works on a lot of concept
heavy websites, image
heavy websites.
Great experience.
Anne Robinson also works for--
ANNE ROBINSON: Yammer.
MARCUS: Yammer.
Sorry, I forgot.
Has written fantastic stuff
about web performance, has
some great ideas about how we
can address on the responsive
images problems using
progressive jpgs.
[INAUDIBLE]
well, has anyone heard
of the clown car
technique, the creator.
So we're going to hopefully talk
a little bit about that.
And John Mellor works
at Google.
And John Mellor is probably the
only person on earth who
can tell the difference between
a device pixel, a real
pixel, a CSS pixel, and all
sorts of other pixels.
And he can do it all
in his head.
It's pretty crazy.
So first up, we have Yav, who
is going to give a 10 minute
talk basically outlining what
the current solutions are that
we've been basically discussing
for the last two
years trying to come
up with a solution
for responsive images.
Take it away.
YAV: So we'll swap seats.
So hi.
As Marcus said, I'm
Yav [? Weiss. ?]
I'm here to talk about
responsive images I'll try to
sum up two years of discussions
into 10 minutes
talk, so bear with me.
So first, in the mid-2000s,
all we had
was mobile only sites.
They were kind of lame, with
very slim content, highly
optimized images.
It got a little better
with the iPhone, but
it wasn't that hot.
Then responsive web design
became a thing,
which was very cool.
One code base to
rule them all.
You can all the devices
through a single site.
But the problem is it
was kind of slow.
It became a synonym
to slow mobile
websites, which is a problem.
So the reason is that most serve
the same resources to
both mobile and desktop.
And most of that
data is images.
So there are a lot of
savings to be made.
I wrote a utility, which can Tim
Cadillac run, Tim Cadillac
is a developer-- sorry
for namedropping.
But basically, we saw that up
to 72% of the image of data
can be saved for some
of the viewports
in some of the cases.
So there's a lot of savings
to be made.
And retina only makes things
worse because the gap between
the smallest images you want
to send and the highest
resolution images you want to
send is getting bigger.
And with most devs owning retina
devices, most devs are
high resolution images
to all devices.
So this is the responsive images
problem, which we like
to divide into two
major use cases.
The first one is resolution
switching, serving different
images to different devices--
different dimension images,
different devices.
The images are the same images,
the same proportions,
they're not cropped.
But basically, the quality
is different.
This is one example of that.
And it can be further divided
into DPR switching, serving
retina images only to retina
devices, and viewport
switching, which is adapting
image dimensions to the actual
display to the sites that in
which they will be displayed.
Then the other major use
case is art direction.
Basically, it's content
optimization without wasting
too many bytes.
Its matching the images
to the layout in a
way that makes sense.
So either a crop, or different
proportions, or something that
works according to the actual
responsive break points from a
survey we ran a lot
of developer.
A lot of developers are already
doing that using hacks
so this is a major
use case here.
And so we've talked
about the problem.
Let's talk about the solutions
there are several proposed
standard solutions.
There's the srcset attribute,
picture elements, client-hints
header, and I put a question
mark in because it's not
really a standard solution.
This is just a proposal at the
moment, but the responsive
image container.
I'll talk about each
one in detail.
So srcset, basically, it's the
same old image tag, now with
new attributes that can include
multiple resources
according to the DPR
and the viewport.
It's a slightly controversial
statement, but it addresses
mainly the resolution switching
case and, much less,
the art direction case.
Some people would
disagree, but--
Srcset it is currently
implemented in
WebKit and in Blink.
It's behind the flag In
blink, and it's not
just shipped in WebKit.
But it's there and
the code base.
Firefox will soon follow.
And basically, it looks
something like this.
You specified the 1x, or 2x, or
1.5x, or 3x, qualifiers for
each image resource you
add to the page.
The entire spec also includes
viewport switching, which
looks something like this.
For each resource, you specify
the max viewport for which it
can be applied to and the x
factor that's adapted to it.
The problem with that--
it gives you a lot of expressive
power, but you also
have to, in some cases, like you
can see in the example I
put up, you have to define a
single URL several times
because it fits several DPR
and viewport combinations.
Then we have picture,
which is mainly
targeted at art direction.
It's an element with multiple
source children.
Each one of them is specifying
an image resource based on
media queries and,
possibly, type.
And the first matching
resource is
downloaded and displayed.
It looks something like this.
And as you can see,
it can mix srcset
into the source elements.
So you can define an
art-directed image with
multiple DPR versions of it.
And the media attributes you use
here are most probably the
same media values if you use for
your layout break points,
unlike viewport resolution
switching, which can be
independent of the
layout viewport.
Then we have, as a third
contender, or third proposal,
we have client hints that is,
unlike the two others, it's
not a markup-based solution.
It's an HTTP-based solution.
And basically, the client sends
out its capabilities.
It sends out hints to the
server, saying this is my DPR,
this is my viewport
width or height.
The actual values are still
debated, but this is the
general spirit.
And everything is done
on the server side.
It's server logic that serves
one resource or the other.
And one recent change
to this proposal is
that it's opt-in only.
The hints are not sent on
the first HTML request.
On the other hand, it saves us
from adding data to requests
where the server is not going
to do anything about it.
So that's recent compromise that
may be able to push the
spec forward.
Then I have something I'm
proposing as more of a long
term solution.
This is not something that's on
anyone's immediate radar.
But it's a long term solution
I'm proposing.
That's a file format
based approach.
We're basically, each targets
resolution that we want to
serve is represented
in a layer in
some sort of a container.
And these layers are building up
one on top of the other so
that the browser can download a
certain number of layers and
then add more layers on
that enhancing the
quality of the image.
It can address both resolution
switching and art direction.
And I'll just to show you
a bunch of examples.
So basically, for resolution
switching, we have this photo
that, if we look into the layers
that compose it, it's a
thumbnail, then and enhancement
layer, which is
basically the thumbnail upscaled
with [INAUDIBLE]
from the original image
downscaled, and an enhancement
layer, and then another one
that's basically used to
recreate the original image
without adding many bytes to
the process.
The overhead is very small.
And for art direction, the
same can be applied.
So this bigger image that's
used everywhere for art
direction can be split into a
crop, then an enhancement
layer, and another one.
The advantages are that
markup is not touched.
You have a single file
per image, so
it's easy to maintain.
And the best one for me is
that the browser can just
download [? difs ?].
If they had downloaded one
image, and then do something
in the browser's environment
have changed, you can download
the [? dif ?].
The disadvantages are that it's
complicated to implement
and basically decoding
performance and network
performance without HTTP2
is currently a mystery.
We need to further investigate
that in order to know if it's
feasible or not without a HTTP2
and in terms of the
coding performance.
And last minute slides added by
John Mellor here maybe you
want to talk about that.
JOHN MELLOR: So a possible way
of making this responsive
format container load more
efficiently when you are
making several [INAUDIBLE]
request, and you don't leave
gaps in between and wait for a
round trip each time, it loads
all of the images on the page
in parallel, progressively.
So I've taken [INAUDIBLE].
I've stolen this, sorry.
On the left, you see the images
being loaded one by
one, sequentially.
On the right, you see images
being loaded all in parallel.
It's the same progressive
jpgs on both sides.
Just on the left, I'm truncating
the stream of
images so that you get the
first image, and then I
truncate out some point there.
On the right, I truncate all
the images at the same
percentage.
So this is 5% of the
image bytes.
And you can see that, on
both sides, the page
doesn't look great.
But by the time you've got to
10% of the image bytes,
already on the right, you can
kind of see what the page
looks like.
All the images are really
blurry, and so on, but they at
least will fill their
space well.
Whereas on the left, you can see
the start of the top left
image, but all the other images
haven't even started
loading yet.
As you gradually load more,
say you're on--
YAV: Incremements of 10.
JOHN MELLOR: Say you get
to 25%, for example.
Now the page on the right, we've
only loaded a quarter of
the image bytes, but it already
starts to look OK.
The images aren't crisp, but
they're still perfectly
usable, whereas, on the left,
we had this, super crisp,
lovely image on the top left,
but the other images haven't
started loading.
By the time you get to 50%,
the page on the right now
looks perfect.
You can almost not tell
that it hasn't
finished loading the images.
Whereas on the left,
again, we've only
got half the images.
And then, as you load more
bytes, the page on the right
gradually becomes like a super
crisp retina beautiful page.
But it's a very subtle
difference between that and
the 1x image.
Whereas on the left, only now,
at 100%, do we actually have
all the images at all visible.
YAV: Yeah, great.
ANNE ROBINSON: This is great.
I love that you're giving
something to the users while
they are waiting.
That's brilliant.
That's what I love about
progressive jpgs, is that it
will download the first scan
as soon as possible.
MARCUS: So I think that that's
kind of a good lead in to the
first question that we have,
which is from Jake's
[INAUDIBLE].
I hope I pronounced
that right.
Jake, do you have your
question with you?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
MARCUS: Mike Runner, please.
There goes Pete.
He's going to be really slim
by the end of the day.
AUDIENCE: OK, so I currently
send, like, a two times, or
2.5 times image, and just
compress the hell out of it.
And the file size is,
kind of roughly the
same as a 1x image.
And that seems to do the job.
Why do we need all these
extra markup examples?
And if, in the future, John's
solution could come and stop
the download at some point,
I mean, surely
that's all we need?
MARCUS: [INAUDIBLE].
JOHN MELLOR: So should we start
with the difference
between fixed width and
flexible width images?
So this ties into what Yav
was saying earlier about
resolution switching.
There's two kinds.
There's DPR switching, where
your images are fixed size,
like a logo or an icon.
It's going to be the
same width, say 32
pixels on all devices.
And all you need to do is switch
it out based on the
device's pick screen density.
So you might need 2x image on a
retina screen, a 3x image on
like the Samsung Galaxy S4,
that kind of thing.
But all you're doing is changing
it based on the
device pixel ratio.
With a flexible width image,
say you've got width 100%.
Then suddenly, the width
for the viewport
of the device matters.
And so your phones, your
tablets, your laptops, they
all have different widths.
They all need different
images.
And here, a simple technique
which gets you up to double
the resolution of an image by
compressing it more heavily
isn't going to scale to an
eight times bigger image.
YAV: Cool, [INAUDIBLE]
One more thing, regarding the
compressive images hack.
MARCUS: Explain what the hell
compressive images.
YAV: What Jake was talking
about, basically taking the
high-res images and extremely
compressing them so that they
will, be when downsized to a
1x display dimensions, they
will still look good.
And also for retina, they look
quite fine because the
actually display dimensions
are--
MARCUS: Hang on, I'm seeing a
few people looking at you--
so let's say if we can explain
that a little better.
Does anyone want to have a go at
explaining a little better.
ANNE ROBINSON: I mean,
I can try.
So hello.
So somebody discovered that if
they keep the resolution
really high on an image, but
they put the compression down
to, I think, zero,
is that correct?
MARCUS: That's correct.
ANNE ROBINSON: So they'll
actually get a smaller file
size that is higher
resolution.
And it looks good on
retina images.
And you have a smaller file
size for the speed.
So it's actually best
of both worlds.
And it's kind of like an
amazing discovery.
MARCUS: So I'm sure if we go
back to 1996, we might find
the same thing.
But who knows.
Because we were, like,
doing it for
modems and stuff anyway.
So I guess what I'm wondering
is, what might be some of the
side effects.
Because we're sending like four
times the data, right?
Basically sending an image
that's two times, or even
more, bigger.
The size maybe like
three times.
So can the browser really
handle that?
Do we know if there's side
effects within the browser?
ANNE ROBINSON: Yeah,
good question.
MARCUS: Maybe John is in a good
position because he's
closer to Chrome.
JOHN MELLOR: We don't have
the research yet.
So yeah, it's going to take
four times the memory.
On an image heavy page, that
might blow your memory budget.
And suddenly things like
painting and scrolling might
get slower.
It is hard to know.
We need more research,
basically.
ANNE ROBINSON: Right, yeah, we
need to experiment with that.
But it's a super interesting
idea.
YAV: Yeah, basically, it's on
the agenda to get some real
hard data on the implications
of that.
MARCUS: On the agenda of who.
YAV: On the responsive images
community group's agenda to
get some hard data on that for
the day DPR switching case.
But exactly as John said, it
doesn't cover all the cases.
And it can cause decoding
performance and memory issues.
So if you're using that, you
need to test it well to make
sure there are no problems.
Because we don't have
general data.
MARCUS: So I'm going to bounce
a question to Peter Miller,
because he's kind of like--
he's working on a lot
of, like you work on
some fashion websites.
And you've done--
anyway, whichever ones,
obviously you'd have access to
the very high resolution
pictures that are coming
straight from photographers.
What would this mean for,
maybe, you guys?
Would it mean anything?
PETER MILLER: Well, first of
all, I think I've looked at
the solution.
And I've got a retina MacBook.
And I think it's still a matter
of subjective opinion,
maybe, about whether this does
look as good as real retina
images, or 2x images.
But I think, possibly, thinking
about it even today
is the bigger problem that,
OK, well we can send these
kind of pseudo 2x images down
to be shrunk down at 50%.
But what happens when we maybe
want to expand those images,
or have them be more of
a percentage width.
And then, suddenly, we're
actually showing those highly
compressed 2x images
at the 1x size, or
their physical 1x size.
And then maybe they
look even worse.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: I think
whenever we have this debate,
we also still have to
remember people who
have metered bandwidth.
Because, yeah, on your MacBook
Pro, on your Wi-Fi, it's going
to be great.
But someone doesn't want to
download that when they are
paying $19 for a meg.
MARCUS: So yeah absolutely.
But let's hold on that one
because that one takes us off
to the following question.
So I want to not go into those
exact concerns because what
Anne originally said was, like,
you can make a larger
image that's actually smaller
in kilobytes than--
so in a sense, it doesn't
really apply.
But it does.
But we're getting to exactly
to the point [INAUDIBLE].
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: We also have
to think about Android 2.4,
and older Androids, which are
still being sold today because
they don't have the
memory capacity.
MARCUS: Right, even Firefox
OS is like 250
megabytes of RAM on that.
And it's like, it struggles.
You know?
So absolutely.
So anyone want to--
I think we should probably move
on to the next topic.
So the second question, is
there a George Crawford?
AUDIENCE: Hi, this is one of the
anonymous questions from
Google Moderator.
Is DPI negotiation
only a stopgap.
Bandwidth keeps growing
exponentially.
LCD prices are dropping.
GPUs benefit from Moore's law.
In several years, will it make
sense to just send high
resolution images
to all users.
MARCUS: So the implications are,
and this goes back, if we
look at all of computing
history, you
know, will 64K be enough?
And Moore's law, computers just
get faster, and yet we
kind of seem to find ourselves
in the same situation over and
over again.
Like back in 1996, like I was
saying before, it's like we
had modems.
And we had to compress the crap
out of images then as
well to cater to users that were
just getting cable and
who didn't have cable,
and still were on the
54 baud rate modems.
Blah blah.
So thoughts?
Should we really worry
that much?
Should we stop caring?
I know everybody's
probably excited.
Let's do a round, and bounce
back if we can, but
let's keep it short.
ANNE ROBINSON: OK, I mean I
think it would be nice if we
could just send super
large images.
But I don't think we can
do that quite yet.
But I think that the responsive
images is such a
topic because we're getting
smaller and slower, and we're
getting bigger and faster
at the same time.
So this is spreading out.
So yeah, I have, obviously,
my opinions.
But I think that we need
responsive images.
Container could be possibly a
progressive jpg that has,
like, really small scans and
really large scans and
possibly the browser only
downloads what it needs.
MARCUS: So we have a delegate
in the queue.
I'll just get Mike [INAUDIBLE]
ready.
If you can jump to a mic, Mike,
and so Pete, do you want
to quickly jump in on this?
PETER MILLER: Well, I think
staying in a hotel room in New
York City, it actually feels
like we're quite a few years
away from being a very
[? fastly ?]
connected across everywhere.
But also, you've got to think,
data plans, roaming, you want
to give the users maybe an
option to have a low
resolution mode.
But if we're just always sending
the high resolution--
but also allowing for the art
direction case, I don't think
this caters for that.
YAV: I think that as Anne
started to say, I think that
Moore's law is not giving us
the expanded bandwidth.
I mean, we get a larger
range of devices.
We have capable smaller
devices.
And the bandwidth coverage
is not ubiquitous.
So basically, it's a question
that asks us whether we can
look into the future.
And unfortunately, we can't.
But I don't think--
in 20 years, in may
be relevant.
MARCUS: I mean, we can't look
into the future, but we can
see what the trends
are, right?
We know, like, that we have
now Google Glass, and
Samsung's watch, and
things like that.
So--
YAV: Exactly.
MARCUS: In a sense, we know
a little bit where
machines are going.
And again, we're going to
see the same cycle.
So--
YAV: Yeah and,
ANNE ROBINSON: So basically, the
problem is getting worse.
MARCUS: So we found Mike.
[INAUDIBLE].
Do you want to jump in?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, just quick
question about.
So I one of you mentioned what
if you have a small image, I
mean, using high compression
at a large size that was
initially seen small
but then expanded.
It seems to be consequence
of actual jpg format.
What about new formats
such as WebP, and
using things like that?
MARCUS: So maybe I'll get John
to respond to that one.
JOHN MELLOR: So I'm not an
expert on WebP, but yeah, it
tends to give--
it seems [INAUDIBLE]
things that are nice.
It gives slightly better
compression performance,
ranging from 25 to 60,
or depends what you
are doing with it.
But it also, when very highly
compressed, you get less of
the sort of blocking artifact
you get with jpgs.
So you can actually afford a
greater compression ratio than
you would use with jpg.
So that can help.
But the ratio [INAUDIBLE]
of course.
ANNE ROBINSON: Also, with WebP,
perceived performance is
slower than progressive
jpg, right?
Because you're actually
getting a scan
earlier than a WebP.
Even if a WebP is a smaller file
size, progressive jpg is
going beat it every time.
MARCUS: Am my right too, someone
can correct me here,
but it doesn't support
progressive
loading, or does it?
ANNE ROBINSON: You know,
that's a good question.
JOHN MELLOR: No, there's
not current support for
progressive loading.
MARCUS: So I think that's
like, at least from
[INAUDIBLE] perspective,
following the blog about
that's a real showstopper
for us.
ANNE ROBINSON: Correct.
YAV: So just I'm not sure a
future progressive WebP can
answer that, or progressive
jpg, but basically I think
that it's not a question of
image format because we have
progressive image formats, or
we can easily come up with,
like, the responsive image
container stuff.
We can easily--
it's a prototype, but it's not
complicated to get this done.
The problem is that currently
there are no fetching
mechanisms in place that can
download only the start of the
image for low resolution devices
and download the
entire image for high resolution
devices that have
the bandwidth and have the
capability to decode it.
And I think that getting the
fetching mechanism in place
would be an enabler for such
optimization, for such formats
to be useful.
MARCUS: So I want to quickly
get [INAUDIBLE]
thoughts on all this.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: So I was going
back to the original
question, I think we're never
going to be able to just have
one image solution, because you
don't have the same image
if your device is this
big versus if your
image is this big.
For those listening audio, you
don't want to have the same
image if you have
a 20 inch image
versus a half inch image.
ANNE ROBINSON: But we actually
could do that, right?
Because with a progressive jpg,
you can have a variable
number of scans.
And the scans are of
increasing quality.
So you could have, say, 40.
Let's expand our minds
about this.
Is that correct?
We could--
MARCUS: If you're getting into
40 times bigger zone, you will
get color distortion.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1:
I'm not talking
about the art direction.
If you're going to--
ANNE ROBINSON: So putting the
art direction topic aside for
a second, you actually can have
a progressive jpg that
has a very small scan and then
a very high resolution.
So you can have a tiny image
that downloads very quickly.
And you can have a super
large HD image for--
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: Yeah, but I
think we can't put the art
direction aside because
we are serving so
many different devices.
So I think the answer to the
question is I don't think
serving one image will be the
solution in the end because we
are reaching such a
plethora of sizes.
MARCUS: I mean, we're going
to come to continue--
the next question is very
much related to this.
So I'm going to--
before I do that, I'm going
to queue up Kyle.
Kyle, do you have
a mic already?
Where is Kyle?
Oh sorry, Kyle Simpson.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1:
He's over there.
MARCUS: So I'm going
to queue of Kyle.
He's right there.
So Kyle, just a quick
question or comment.
AUDIENCE: So a lot of these
solutions seem to be some sort
of art direction centric, like
I want the best possible
images that can be there.
But responsive seems to respond
to, maybe the screen
size, maybe to the bandwidth,
but it doesn't seem to react
to the environment.
So if I start out loading a
Flickr page that the battery
power is at 50%, I've got plenty
of processing power.
But if I'm now at 2%, maybe
the device should start
choosing not to render
these higher things.
So can't we have solutions that
allow apps to respond to
more complex situations than
just the screen size?
MARCUS: So we're going to
cover that as well.
But somebody wants to make
a quick comment?
YAV: Just a quick comment.
That's something that certainly
should be possible
when we're talking about
resolution switching, when
we're not talking about things
that won't break the layout,
but just would give the user a
lower quality image when it
can't download the high
res quality image.
And this is something that
should be heuristically
possible with srcset.
So the browser in srcset,
basically, the spec contains
an asterisk saying eventually
the browser can do whatever
the hell you want.
So the browser can decide based
on user preference,
based on environment, based on
memory, to not download the
high res images but the
lower res ones.
MARCUS: So it's kind of a good
thing and a bad thing.
But it's a declarative model.
You're handing over control.
You're saying to the browser,
this is what I
got, deal with it.
Do it best for the user.
YAV: Yeah, I don't think this
should be something decided to
by the web developer because I
don't think they have this
kind of information.
We cannot have this kind of
information available to the
web developer.
This is something that should
be done by the browser with
the user preference.
MARCUS: So I'm going to be
moderator here and jump over
to the next question.
Because they are all
related anyway.
[INAUDIBLE]
Calvin [? Spillman ?].
Your question.
So [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I was basically
wondering about if
we are fighting a losing
battle by continually
generating all these different
image sizes and different
resolutions up front, when
there's constantly new
devices, constantly different
sizes, we're always going to
be constantly trying to catch
up and generating more and
more images, as opposed to
having some server side
solution that does it
dynamically and optimizes the
set of images we have.
MARCUS: So I think this ties in
kind of beautifully to the
stuff that John was presenting
before, and also to the
progressive jpg, to having
those multiple scans.
So John, with the kind of work
that you've been doing, what
are you using, what
are the numbers
basically telling you there?
JOHN MELLOR: So I guess
there's two
aspects to this question.
On the server side, sure, you
don't want the artist to be
manually saving out
like 20 different
versions of every image.
It's not scalable.
So I guess on the server side,
you kind of have to be, at the
moment, dynamically creating
these images by automatically
resizing them.
But then, I guess [INAUDIBLE]
as well, it would be nice if
there was only one image you
have to save, like you just
tell your Photoshop or
whatever, save out one
ultra-high resolution image,
and the [? bells ?] downloads
just to beginning of it, like
however much it needs.
ANNE ROBINSON: Yeah,
that's perfect.
I think that's the most
elegant solution.
I think that the second most
elegant solution is, like with
client hints and having the
server serve up different
resolutions, different versions
of the image.
But it has to be automatic.
We should not be creating x
number of images to serve to
different devices.
And we are fighting a losing
battle in that case.
YAV: I think the--
MARCUS: Quick audience, did
you have a question?
AUDIENCE: But if you have that
situation, aren't you going to
end up in the thing that
all the developers were
complaining about when they
operators started to compress
your image on the mobile
networks, and they said, just
get out of my way.
I don't want you to
touch my stuff.
If you've got some automated
system that sits between the
thing, you're creating that's
the same problem that, three
years ago, you were all
whingeing about.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: My thought
was that this would be, I
think it should be server side
so that the developer is
actually deciding what
you're sending over.
The browser should
not be altering
images, is my thought.
JOHN MELLOR: But the developer
doesn't know the bandwidth of
the client.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: No, I mean,
when we're all said and done,
when we have client hints, and
everything else, it should be
the server that's making the
20 images and serving the
correct image based on client
hints, or the source set, not
the browser that's taking the
image and deciding that the
upper left hand corner should
be shown instead of
the middle of it.
JOHN MELLOR: It seems a lot
easier for the browser to take
user's preference into
account, though.
If the user decides that--
they are roaming, or something,
and they only want
the resolution image, then do
you want, like, an extra
client hint, saying I'm roaming,
extra client hint
saying these kinds of things?
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: No, the
browser can say--
you can change, when you
have client hints--
Should we ask the question about
client hints that we're
going to ask later?
MARCUS: No, because I think we
are talking about, I don't
think we need to move to that
question yet because we are
kind of dealing with, or
discussing a very serious
problem, which is, A, how can
computers really decide this?
How do we set the break points,
or not even the break
points, but the, this looks
good here, so send
this, and so on.
So having that level of control,
which was as Steve
was saying before, that was
pissing people off,
developers, because it
didn't look good.
And to some degree, well
that's what we really
need to look at.
Can we computationally
do that?
And John's research seems to
suggest that it can because
you do get a, at least the user
gets the initial layout
with the nice images, or
beginnings of a nice image,
and then, from there, you start
progressively improving it.
So how much do you
need to push it?
And what does that mean
on the server?
It's kind of hard to know.
YAV: My opinion on this is that
basically you need all
solutions to be automizeable.
So you can do either dynamic, or
a build step, or something
on the server side that does all
the grunt work for you as
a developer.
But I don't think, at least,
we must have some solutions
that don't require it.
So--
MARCUS: So I've got two
questions from the floor.
I've got one from--
your name, sorry, OK.
Sorry, I thought you were
going to ask a question.
No problem.
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: So if we start
generating 20, 30 different
versions of files on the server
side and start doing
[? varied ?] client hint headers
or whatever, are we
going to have problems where
the edge caches just can't
keep all of these?
I mean, we're going to be
blowing out 20 different times
the number of files on
all the edge caches.
Are CDNs going to be useful
anymore that point?
How is it going to scale?
YAV: I think that since the
varied would work, since the
client hints is my one
hint per header.
So varied would work.
But I think the edge caches will
have to adapt to the new
reality of much more
images than before.
But since I don't think
this will be--
it may be exponential, but there
will be time to adapt, I
mean, as far as the
edge caches go.
That's my opinion.
MARCUS: Hang on, don't speak
without the mic.
So I was going to jump to--
I'll go to Matt.
I think you had a question.
No, you're good?
OK, cool.
So Peter, you're looking like
you want to say something.
PETER MILLER: Well, I mean, when
the original question was
first asked, the case that comes
to my mind is still the
art direction case.
Because it is very
important for
publications that I work on.
And the crop has to be right.
And that's why we do do
upfront generation.
We have picture editors.
And they are in charge of
saying, when this image is
displayed at this size, then
here's the crop I want.
But I've worked with content
management systems in the past
that would find that
given coordinates.
So yes, we can automatically
resize images dynamically.
But maybe we could allow picture
editors to dynamically
come in and draw some
coordinates for different use
cases and different contexts.
And about the question about
whether it's the browser that
decides it or it's the developer
that decides it,
absolutely, I think it
has to be the browser
that decides it.
It's not just the resolution
of the screen.
It's not just the size
It's not just the
battery power.
It's actually everything else
to do with what's rendering
that image element.
And it's not just the HTML.
It's the style sheet as well.
MARCUS: So this leads
beautifully the next question,
which is by Jeffrey
[? Sellman ?].
Is he here?
There he is.
AUDIENCE: Thank you.
So this is an annoying
theoretical purity question
supplied by the moderator.
And I have a complicated
relationship to it because,
since 1998, I've been beating
the drum for separation of
presentation and structure.
But I'm also a big supporter
of Matt, Marcus, and
[? Picture. ?]
Hey buddy.
Is it problematic that we
describe the presentation of
images in markup against our
typical mantra to separate
presentation from content.
And if so, does the
specification of a myriad of
sizes make this worse?
MARCUS: So we saw this.
Hopefully you had the same kind
of gut reaction when you
saw both srcset and picture,
when you saw the code up on
the screen, and you
kind of went--
really?
We have to type all those times
1, and times 2, and you
saw picture bloats all
over the place.
And it has media queries
in it as well.
So this goes straight to--
I know Jeffrey didn't ask the
question specifically.
But like you said, it's like
it's bad because we are
putting media queries
into our markup.
What can we do there?
Is there possible solutions?
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: So the
reason that there's a
difference between images and
background images is because
the image tag, img, is
a foreground image.
It's content--
versus all the design that
we have on the web page.
So yes, we do have
to keep it--
the image is actually content.
MARCUS: Right, but what about
the media query component?
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: The media
query should be--
I mean, that's why we're trying
to come up with all
these different solutions and
why the picture element, and
the srcset, looks so ugly.
And actually, why I like the
clown car technique because it
actually separates
out the content.
MARCUS: So just for people who
don't know the clown car
technique, just like a super,
super Twitter size?
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: OK,
three tweets.
It's basically, instead of
pulling in an image,
it pulls in an SVG.
And inside the SVG, that's
where all the
media queries are.
So it pulls in the correct image
based on the container
of the SVG.
And it works fairly well.
It's basically a stopgap
solution while we're trying to
figure out the correct
solution.
But the reason that I liked
the clown car technique is
because it actually separated
out content, from
presentation, from behavior,
from images.
PETER MILLER: I think it
absolutely is a problem that
we're defining the media
queries in the HTML.
I don't think it's a
problem of bloat.
That's fine.
I think we can give the HTML,
[? all ?] the sources of the
images, as I was
saying before.
But I think the problem is
illustrated in the case where,
let's say, on a 500 pixel wide
screen, virtual pixels, you
have an image at 100% width.
On a 700 pixel screen, you might
actually have that image
at 50% width because you've got
a second column come in.
And OK fine, when I'm writing
the HTML, maybe I'll
take that into mind.
But what if it's not an HTML
generation problem?
What if it's a render problem
where when the user's logged
in, then you have a sidebar.
But when they're
not, you don't.
In the CSS, I can have the
column at 50%, or 100% if it's
got a sibling with the
logged in sidebar.
But I'm going to want a
different image source to
apply to that element.
And that's why a technique that
takes into account the
actual width of the image
element, rather than the width
of the screen, I think is
absolutely essential.
And that's why I do you still
have a problem with the
picture element.
MARCUS: So I think
Yav will come in.
YAV: Yeah.
MARCUS: So this is alluding
leading to, some people might
have heard about element
queries, which are kind of
like CSS applied to a particular
container element.
And it's pretty cool.
PETER MILLER: It has
its problems.
MARCUS: It has its problems.
YAV: So actually there are
several questions here.
First, for the separation
of the content and the
presentation.
I think it's a problem.
I think that this is something
that can be resolved by drying
out the media queries out of
HTML and into some sort of a
media query variable.
MARCUS: So drying
out out being?
YAV: Don't repeat yourself.
Just basically creating
variables that say mobile, or
whatever that means, or
basically create named media
queries and use them instead
of the actual media queries
wherever you have media queries
in your markup, be it
picture, or external style
sheets, or in the CSS as well.
There is work in the CSS working
group regarding that.
I have been no idea when
it will go in.
But people are working on it.
And so regarding that, I think
that will resolve most of the
issues from this separation
of concerns point of view.
Regarding--
MARCUS: So hang on.
So a question I have is like,
OK, so picture is probably the
main offender here.
Should we even bother continuing
to work on it, in
that sense?
YAV: I don't think picture is
the most visible offender.
But again, there are
style sheets.
If I'll have my way, media
attributes will be everywhere,
which I probably won't have my
way, but I think that there
are a lot of resources
that can be
downloaded based on media.
And I think we need to have
some shortcut for media
queries that we don't have to
repeat them everywhere,
including in CSS because in CSS
we repeat them as well.
MARCUS: That's true.
YAV: And regarding the element
queries stuff, first of all,
I'd like to say that the main
advantage of the clown car
technique versus basically
anything else is that it
basically emulates
element queries.
The media queries there refer
to the viewport of the SVG,
not the viewport of
the document.
So while it creates some delay
in download, it's sometimes
necessary to, I mean, there are
cases where it's useful,
extremely useful.
But the problem with element
queries is that you cannot
start downloading the resource
before you have layout, which
means you add a significant
delay to the
the entire page load.
MARCUS: So Anne, do you have
any comments about that?
ANNE ROBINSON: I mean,
yeah, I'm still a fan
of progressive jpgs.
And I think that--
[LAUGHTER]
ANNE ROBINSON: No I think that
there's definitely--
the art direction
case, it doesn't
really handle, obviously.
But I don't think that we should
forget about it as a
file format that we
might explore.
And we often do forget about
progressive jpgs.
I think we forgot about
progressive jpgs
for, like, 10 years.
We just--
MARCUS: So what is the reason
we forgot about them?
What browser doesn't really
support them well?
ANNE ROBINSON: Oh.
I mean, I think that in general,
there's pretty good
browser support.
I think that the reason browsers
don't support them is
because we stopped using them.
And I think we stopped using
them because things changed.
We had faster connections.
But then things kind of reverted
with mobile, and we
went back to where we were,
where speed turned out to be
an issue again.
So yeah.
MARCUS: Cool.
ANNE ROBINSON: That's it.
MARCUS: So there's one question
from the audience.
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: It sounds like the
best solutions for a
[? pictured ?] element is,
basically, to move
the rules to CSS.
You can go back to regular img
and have something that says,
in CSS, for all images which
have a path that looks like
this, then apply these rules
to add that 2x to the path.
That's largely to move the more
presentational parts of
it to the CSS while keeping
the content, namely, the
fallback image, in the HTML.
And it can do something like a
regex to not have to write
this 2x, that 2x, something else
2x, for 2x versions of
every single image you have.
MARCUS: So--
AUDIENCE: And you could sort
of do this right now using
attribute selectors
and the img tag.
MARCUS: Using what selectors?
AUDIENCE: You can sort
of do this now
using attribute selectors.
MARCUS: Attribute selectors.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but once
per [? src ?],
which would be annoying.
MARCUS: Right, so yeah,
so it's kind of
like a mix of things.
So I'm sure one of these other
guys will be able to talk
about the concerns there.
I can give a little bit.
It's like, some of the main
problem that we're trying to
solve with responsive images
as a whole is integrating
nicely into how browsers load
images performance wise.
So to block and wait for a style
sheet to download that
will give you the instructions
to then be able to fetch the
files that you need will
probably cause issues.
Part of the stuff that Yav was
talking about before about
these CSS-based variables that
you can put in is that you
would need to insert them at the
top of the document inline
so then they would actually
parse before anything else.
So there's like big performance
issues with all this.
So it's a cool solution.
And I'm not saying that it
wouldn't work, but it's like
working out how all the dynamics
work there, within
the browser, is pretty crazy.
Does anyone want to add?
Yav probably [INAUDIBLE].
YAV: I just want to add to it
it's basically violating the
separation of concerns from the
other side of the spectrum.
Basically, your content is now
part of your presentation, in
a way, because the content
URLs rely on the CSS.
So you would have to either--
I mean, for CSS caching,
content images
tend to change often.
Everything that's in CSS usually
changes, I mean, less
often than that.
So it can be cached
for a long while.
So it violates the layers,
as far as I'm
concerned, in a way.
MARCUS: So let's take that
one [INAUDIBLE].
So I've got another question
from the audience.
Another one from-- oh, so
I've got a couple here.
I'm going to go there first.
And then we'll bounce to, sorry,
you already have the
mic, so go ahead.
And then I'll bounce to.
AUDIENCE: This is real quick.
Just to counteract that.
[? You ?] say if you need to
download the CSS first in
order to display the image, but
[? if ?] the CSS modifies
the size of the image, which
could modify the art direction
and the actual one
that you want to
use, isn't that important?
MARCUS: It is.
But like I said, it's all like
a trades and balances kind of
things because you really--
we are trying to keep the
performance high.
So there is going to be a
penalty for everything.
So where you defer, like Yav was
saying, the separations a
concern, it's going to have
issues with how the images are
loaded and when.
So if the things have
to be deferred, then
you might defer layout.
And that's going to impact the
user perception of whatever
application you're
trying to run.
So again, we need to test
a lot of this stuff.
We don't know.
It's still like, even though
we've been talking about it,
now it's like really time
to start testing.
[? So ?].
AUDIENCE: I guess I just
had more of a direct
question for Peter.
Sorry to put you on the spot.
But given the kind of art
direction perspective, I was
wondering if you could talk a
little bit about, from your
standpoint, what is best
practice right now, given that
it's not all just programmers
trying to do stuff in an
automated fashion.
Because every time I've tried
to do that, I fail.
And the art director looks at me
and is like, no, we need to
crop it this way instead.
MARCUS: So I want
to answer that.
But I think this is a great
question because it's really
about what should developers
be doing today?
And I think, like, John
has some ideas.
Anne's already talked about,
let's try out these
progressive jpgs.
And Yav and I have kind of been
working on the standards
trying to look forward.
[INAUDIBLE]
been kind of experimenting with
the clown car technique.
So by all means--
so we have five minutes.
So like one minute each, what
can developers do today,
starting with Peter?
PETER MILLER: OK, well here's
what we're doing we're sending
and lots of the jpg sources
into the HTML as JSON and
storing it on a data
attribute.
We've got JavaScript running
that will, after the CSS has
evaluated the layout, will
pick the right source and
apply a non-resized change.
Yeah, the performance isn't
great for that.
But to answer a little of what
Yav was saying, that I think
that having a default source
there, low-res, your best
guess, is, I think, an OK way
to go for we have now.
MARCUS: OK.
Anne, what do you recommend
for developers?
ANNE ROBINSON: I mean, I think
that, yeah, what we have now
is a bunch of hacks, right?
That's what we have.
I think that we should
try and focus.
I love that we're doing this.
And we're, actually, I think
what we're talking about are
big wins and solutions for
responsive images.
And I think we should really
be forward thinking and not
forget all of the different
options, and all of our
different paths, and
explore then all.
MARCUS: It's great.
YAV: I think that current all
current hacks have performance
trade offs.
All current hacks, basically,
you're deferring the loading
of the image to a later time
in order to download the
appropriate one.
I think that the things
will look up soon.
That things will get better soon
with-- there's currently
work in the responsive images
community group on an x
picture [INAUDIBLE]
that's will use--
MARCUS: [? components ?].
YAV: That uses web components
in order to emulate picture.
It won't work with a preloader,
but assuming if you
don't have any blocking scripts
at the page's top, it
should have similar performance
characteristics as image.
So current hacks all
have problems.
Future hacks will get better.
And hopefully, then
there is a srcset,
hopefully it will ship--
MARCUS: Soon enough.
YAV: In a release build
soon enough.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: So I guess
the question is, what
developer should be doing now,
and what developer should be
do now is being concerned about
what they're sending
over the wires and making sure
they're not sending huge
assets to limited bandwidth
devices.
And in terms of what we should
be doing, or the spec authors
should be doing is, we should
also, I think, what I haven't
heard, and I just thought of
while I was on stage, so I
don't know, maybe it has been,
there's some CSS, there's the
image element you can clip
and certain areas.
So maybe figuring out a way to
do that on the back end, or
through client hints, so that
you're actually just
downloading based on that
instead of downloading the
whole image.
MARCUS: Right, so just expanding
on that one, so it's
basically just taking, you
have your normal image.
And then you select the area
that you want to crop out.
And basically, you just
crop it out with CSS.
It's a good way of doing
art direction.
And it fits quite well with
compressive images as well.
JOHN MELLOR: So I'll give
several answers.
For CSS, you can just use media
queries to switch out
the right image.
It's in a better state
these days.
For HTML, there's three
different things.
For fixed-size images, we're
just switching basically the
device-pixel ratio.
Compressive images, like serving
a double sized, but
highly compressed image,
is reasonable.
Srcset would be nice, but only
once browsers support it.
For viewport-based switching,
where you need to take into
account flexible images, I think
the best solution these
days is to load a very low
quality placeholder which is
directly reference
in your HTML.
And then, later on, using
JavaScript, you swap it out
with am appropriate resolution
image based on the actual
image size, or.
MARCUS: Or would you
use the classic--
[INAUDIBLE].
But there about like there
low source, low src
attribute on HTML?
JOHN MELLOR: I'd just use src.
So put the low quality one on
src, and use JavaScript to
replace that with a better
quality one once you've loaded
that in the background.
So you get kind of like this
progressive thing where the
page loads in low quality
quickly and gradually becomes
higher quality.
So I actually released a library
for this yesterday.
It's on [?
Github.com/JohnM
allor/respswap.js ?].
Very early stages.
Finally, for art direction,
where you actually need a
different image, rather than
just a different resolution of
the same image, you can't load
a low quality place holder
because you don't know what
image it's going to be.
And so for that, you've can
use something like picture
fill, or whatever.
But don't use picture fill
for viewport switching.
MARCUS: So picture fill, just
for people who don't know what
that is. picture fill is, you
can Google it, you'll find it
pretty quick.
And it's basically the similar
syntax to the picture element
but done with divs and
spans or something.
But it basically works.
JOHN MELLOR: But the downside is
that the images don't load
until the page is fully finished
loading, and you've
reached DOM content loaded.
And so your images will start
loading much later then if
you've got a placeholder
or something.
YAV: And just to emphasize on
that, [? picture fill ?]
should be used for art
direction and not for
resolution switching.
FEMALE SPEAKER 1: I'd like
to add one comment.
Because the picture fill, the
reason that it's an issue is
because it's on DOM
content loaded.
We should make on DOM content
loaded much faster.
It shouldn't be taking 10
seconds to download your page.
And that's one thing we should
definitely work on.
MARCUS: So I think that one,
I think, will hopefully be
covered in one of the other
sessions because it's part of
the performance thing.
So there is work around that
that we would basically say.
And I'm just wrapping up
here for the session.
But it basically would just
say, my page is ready now.
So, as an author, you say,
forget DOM content loaded.
But page is done.
And you sent, like, a fake DOM
content loaded event that
indicates to the browser, now
I'm ready to do other stuff.
So please to join me in thanking
the panel here.
[APPLAUSE]