NATASHA ROONEY: Thank
you so much.
So yeah, we have the exciting
topic of payments left for
this afternoon.
I'm sorry, but it's one of
these things that is--
yeah, I know.
Usually at home, actually, when
we have the last panel,
I'd say, look, I'm sorry for
standing in the way of you
guys and the pub.
But we don't really have the pub
here, so I'm sorry we're
standing in front of you
guys and dinner.
But there is decent beer,
so I suppose that's OK.
And now I'm starting
to sound like an
alcoholic Brit, so sorry.
OK, let's move on.
So payments are very,
very important.
I've been speaking a lot with
the W3C people, a lot of
people that are involved
in standardization.
And we all want to make the web
better, and that's fantastic.
But one of the problems
is the money needs
to come from somewhere.
We need the funding to
do the cool things
that we want to do.
So unfortunately, this is just
something that we have to go
and have a chat about.
And if you're really into it,
then great because there's a
lot of money to be
made out of it.
So cool.
Panelists, we've got Manu
Sporny on my left.
He sits in the W3C and the IETF
doing a lot of work on
standardization on payments
right now and founder of
Digital Bazaar.
Ricardo, Ricardo from
Telefonica, Ricardo Varela,
head honcho of the BlueVia
Change to Mobile work and did
some stuff on WAC before then.
Rob Grimshaw, Managing Director
of the Financial
Times is sitting to my right
here, so known for FT's
pioneering payment models.
[INAUDIBLE]
a lot of questions for you.
Kumar McMillan right at the
end there from Mozilla,
working on a lot of things.
I'm sure you do a lot of stuff
with mozPay and Firefox
Marketplace.
Excellent.
And Cyndy over here does a lot
of work in Google with Google
Wallet and the magic
requestAutocomplete, which I'm
sure will come up today.
So Manu is speaking
for us today.
So I'm driver of the slides.
So--
MANU SPORNY: Driver
of the slides.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah, I
get all the good jobs.
Cool.
So take it away.
MANU SPORNY: All right, so this
panel is kind of titled
payments, but I think it's
far deeper than that.
I think, when we think payments,
we think getting
payment from customer
to the vendor.
We don't think about, for
example, 30% of the people in
the United States that currently
don't have a bank
account that have no
way of saving.
In other nations, it's
even worse than that.
It can be up to 70% of the
population that has no way of
saving money, putting money
aside, for school, for food,
things of that nature.
So while we're talking about
web payments, I think that
there's a far deeper and more
important story here.
And that is figuring out a way
to get the web to help people
that can't save money, that
don't live in countries where
putting money in a bank is a
feasible solution for them.
So this isn't just about
paying for products.
While that's important for all
of us, this isn't just a first
world problem.
It's a problem for people
all around the world.
So as Natasha said, I am the W3C
chair for the web payments
group right now.
I also deal quite a bit with
linked data, microformats,
microdata, RDFa, JSON-LD,
things like that.
And I also deal quite a bit with
identity and security,
both at the IETF and the W3C.
And basically, what that means
is I get to see a lot of
different technologies
come by these groups.
And what we're trying to do is
we're trying to pick and
choose which technologies will
probably be good candidates
for integrating into the core
of the web's architecture.
Until now, we really haven't had
a core way of transferring
value around the web, right?
I mean the thing that we look
at to spend money on the web
right now are to move money back
and forth are things like
credit cards and ACH, and that's
just not cool anymore.
We have to have a
better solution.
And so I spend a lot of time
kind of championing
technologies, a lot of the
technologies that our
panelists are working
on currently.
So we've got a problem
on the web, right?
And that's sending and receiving
money is typically
proprietary.
It's very slow.
It's insecure.
And it is actively hostile
to innovation.
That's the reason that we
don't have very many
innovative companies in
the payment space.
You can argue that we do, and
I hope that we do get into
that argument on this panel.
But really, when it comes to
making money on the web, many
of us make--
our jobs are such that we get
paid to work on the web, but
some people don't have the
benefit of working for a large
company like Google
or Microsoft that
can cover their expenses.
They would like to have
a more direct
relationship with their customers.
And right now, content
monetization on the web is
really hard.
It's really expensive,
especially if you're a merchant.
You pay thousands of dollars in
fees just for the right to
process credit cards.
And the reason that is partially
is because a lot of
the payment tech that we use
today on the web was invented
in the '70s.
It's the ACH Automated Clearing
House system.
It's credit cards.
All this stuff is really, really
old legacy stuff that
predates the web by
a large degree.
So I guess it would be good to
kind of take a look at some of
the use cases that we're trying
to address, right?
Let's ground this discussion.
Payment for physical goods
today is actually--
we do a pretty decent job
at it on the web, right?
I mean, we've got like things
like Google Wallet and PayPal
that you can use to
pay for goods.
We get the goods.
Everyone's kind of
happy, right?
But when you look at the
merchant side of this,
creating a merchant account to
be able to process credit
cards is very expensive.
There are a lot of fees
attached to it.
Even when you have a really
good merchant provider,
payment provider, it's still
an awful process for folks
that are kind of mom and
pop shops that try to
set up on the web.
You're usually locked into
a payment processor
when you pick them.
There's no such thing as data
portability, or if there is,
it's really kind of terrible.
Doing things like in-app
payments right now, you're
usually tied to a particular app
store of some kind, either
the iTunes Store or the
Google Play Store
or things like that.
And doing things like crowd
funding and crowd loaning on
yourself or by yourself instead
of going through
Kickstarter, which takes 10%
of the money that you make.
You can't do that, right?
And these are things that at
least some of us in the web
payments group think should be
fundamental rights, not just
in the US, but around
the world.
You should be able to be in
charge of your own financial
well-being.
So I guess that the core here
that we're talking about at
this panel is three different
categories of things, three
different ways that we spend
money on the web, three
different ways of
raising money.
And the first one is kind of
the old money, the popular
proprietary category, right?
This is most of the payment
services that
we have right now.
And this is absolutely not a
slam to any of the companies
that are on this slide.
These companies solve a very
important problem, which is it
really sucks to do transactions
over the web
using your credit
card and ACH.
So we've got PayPal, Amazon
Payments, Google Wallet, even
the new poster children for
really cool payment startups,
like Stripe, Square,
[? Paymentwall, ?]
and sites like Kickstarter,
Indiegogo, and Crowdtilt,
these are all based on this
really horrible old legacy
system, right?
There are tons and tons of
problems that we'll go into
during the discussion today.
So that's kind of the
first category.
This is what's kind of
popular right now.
The next category is
online app stores.
So these are other types of
kind of proprietary silos.
They lock you in Apple,
the Apple iTunes
store, the Apple store.
Facebook credits, which used
to exist when these slides
were made, but doesn't
exist anymore.
They were just shut down
a little while ago.
The Windows Store, Google Play,
these are all kind of
examples of stores that give
really great kind of user
experiences, but you're kind of
locked into them when you
use them, right?
There's the idea of having this
open app marketplace, has
been talked about, and luckily
for us, I think, Mozilla has
been doing some really great
work in this area, making it
so that you can sell web
apps from any website.
You don't have to go through
an app store
of one kind or another.
And so the final category, I
think, is predominantly what
I'm really excited about.
This is what gives me hope.
And so the last bit are these
Open Web payment solutions.
Finally, people are starting
to work on things that fit
very nicely with the web.
They don't try and shim the
old 1970s credit card
architecture into the web.
They are a new way of looking at
payments on the web, where
payments are instantaneous,
there's a lot of rich metadata
that goes with it.
So FirefoxOS is doing
a great job with
their marketplace stuff.
We have PaySwarm, which is the
first universal payment
standard for the web.
Bitcoin, I'm sure many of you
have heard of Bitcoin.
How many of you have
heard of Ripple?
Wow.
I was just at a banking
conference last week and half
the bankers raised
their hands.
So that's surprising.
That never happens.
So anyway, Ripple was built
by the Bitcoin folks.
It's kind of a better
version of Bitcoin.
But these there all really cool
technologies that are
native to the web that
are really going to
shake things up.
I think they're really going
to finally bring kind of
payments into the modern age.
So I guess the goal here, what
we're trying to do, is we're
trying to integrate open payment
technology into the
core architecture of the web.
We did this for communication
with email.
Email's got protocols.
The reason that it's so easy
to type in a person's email
address and send a message
halfway around the world is
there's a whole set of
protocols around it.
No such thing exists for
payments on the web.
It's just starting with that
kind of Bitcoin and Ripple
coming along.
But we really need
to work on it.
And that's what we focus
on at the web payments
group, at the W3C.
Most of the panel members
here are a part of the
web payments group.
It's completely open.
We really need developers
to join.
So if you're interested in any
of the stuff that you hear on
the panel today, please join.
Jump onto the group and join.
If you just Google
web payments W3C.
And if you want to talk about
this stuff, pull me aside and
introduce yourself.
I love talking about
this stuff.
So please, at the party after
this, pull me aside if you're
interested in any of the stuff
that you hear on the panel, as
well as the rest of the
panelists here.
So quickly in closing, there's
a whole bunch of contact info
for you to get in touch if
you're interested in payments
or interested in actually taking
part in this work.
There's a lot of good that
you can do here.
This is world-changing stuff.
Twitter, G+ handle email, and
the slides are posted up
there, payswarm.com/slides.
So without further ado, let's
get into the discussion.
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
[APPLAUSE]
NATASHA ROONEY: So thank you
very much for that, Manu.
And with that, like you said,
we'll kick off with the first
question, which comes
from Ada Edwards.
I believe you're reading
out this one.
ADA EDWARDS: [INAUDIBLE].
NATASHA ROONEY: Oh, actually,
could we just wait for a mic?
Thanks.
ADA EDWARDS: So I have
a question from a
certain Andrew [? Bet. ?]
[INAUDIBLE]
a prepaid account with a
merchant to fund micropayments
is free money for
the merchant.
Why would they kill the golden
goose by moving to instant
micropayments?
MANU SPORNY: So I can jump in.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah,
go for it.
MANU SPORNY: I don't know if I
quite agree with the question,
meaning that I think it's
shortsighted for any merchant
to think of it as-- anybody
that's not large.
So Google can think
in that way.
Google can say, I'm going to
require someone to prefund an
account, and then across all the
Google properties, you can
buy things.
Your mom and pop web store,
someone doing like a niche
site, is never going to
be able to do that.
Or if they're going to do that,
they're going to lose
quite a bit of business.
Because I guess ThemeForest is
a great example of this.
They require you to put in
like $5 or $10, but their
themes cost $1.24.
And you have to kind of be--
at least, I was when I bought
one of the themes off them.
I was pretty desperate.
I was really looking
for a theme.
I was under a deadline.
I was like, fine.
Here's $5.
And a lot of my money is kind
of sitting there still.
So I'm a bit ticked at
them for that, right?
I wish I could have just gone to
the site, spent $1.24, and
gone somewhere else.
And I think that is the model
that we really should be
shooting for on the web.
You should be able to go to a
site, just click a Buy button.
You don't have to sign
up for an account.
You don't have to put in your
credit card information.
Just click Buy.
The browser takes care of
the vast majority of
the payment for you.
It's ease of use.
And I think micropayments is
kind of a part of that.
You don't want to be charging
people like $0.02 or $0.03 at
a time, but the idea that you
should be able to do a $1.25
transaction I don't
think is crazy.
I think we should be able
to do that on the web.
NATASHA ROONEY: Does anybody
feel any differently
regarding--
RICARDO VARELA: I was actually
going to comment one thing.
So first, actually, if I could
do a bit of a survey, how many
people actually take payments
on the web?
How many people have a product
that actually takes payment?
[INAUDIBLE]
one.
And regarding the Ripple
question, how many people know
Bitcoin, for example?
Everybody.
[INAUDIBLE].
Good.
So the thing that I was going to
mention is that one of the
problems that we have
had with payments--
I've been working in
payments for years.
And when I got in, I worked
with mobile operators.
Which, if they're good at
something, is basically at
taking your money, as
you probably know.
So has anybody never
received a charge
from a mobile operator?
The bill always gets
there, right?
And I thought that actually we
had our staff better sorted
out than when I actually
got there.
And in payments, the main
problem is a domain-specific
problem, and it's a heavily
regulated domain as well.
So, for example, why would
somebody want to preload an
account and then take your money
from there and actually
make that charge of fees
in that transaction?
Because there are different
roles in payments.
So actually, when a
payment occurs, it
hasn't really occurred.
It occurs in different phases.
So when you, for example, pay
something with a credit card,
that money's not yet in
the merchant account.
That money has got to go from
bank to bank, normally through
a series, if not only
one, clearinghouses.
And then that ends up
in the other bank.
So basically, that means
that that bank hasn't
actually got paid.
There's actually a risk that
that money never gets paid.
And that is what normally the
issuer bank calls bad debt.
So when you, for example, prepay
an account, what that
merchant that acquiring in that
case is actually trying
to do is reduce their
bad debt problem.
They're trying to say,
I've got the funds.
So if actually this transaction
occurs, I'm going
to automatically pay myself.
Thank you very much.
So that actually occurs whenever
two parties in a
transaction don't have trust
in between them.
And this is a concept that I
suppose we'll go back and back
again in the panel because
payments is all about trust.
If I actually emailed you and
tell you, would you lend me
$20, and you actually give me
$20, that is actually a
transaction that has occurred.
Maybe I don't even have my
money, but you've promised me
that you're going
to pay me $20.
Then I get my $20.
At some point, I may pay
you back or not.
You never know.
So that is [? actionary ?]
transaction.
That actually happens.
So the concept of you pay
me, the concept of you
establishing my identity via
receiving an email from me,
which by the way is not
something that you should
trust probably--
SMTP is not the most secure
thing in the world--
those things are what actually
happens in payments.
And I think we still don't have
a full solution to model
all that complexity technically
in the web.
And that's one of the products
we're trying to deal with.
NATASHA ROONEY: I think I
actually owe Andrew [? Bet ?]
$20, so we'll see if he does
or does not get that money.
So we actually have a question
from the floor.
So Alex Sexton, [INAUDIBLE]
over there guys.
ALEX SEXTON: Hello.
Full disclosure, Stripe
employee.
NATASHA ROONEY: Oh, actually,
for the floor, do you mind
just explaining what Stripe
is, just in case?
ALEX SEXTON: Stripe is a company
that currently does
payments for the web.
So I think we're in the
first slide along
with many other companies.
So I think me and my friends
would all agree that stuff
like Ripple and Bitcoin is
really cool and totally this
cool, federated way
of doing payments.
But the bootstrapping
of that system is
the blocker, I think.
So how do you get my
parents to be able
to deal with Bitcoin?
You're talking about,
I don't want to
sign up for an account.
I don't want to do any
of this stuff.
I just want to hit this button,
and money changes
hands, and there aren't any
of these old systems.
So how do you rewire people's
brains to make this much more
complicated system to
them something that
makes sense at all?
MANU SPORNY: I think the short
answer is ease of use, right?
I mean that is the killer app
for all of these payment
technologies, is the ability to
just go to any site, click
the Buy Now button, be shown
what you're going to buy, and
that's it, right?
And it doesn't matter if you're
using Google Wallet.
It doesn't matter if
you're using Stripe
or Paypal or anything.
They're all speaking a fairly
similar payments protocol.
This is kind of what PaySwarm,
that universal payment
standard, is designed to do.
The idea here is that you have
a common payments protocol
that all of the sites use.
So it's open, non-proprietary,
W3C standard.
And then you can
choose, right?
You can pick and choose who's
going to process your payments
for you, if it's going to be
your bank, or if it's going to
be Google Wallet, or if it's
going to be PayPal.
And then the merchant can choose
whoever they want to.
So I think the way that you
bootstrap this stuff is one,
through ease of use, and then
the second thing is you have
to somehow convince vendors
that this is worth doing.
And I think that's going to be
incredibly difficult to do if
Google Wallet, Stripe,
PayPal, don't join
onto the work, right?
If they continue to do the
proprietary stuff.
NATASHA ROONEY: We'll take one
more comment from Rob, and
then we'll--
ROB GRIMSHAW: I do agree,
actually, with the point of
the question.
Things like Bitcoin, they're
wonderful ideas.
But these things only really
thrive if they're starting
from scratch.
I mean, if you do it in a market
like somewhere like
developing countries like
Kenya or whatever, then
actually you can make something
happen very quickly.
So you've got a system like
Empasa with 17 million users.
But mostly, these people
never had a bank
account in their lives.
So they just accept it as
this is what it is.
For most of the developed
markets that we're dealing
with, on a day to day basis,
is a merchant like the FT.
All these people have got their
money in existing bank
accounts stuck in this
1970s system.
And it's not going to
come out quickly.
So for me, the practical
solutions are about mitigating
that existing system of making
it to something which is at
least some way practical from a
web payments point of view,
rather than thinking about how
we can start again through
some of these ideas, which are
wonderful, but to some extent
utopian from the perspective
of today's business.
MANU SPORNY: Just quickly,
Ripple's whole business plan
is to get banks [INAUDIBLE].
NATASHA ROONEY: We'll get to--
yeah, we'll come to Ripple in
the next couple of questions.
But interesting to what Rob
said, I think one of the next
questions is going to make you
touch on those utopian
viewpoints a little bit.
So Teddy Condo, I think, has the
next question for us here.
Thank you.
TEDDY CONDO: So this question
kind of strikes close to home
because I worked in publishing
and media for a good majority
of my career.
And I don't know if we'll have
an answer to it in this forum
because it's a topic that
has fundamental
problems of his own.
However, I'll add a bit to it,
as well as read the question.
What payment model is the one
that will finally make quote,
unquote, "old media" profitable
enough online, and
how soon can we get to that?
And furthermore, do you know
of any media venues,
publishing houses, that are
doing this correctly and are
actually profitable through
a payment model online?
RICARDO VARELA: Well, I think,
Rob, this kind of fits in--
ROB GRIMSHAW: We've done it.
It's fine.
NATASHA ROONEY: So explain
it to us, Rob.
What's it all about?
ROB GRIMSHAW: Well, the sort of
key thing is actually to be
bold enough to charge
for your product.
And actually, the world
is prepared to
pay for great content.
And I think we've established
that.
Quite successfully over the past
five years, we've really
pursued this policy of becoming
a company that
generates the majority of its
money from content rather from
advertising.
If you look at ft.com's
finances right now, we
generate in excess of 70% of
our revenues from content,
i.e., subscriptions, of the
vast majority of that page
digitally through our
subscriptions.
And that is not an indication
that we lost all our
advertising revenue.
In fact, our advertising grew
over the period of time that
we grew our subscriptions
business.
It's a sign that, actually, if
you have the right offering,
and you do work hard on the
payment side, you can build a
very successful business around
quality content online.
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
We've got a couple of questions
from the floor.
So Ally, if you want
to raise your hand.
Oh, sorry.
ALLY: It's kind of off topic now
because I wanted to speak
actually about the last topic.
Is it OK to go back to that, or
would you rather continue
moving forward?
I guess what I was thinking was
we mentioned, like with
the problem with more widespread
adoption of Bitcoin
being ease of use.
And I just had a gut reaction to
disagree with that because
I think that a much bigger
issue with it, especially
among an older crowd, has to
do with trust issues and
feeling that they can trust
these different sources.
And that was just kind of what
I wanted to bring up, and I'm
wondering kind of how you
address that, and how you make
those older people feel
more comfortable with
these payment options.
CYNDY LOBB: I'm not sure that
they'll ever be comfortable
with them, honestly.
I mean, look at the
supermarket.
When you're standing at the
supermarket, how many older
people use debit cards,
and how many are
still writing checks?
So it might be that that user
behavior is so divergent that
they won't get there, but that
doesn't mean that we should
not continue to push
the envelope.
Like I do believe that Bitcoin
is going to be really
challenging.
I do believe that from a
usability perspective, even
when I read up on it, and
there's big warnings.
Keep your wallet offline.
I was like, whoa, you know?
And I'm a tech person, right?
So the lay person is going to
read that one line that's
right on the Bitcoin website,
and they're going to run.
They're going to run as
fast as they can.
So it's a ver--
this is a social issue as much
as it's a payments issue, and
it's a trust issue.
So payments is that complex
ecosystem of a lot of
different players.
And trying to make everyone
happy is very challenging.
ROB GRIMSHAW: We do live in a
period where the price of gold
is at an all-time high, mainly
because people don't trust
currencies full stop, let alone
new ideas like Bitcoin.
And this is a really difficult,
complex issue for
societies and economies as a
whole, which people have been
wrestling with for hundreds
of years.
And just kind of introducing
something new into that is not
something that happens
in a couple of months
or a couple of years.
It can take decades, hundreds of
years, to really establish
a new currency properly.
RICARDO VARELA: Also--
sorry, was going to comment
that actually, in payments
recently, we've been actually
talking about how this whole
payments on the web thing should
really be a bit more--
well, some of us think that
this should be more like a
two-face approach.
Essentially, there's no open
technology to basically the
payments on the web
at the moment.
And there's also the whole
virtual currency thing, which
at some point may arrive.
And actually, I think there
will be even government
initiatives to this because
there's lots of benefits about
issuing currency that
is not physical.
But until that moment happens,
basically, that doesn't mean
that you cannot start with the
first part of it, which is
the, OK, how about we have open
technology to do those
payments on the web?
Because sometimes, and we have
that thing in W3C where we
basically go into inventing
problems that you cannot
really solve, not even in
the existent system,
[? emerging ?] on
the new system.
So we try to first have a
system, and then we try to add
things like virtual
currencies on it.
NATASHA ROONEY: So this goes
into the third question, which
came from--
actually, Manu, I believe this
is one of the questions that
you originally asked, so I will
ask it for you, which
actually goes back to the
Bitcoin and Ripple question,
which is do they fit into the
plan for web-based payments,
and should they be included as
payment options, or should
they remain on the periphery?
But it seems like what Ricardo
is talking about now is
they're already being considered
as being wrapped
into the standards.
MANU SPORNY: Yeah, and I really
asked that question
because I was more interested
in the answer from the
panelists, right?
And I wanted to be a bit more
pointed with the question.
Are there definite plans to
integrate alternative
currencies into product lines
like Google Wallet?
Would Google Wallet
ever consider
adding Bitcoin or Ripple?
Would Mozilla consider putting
a Bitcoin wallet or just some
kind of, even a USD wallet,
directly into the browser, so
that when you download a
browser, you've got preloaded
$10 that you can spend
online with it.
You go to a website.
You click Buy Now.
And the payment's made.
It's instantaneous.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah.
That's actually a quite
interesting question.
So like Manu said at the
beginning, lots of us are
involved in this
payments stuff.
And Ricardo and I from the
operator's space, but Kumar
and Mozilla have taken a little
bit of a different
approach to this, where they
have said, we don't care who
the payment provider
is, right?
We're just giving you the option
to pay, which is a very
different stance
in this space.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Yeah.
I mean, the thing with Bitcoin
is you can already pay with
Bitcoin on the web.
There's already web-based
wallets.
And so--
I mean, Mozilla's mozPay API,
which I think you're referring
to, is just one of the ways
you can pay in FirefoxOS.
It's not the only way.
So any app in FirefoxOS can
take the Bitcoin payments.
They would just need the
JavaScript to do it.
They would need the online
wallet in order to do it.
So it would just work.
But yeah, as far as mozPay, a
lot of people are interested
in incorporating Bitcoin.
It's already being asked
by a lot of people.
They want to see that as a
way to buy apps in the
marketplace, for sure.
Whether or not it will
happen, I don't know.
Because it is tough.
There's a lot of challenges.
RICARDO VARELA: While we are at
it, actually, so that you
get some of the data that we
wanted to get, how many people
here actually own Bitcoin
of any kind?
Because, I mean, we're like
the geekest of the geeks.
Everybody here should
have Bitcoin.
How many people have
actually done a
transaction with Bitcoin?
OK.
And how many people, when they
bought Bitcoin, actually when
you mean you have Bitcoin,
you bought it either in
[INAUDIBLE]
or one of those, basically
the big exchanges?
How many people are [INAUDIBLE],
actually?
OK, then you use a
smaller exchange.
Woohoo.
OK.
This thing's working.
ROB GRIMSHAW: How many people
have lost their wallet and
lost over $10 to $15?
There's the problem right there,
at least with Bitcoin.
NATASHA ROONEY: Cool.
Can we throw some questions
to the floor?
I think Marcus has got a
question at the front.
This is quite a contentious
topic, so if you guys want to
vote on the on-slide tool,
that would be great.
Because it's a strange one,
where we'd like a little bit
more developer feedback on how
people are feeling about
particular payment methods.
So Marcus, please.
MARCUS: OK, this one.
Sorry.
So Manu started the discussion
kind of talking about people
that are not in the old system,
so they're still using
real money, so paper money.
So one thing to notice, like
other people don't want to
move to digital money, even if
they now need to or if they
had to because they want
to buy a service.
How would they enter this
digital economy?
You haven't really
touched on that.
MANU SPORNY: Mobile devices.
[INAUDIBLE]
is completely mobile-based.
Mobile devices are basically the
way that a lot of people
in emerging nations are getting
access to the web.
And I mean, they have access to
the largest communication
network that mankind
has ever known.
And if we build a financial
protocol into
that, that's huge.
That's a really big thing.
MARCUS: You're basically
converting telcos into banks.
MANU SPORNY: Hopefully it's
going to be telcos and the
banks and companies like
Google and PayPal.
Everyone would have a level
playing field to effectively
be a financial institution
to these people.
RICARDO VARELA: So we know,
for example, in Europe,
there's actually a green paper
that's being discussed at the
moment in the European Union
regarding what is the role of
actually telcos regarding the
whole payments industry.
This is to regulate, explicitly,
these [INAUDIBLE]
payments.
And one of the things that would
have full consequences
for telcos if it actually ended
up being true because
the moment that you regulate
it as a financial product,
then basically you don't have
a prepaid phone account.
You have a value-added account
that telcos is storing, which
means you could go to a shop,
and they should refund your
money, and things like that.
So it has a lot of implications
regarding how you
handle money there.
But also, it also has
a lot of advantages.
So in this, I can actually give
one anecdote, which is
BlueVia, we do payments
for different--
basically, we're the back
end that different
stores connect to.
We do payments with Mozilla.
We do payments with Google.
And one of the things that
happened in Google recently is
that in the Android store,
WhatsApp, which is this famous
IM application, recently
decided to charge for
subscriptions.
And WhatsApp, only WhatsApp,
triplicated our transactions
during a period of time in Spain
because people who had
never entered their credit card
in Google Wallet decided
to pay with their mobile account
because they didn't
want to enter the whole
credit card thing.
They just said, OK.
There's an option to actually
pay with my phone.
That was the first time they
saw the option pay with my
phone, probably because it was
the first time that they
actually paid.
And that thing really launched
the transactions up.
So actually it shows that that
percentage of population, who
probably it was the only paid
transaction they ever did,
they actually used
the mobile phone.
MARCUS: I mean, the larger
question is--
you mentioned some of
the implications.
There are tons of legal
implications around this.
How are you guys going to deal
with that, especially in that
small community group?
RICARDO VARELA: Right now, it's
actually a bit of a gray
area because at the moment, for
example, when you charge
something to your phone, and
then it gets into your bill,
and then your bill gets
settled with your bank
account, in reality, the
operator never got hold of
that money.
That money has never gone
to the operator.
It actually only settles when
the bank pays me from your
bank account.
So in reality, your money
has always been
in your bank account.
It's more like a beautiful
ledger, what we are holding.
MARCUS: This wasn't what he said
initially about the 70%
of the people in the
world not having
access to a bank account.
The thing that I'm not
getting is that.
RICARDO VARELA: Yeah, but that's
because that 70% of
the-- so you take, for example,
a country-- this is a
country like Spain, where people
have got [INAUDIBLE]
contracts, or UK.
There's countries like Brazil
or most of Latin America,
where actually there's
three phone plans.
Basically, there's prepaid,
there's postpaid, the contract
that you're used to, and there's
[INAUDIBLE], which is
where I pay during
a period of time.
So I say, I pay 5 euros, and I'm
locked in a contract for a
week, that kind of thing.
So when you're in those systems,
most people are
prepaid on those markets,
by the way.
And what they do is
they actually pay
their bill on a shop.
They go to a shop.
They get a coupon, and they
load their phone.
So that's what they use.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK, yeah.
Complicated like a
Las Vegas hotel.
So we will go onto the next
question, which has come up a
little bit already, but Morgan,
if you're around and
stick your hand up.
Oh, there we go.
Very easy.
MORGAN: Hi.
I think part of this question
comes from our
host, Andrew Bets.
I'm going to personalize
it a little.
The basic question is, what
needs to happen to make
one-click payment a reality
for everyone?
What I'd like you to do is
think of everyone really
broadly and include maybe
organizations like libraries
and their readers for whom
complete confidentiality is a
requirement.
NATASHA ROONEY: So yeah, the
one-click payment thing is
quite interesting.
And it was one of the things
that I was quite blown away
with at Google I/O this year.
And Cyndy, this is something
that you work on, right?
CYNDY LOBB: Yep.
So I mean, this is
a common problem.
Users go to hundreds of
different forms and fill out
the exact same information.
So that was kind of the
hypothesis behind
requestAutocomplete, which
is the new web standard
initiative that Chrome
is implementing.
And part of that initiative, I'm
fortunate to be able to be
part of it because they are
integrating Google Wallet as a
payment option in addition to
Chrome autofill data, but it's
that concept that users are
filling out the same exact
information again and
again and again.
They don't necessarily want to
hand it over to 50 different
merchant websites, so why does
not the browser as the
container hold that information
for them and
provide it to the different
merchant
websites on their behalf?
So now, requestAutocomplete is
obviously dedicated to that
true payments use case.
It is providing the user's
information to complete the
transaction.
So in terms of [INAUDIBLE].
I cannot pronounce--
[INAUDIBLE].
In terms of that, that gets
challenging in payments period.
So that's an interesting thread
that I was surprised
hasn't come up sooner because
that is one of the biggest
changes between those 1970s
technologies and kind of what
is coming out today.
Because there are tons
of regulations
around payment companies.
And once you're regulated, you
have to monitor for depending
on changes country by country,
but there's anti-money
laundering.
There's initiatives that
governments put in place
really for consumer safety that,
with this anonymous new
digital currency, you lose.
So that's definitely the
identity thread is an
interesting one.
MANU SPORNY: You will not be
able to be anonymous when you
do a payment online.
It is going to be highly,
highly, highly unlikely your
government will not
let that happen.
Unless you rise up and change
it, but if we look at history,
that doesn't happen.
NATASHA ROONEY: So actually, I
have a quick question to go--
[INAUDIBLE]
talking about one-click payment,
is this something
that FirefoxOS or Mozilla are
looking at generally?
And then, what if a user decides
to opt in to do not
track, and then would
that then--
how does that work?
[INAUDIBLE], sorry.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: I mean, yeah.
One-tap payments are definitely
something that
mozPay wants to support.
Firefox marketplace wants
to support it.
That doesn't mean it'll
work for everybody.
So that's a really harder, much
harder problem to solve.
Amazon already does one-click
payments.
I mean, it's obviously very
possible on the web.
It's very easy to do.
I think in the short term,
requestAutocomplete is the
best way to get there.
I think that's just the reality
of the web right now,
is that every place takes a
credit card form, and carrier
billing is a little bit more
complicated, but with credit
cards, you can have
requestAutocomplete securely
store your credit card number.
And it's two clicks maybe, but
you could just tap the button
and say that, yes, fill in my
credit card, and you're done.
And that's going to be a big
win for both sides, for
consumers and for
the merchants.
Because on mobile especially,
it's really hard to enter in
your credit card.
If you do it once on one site,
and if you have to do it an
infinite number of times for
each other site, that's going
to really suck.
MANU SPORNY: So I disagree
partially.
I think you're right
in that it is-- and
you were very specific.
You said in the short term,
that's probably going to be
the best solution,
requestAutocomplete.
And I totally agree with that.
But I think that is--
and I don't think anyone on the
panel believes this, but I
think it would be incredibly
shortsighted for us to stop
there, to say that this is the
way it should be for the next
5 or 10 years.
We really need to fix the whole
like credit card numbers
given to every single merchant
you visit on the web issue.
I mean, how many people in here
would tell your users, I
think you should use the exact
same password for every single
financial account that you have,
and whenever you go to a
website, whenever you want to
spend money, you give them
your password?
That's your credit
card number.
CYNDY LOBB: OK, I'm
going to jump in.
I'm going to jump in.
And that's where the Google
Wallet integration with
requestAutocomplete, especially
on the Chrome side,
does close that hole because we
do use the virtual tokens.
So we do protect that user's
true credit card number.
MANU SPORNY: But it's
proprietary to Google, right?
CYNDY LOBB: It is.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK, we
probably should take
[INAUDIBLE].
CYNDY LOBB: But we are open to
integration with other browser
manufacturers.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK, we
need to take some
questions from the floor.
[INAUDIBLE], So yeah, somebody
can pass [INAUDIBLE]
a mic, please.
[? AUDIENCE: So ?]
I guess my question kind of
relates to the debate that
kind of was just going on, but
we've been talking about
responsiveness [INAUDIBLE]
clients.
And it's great if we move to a
world where, yeah, there is an
Open Web standard
for payments.
But right now, it's not that.
It's very fragmented.
Everyone's trying to push a
one-click solution to payments.
You have Amazon.
You have Stripe.
Everyone's putting a button on
your page, saying pay with me.
And so now we're in a--
for developers, our payment
form is just now cluttered
with pay with everything.
So is there kind of a strategy
for developers in a way that
we're not cutting into our
margins because we're not
giving the users the payment
method they want?
How do we balance that?
NATASHA ROONEY: This is a
web-intense [INAUDIBLE].
ROB GRIMSHAW: We can't just
endorse that comment because
referring back to the last
answer, so many of these
solutions for one-click payment
are essentially
proprietary.
And when you look at it from a
merchant's point of view, what
it amounts to is this sort of
smorgasbord of different
payment solutions that, one by
one, you have to kind of
integrate with your
own systems.
And each one just
delivers a tiny
fraction of extra payments.
And for a merchant
like us, which is
operating across borders--
I mean, we have subscribers
in 150 countries--
this is just a nightmare
because many of these
solutions only work in one or
two or a select number of
territories.
And it's completely
impractical.
We are so far away from a
one-click solution which will
operate seamlessly around the
globe for any merchant,
really, at the moment.
And that's what we really need
to make things work.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah, I was
going to talk about something
around the [? intense ?] model
to be able to say, I just want
to pay, and then it's just your
chosen payment method
comes through.
But this is very similar along
the lines of what Facebook
tried with credits, right?
And then they came up against
the foreign exchange problem,
which anyone who's worked in
the financial markets will
know is just a complete
nightmare.
So yeah, any other thoughts
on this topic?
MANU SPORNY: Yeah, so I think
Cyndy and Kumar are probably
never going to talk to me again
after this panel, but--
CYNDY LOBB: You're sitting
dangerously close.
MANU SPORNY: Yes, I know.
And by the hole too.
So I think the best thing that
web developers can do is put
some pressure on Google and
Mozilla and PayPal and Stripe
and tell them that you want some
kind of unified payment
mechanism that's non-proprietary
on the web.
I mean, I honestly think that
is the best thing for
the web right now.
And I really, in your
heart of hearts, I
think you agree, right?
I mean, we--
CYNDY LOBB: But sometimes.
MANU SPORNY: Everything
[INAUDIBLE].
CYNDY LOBB: [INAUDIBLE].
KUMAR MCMILLAN: What I think
is really interesting about
that is Mozilla and Google
are browser vendors.
And I actually don't think
we have a lot of
leverage to do this.
I think it needs to
come from banks.
MANU SPORNY: You do.
You do.
I was in Dubai at a banking
conference with all the major
world banks, and they are
absolutely terrified of
technology companies coming in
and stealing their customers.
You have so much power
to change this.
I am being ab--
you have so much power
to change this.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK, let's
move back to the
questions from the floor.
Steve, here, if we can
get another mic to--
STEVE: Yeah, I guess it was
really just a question about
what Manu said, that I can't
be anonymous on the web.
In the physical world, I can
go and pay with something,
cash, and be completely
anonymous.
Why would I want to give up--
I mean, why should I give
up that anonymity that I
currently have in a
physical world?
MANU SPORNY: That's a
very good question.
You shouldn't if you
don't want to.
But we're dealing with--
I mean, you know, there's a
lot of information that's
collected on us on the web.
If you don't want that
information collected on you,
don't get on the web.
We've got issues with
PRISM, the NSA.
We know how easy it is
to tap this stuff.
It's very easy to track.
And even Bitcoin, which is
supposed to be this pseudo
anonymous protocol, people have
been able to track down
spending habits, who's
spending money.
So for example, if someone
steals your Bitcoin wallet,
that money can't ever be used
really because if it's used,
and it's tracked down to a
shipping address, then they
can find you.
You report your wallet as
stolen, and any money coming
out of that wallet can be
tracked to the person that
made any kind of physical
purchase.
NATASHA ROONEY: This brings
me back to the whole
do not track thing.
I'm still really quite
interested to know about how
this would work with a mozPay
system on FirefoxOS.
Because they're pushing
so much for that.
RICARDO VARELA: I'll wait
for the mozPay one.
If I can add only one thing to
this, the problem, as we were
saying before, is basically the
whole payments is based on
risk and trust.
And in this case, what you're
saying, what you're doing in
that financial transaction in
cash with somebody, is that
the issuer, the person who's
generating the funds, aka,
you, is making a transaction
with a merchant, which is at
the same time the
[? acquiritor, ?]
this person.
And this transaction occurs in
something that we both trust,
aka, government money.
Because we both think
that that is
actually valuable money.
So this transaction has
occurred between us.
You actually gave away
your identity.
You gave away your identity to
this person, who actually can
recognize you.
And he thought that this was
enough to establish trust.
So that's why they accepted
your money.
In the digital world, the
problem is that this person is
a server down there, and
you are a browser
somewhere down here.
And that trust has got to be
established between you two
before those funds get changed
from your bank to their bank.
And that's kind of the problem,
is that at that
moment, the issuer, that other
person, that acquirer, is
going to only trust something.
And in general, Google will
perfectly trust your Google
Wallet account.
PayPal will perfectly trust
your PayPal account.
And Mozilla will trust whichever
account you actually
have got to be configured
in mozPay.
But Google won't accept your
PayPal identity as being a
valid identity.
That is where the
problem comes.
Because they don't establish
trust based
on the other identity.
NATASHA ROONEY: Excellent.
We probably should actually
move forward.
So Tom C, if you've--
oh, OK, good.
There we go.
TOM C: Thanks.
I think if we--
if I can distinguish between
anonymity and confidentiality.
Somebody's coming to the library
to pay a $0.25 fine
for an overdue book, and we
don't want anybody to know--
we know who that person is
because we know you checked
out the book.
But I don't want anybody
else to know that you
paid a fine on it.
Is there a way I can do
that online for $0.25?
RICARDO VARELA: No.
ROB GRIMSHAW: No.
MANU SPORNY: Yes.
Yes.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: I
mean, not yet.
MANU SPORNY: Well, I think
there is, right?
If you use Bitcoin to do it,
and you create a one-off
wallet, you could
do that payment.
But I mean, that's really--
it's very difficult
to do that.
Technically possible, not very
feasible, which I think is the
answer they were giving.
It's not a good user
experience.
NATASHA ROONEY: So Kumar--
oh, sorry, Rob, you--
ROB GRIMSHAW: Some of this
stuff is not about the
technology, either.
I think governments around the
globe are attacking anonymity
in the financial system on all
fronts for issues of taxation,
money laundering, et cetera.
And I don't think that effort
is going to stop.
And as we move into an
electronics payments world, I
don't think they're going
to allow big channels of
anonymous payments,
whether it's
technically possible or not.
NATASHA ROONEY: Cool.
All right, we should
move on now.
I'm liking what people are
managing to get on the--
I think we have money
bags [INAUDIBLE].
CYNDY LOBB: Is this end
of the day humor?
NATASHA ROONEY: [INAUDIBLE].
That's fantastic.
[INAUDIBLE].
I kind of wish that
was the case.
Unfortunately, not.
So Matt Andrews, if you stick
up your hand for the next
question, please.
MATT ANDREWS: This is another
anonymous question.
I think it's pretty much been
done to death, but here we go.
What are the possibilities for
decentralized peer-to-peer
payments, and what security
considerations are involved in
doing this?
NATASHA ROONEY: So decentralized
peer-to-peer
payments, and what security
considerations are involved in
doing this, going back
to a similar thing.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Kumar, do you
want to start us off on this?
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Sure.
Well, I've been sort of in the
realm of FirefoxOS, which is a
mobile operating system.
And it's really hard on mobile
devices to do something to get
to a decentralized
place like that.
We would need like the web
crypto API to land so that we
can make sure that things are
very secure and even in memory
are secure.
And another API which is coming
is to access a secure
element on certain Sim cards,
where you can actually do sort
of public key exchange
type of things.
All those technologies
are needed.
But at the end of the day, you
could still root a device, if
you were to steal it,
and then you can get
access to a lot of things.
So I think we're pretty far
off from it, but I think
that's what would
need to happen.
It would have to be something
that's would have to be this
bulletproof device.
Because also, if it's completely
decentralized, that
means that you're paying with
a device, and let's say it's
Bitcoin or something, and it's
not backed up on a server
because it's decentralized, you
might lose that device,
and then you lose
all your money.
And maybe there's some
way to distribute
that across many nodes.
I don't know.
But yeah.
Hard problem.
NATASHA ROONEY: Sort of against
the cloud pattern that
seems to be happening with
lots of things, I guess.
Any other points on that?
MANU SPORNY: I mean, there
are already decentralized
peer-to-peer payment systems
on the web, right?
Bitcoin and Ripple
are two of them.
You can use them.
They're online wallets, so you
have to be able to get to some
website to run the
transaction.
But the protocols work, right?
I mean, the Bitcoin's been under
attack since it ever
came out, and by really smart
people in crypto and security
areas, and no one's really
broken the protocol.
So I think they're here.
It's just the idea of it being
integrated directly into the
browser is probably--
I would expect that it would
never happen, or at least not
for the next 10 to 15 years.
Because the risk you run when
you put it into a browser is
you have to end up supporting
it forever.
And I don't think any of the
browser-- and I don't think it
would be smart for any of the
browser vendors to build that
technology in right now.
Which is why the Firefox
marketplace and Telefonica are
taking the approach they
are on these APIs.
They're trying to be very
generic and not trying to be
king makers when it comes
to payment technologies.
It's the right way to do it.
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
Let's take another question.
So Adam Sontag, if you're
in the room [INAUDIBLE].
I think he's over there.
ADAM SONTAG: So this is an
anonymous question that, at
the request of Jake Archibald, I
have mildly reformatted into
rhyming verse.
So one question that still needs
distilling is, what's
the feasibility of
operator billing?
And given that phones prefer
Wi-Fi to cell, will I have to
forget this network
to buy and sell?
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
[APPLAUSE]
RICARDO VARELA: Very impressive,
by the way.
So my skill is not enough to
actually answer you in verse,
I'm afraid.
But definitely, operator billing
is something that is
widely used now.
We are also in the middle of,
for people who are not
familiar with, in the middle
of a change of technology.
So we went from premium SMS,
which is essentially I charge
you for an SMS message, very
clunky, had lots of messages,
really high revenue share for
the operator because it was a
really old technology used
to sell ringtones
and things like that.
So not as good.
To direct operator billing,
which is essentially you make
a call to an API, which
is more [INAUDIBLE]
for 21st century.
And basically, you send me an
amount and phone number, and
the phone number acts as
basically the user account.
That is working now.
It's actually you can pay
with that in Google.
You can pay in Rim, in Nokia.
In BlueVia, we work with at
least 20 something different
providers, including Mozilla.
And basically, that
is what modern
operator billing is about.
The problem that I see in modern
operator billing is
that modern operator billing
thought to be something that
you negotiate with
an operator.
So you negotiate with O2.
Then you go and negotiate
with Vodafone.
with Telefonica.
And the problem there is that
you have to close one account
for each of these things.
So one of the things that we
actually tried to start with
BlueVia is to give to the
Telefonica group just one
connection for all
those billings.
So do what Visa does in the
case of banks, where you
basically take Visa
payments, right?
You don't take [INAUDIBLE],
Barclays, and
don't know what payments.
You take payments
from a network.
So I think that is the step
that we have missing, but
actually, you can do charges
to a phone number now with
modern technology.
NATASHA ROONEY: One of the
problems is, though, is this
issue of being over Wi-Fi is
that an operator cannot
recognize you as a user
if you're on a
Wi-Fi network, correct?
RICARDO VARELA: You only need
to know what's the phone
number of the user.
And that can happen in a
one-time transaction, which
is, for example, how
Google does it.
This is how Mozilla does it.
Basically, if you are--
operators have multiple ways
of recognizing what phone
number you're in.
For a start, you're connected
to a base station.
So if you are giving your
service, we know your number.
So if you're connected to the
normal network, you can
identify the user through
the network.
If they're connected in Wi-Fi,
then you do a fallback to SMS.
Which normally is either you
send an SMS to the device with
a code, or you make the device
send you an SMS, and then you
receive it.
In both cases, you establish
what is the number of the
user, and then you can just
use that again and again.
We have a specific API built
for this in BlueVia.
In other operators, you have
to do it more manually, but
you can do that.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: And to be clear,
you can do it again and
again because it just stores
a cookie on device.
I mean, the cookie lasts 30 days
or something like that.
And when you're on Wi-Fi, it
reads the cookie so it knows
that you're authenticated.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK.
So fantastic.
So can I be Montgomery
Burns, please?
[INAUDIBLE].
Awesome.
It's getting better.
Right.
We only have five minutes
left, so I kind of
want to close on--
but we have a room of
technologists here, and I'd
like to focus on a little bit of
the standards, a little bit
of the what we can do.
So if we just go around and have
a little bit of a chat--
well, if you could all say,
give one minute on what we
could do as developers
to push to the
ideal payments solution.
And Kumar, I'm afraid I'm
going to start with you.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Sure.
As developers--
NATASHA ROONEY: Or
standardizers.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Yeah.
That's a tricky one.
I do think, as I mentioned
before, I think to really have
a sort of federated payment
system where anyone can pay
with any currency, and any
merchant can accept money from
anywhere, I think something
needs to come.
Some API needs to be agreed upon
and implemented by banks,
or something, maybe a
clearinghouse, in front of banks.
And I don't think that browser
vendors can do that.
So I have strayed from
the topic of what
developers can do.
I still don't know what
NATASHA ROONEY: Ricardo?
RICARDO VARELA: Well, I think
that for a start, we have to
have more realistic
expectations, I
think, in all of this.
I think there's [INAUDIBLE] for
the work that we did in
WAC, where you try to do a
mobile billing, in this case,
for 40 something operators
across the globe, and this
includes Asia and Africa and
Latin America, there's no way
you can sink all of
those things.
It's too big a problem.
However, you can start
in smaller areas.
You take something like
the European Union.
The European Union is about to
standardize on a series of
measures called SEPA.
You could do, in theory, some
hub for the European Union
with a specific protocol that
works across all the providers
in the European Union.
Obviously, it won't work
in Latin America.
It won't work in China.
But it's something.
So we start trying to
standardize there, and we try
to push for a standard idea or
a standard way that different
providers can implement that
there, which is how it
normally happens.
Banks didn't go and try to
standardize on this type of
thing worldwide.
They standardized in European
Union, more or less.
And then let's see
how it extends.
Or you do two networks, and then
we talk a common protocol
among our networks.
That would be fine.
The thing is that you
need those initial
solutions to be there.
So requestAutocomplete or mozPay
are initial tries of
getting to that standard API.
Just use them, feedback to them,
and saying I'm lacking
this thing.
So requestAutocomplete doesn't
support [INAUDIBLE] billing.
MozPay, we're going to do
another iteration now.
Whichever thing that we have,
just feedback to that, and
start with that smaller
goal before we get
to the bigger goal.
ROB GRIMSHAW: I'm actually very
excited about some of the
things that Ricardo
is talking about.
I believe fundamentally that the
solutions are going to be
mobile-based ultimately.
We're almost to the point where
there are more mobile
devices than people
on the planet.
There's far more people with
mobiles than there are with
bank accounts, for example.
And if some of the things that
Ricardo is talking about, the
development of a network and
a sort of global standard
network for payments across
major mobile operators can
develop, then I can see how a
merchant like us can take
payments on mobile devices
potentially from a marketplace
of billions of people
around the globe.
And that's very,
very exciting.
And if you think about
it, what you've
got there is a chain.
All these devices in some
way are linked up
to a source of value.
Whether that's a bank account or
whether that's a prepaid or
whatever, the chain of value
is already there.
If you can create the standard
across the top of it, maybe
starting in the EU or the US
or whatever, which then a
merchant like us can then
hook into, that
can deliver the solution.
And I don't think you have to
think about utopian scenarios
in order to get there.
It's not difficult to see how
this step can be taken.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah, so from
my point of view, I think
that's an important issue.
Lots of users think about what
would be great for the users.
And I think the way that you're
going to get the thing
that you want as a user is to
influence from a merchant
standpoint or from the bank
standpoint or from the
standardization standpoint.
And that's my takeaway, is that,
OK, if you want your
user goals, you go for it.
But you put a slant on it and
sell it up to those other
people that makes them think
that they're getting
something, when you're actually
getting something,
and that's the way to
get what you want.
So lifestyle tips.
Manu, go for it.
MANU SPORNY: So anybody in
here that's interested in
payments, the thing that you
could do is join the web
payments group.
Join the discussion.
It's completely open.
Anyone can join and
participate.
Educate yourself about it, and
help us actually figure out
what standards to build, what
to build that you can use.
The other point I wanted to kind
of make is playing off of
Kumar's bank-based thing.
I did spend the last week
at the World Banking
Conference in Dubai.
No bank is working on this.
I guarantee you.
I had high level, low
level, all kinds of
discussions with them.
The standard bank system is
written in COBOL or Fortran.
It was implemented in
1987 [INAUDIBLE]
through 1992.
They're still running
that code base.
They are absolutely mortified
of doing any kind of large
change to their system.
So this solution is not going
to come from the banks.
It could come from the
mobile operators.
people like Google
Wallet, PayPal, Stripe.
But at some point, all of us
are going to have to band
together in some kind of clump
and push something forward.
It's definitely not going
to be the banks
that do that though.
NATASHA ROONEY: So throw
yourself into the
standardization.
Finally, Cyndy.
CYNDY LOBB: Real quick, because
I know everyone's
ready to be done.
No, just really use mozPay.
Use requestAutocomplete.
Even though it is technology
from the '70s, it is what
everyone is still using.
And there's plenty of room to
improve that '70s technology
experience on the web as we try
and lay a foundation and
segue into more different
technologies.
But definitely
requestAutocomplete, mozPay.
Participate.
We are trying to
make it better.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK, excellent.
So that's [INAUDIBLE].
Thank you so much to
the panelists.
[INAUDIBLE].
[APPLAUSE]