JAKE ARCHIBALD: Hello
everyone.
Welcome to the Offline panel.
Most of us, as web
developers, we--
I think I was about to say that
we declare game over when
there's no network connection
available or when it's faulty.
But if we want to compete with
the cream of native apps, then
having the network as
a dependency is
simply not good enough.
But the five brave souls in
front of you today, they laugh
in the face of zero bars
of connectivity.
And they do not want your wallet
to be drained when you
are roaming.
And they do not want to give up
on you when your ISP has.
We have Matt Andrews from the
"Financial Times." You've got
Craig Cavalier from
Liquid Frameworks.
And we've got Calvin Spealman
from Caktus Consulting.
These guys have been building
stuff with the current crop of
inadequate APIs that
we have on the web.
But they have suffered
through that.
So give them a hug afterwards,
because they've
been damaged by that.
But we also have Anne van
Kesteren from Mozilla and Alex
Russell from Google.
And these guys have been working
on the future APIs
that are going to solve all
of our worldly problems.
Is that fair to say?
Yeah?
OK.
That's good.
So we're hoping that in the
future, making a site work
offline is not going to be an
act of self flagellation.
And on that note, Alex, I
believe you're going to
introduce a topic.
Are you good to go?
ALEX RUSSELL: Sure.
[LAUGHTER]
ALEX RUSSELL: As Jake
says, I'm Alex.
Do we have slides?
Did I fail at this
miserably again?
I'm so good at this.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So yeah, we've
changed the name of the new
stuff a couple of
times recently.
It kind of started off as
Navigation Controller, but
it's been expanded.
It spent a little bit of
time as Event Worker.
And now it's Service Worker.
But it has been pointed out by
Lady Ada King on Twitter that
Service Worker does sound
somewhat like the oldest
profession in the world.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So
I don't know.
We kind of thought, maybe,
Service Controller.
But does that sound
like a pimp?
I don't know.
But an app pimp, that's
pretty cool.
We all want to use
an app pimp.
So maybe we'll go with
that, pimp our apps.
That could be cool.
So, yeah.
We're going to have to find a
name for it that doesn't evoke
that kind of negative thing.
But how are you doing, Alex?
Because I'm running
out of filler.
ALEX RUSSELL: Yeah.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Is it because
it doesn't work offline?
Is that your problem?
[LAUGHTER]
ALEX RUSSELL: That might
actually be it.
Yeah.
So as Jake says, I am Alex.
And I am re-scaling the
slides as we speak.
So I spend a lot of
time offline.
I most recently lived in London
before I returned to
San Francisco.
And they did something in the
tube for the Olympics where
they said they were going to
put Wi-Fi in all of the
stations, which technically
speaking is accurate.
They did happen to put Wi-Fi
transmitters and receivers in
all of the stations.
But one of my most frequent tube
journeys was to and from
airports, because I spend a
lot of time in airplanes.
And it always seemed really
punitive, because you would
get to a station and for about
20 seconds, while people were
loading and unloading, your
wireless Wi-Fi radio would be
attempting to connect
frantically to the thing.
And you'd be trying to log in
a little bit so you can just
download the next-- no!
Fuck!
We're moving.
[LAUGHTER]
ALEX RUSSELL: So I got really
good at figuring out how to
turn off the Wi-Fi in my device,
because the network
just wasn't reliable.
Even when I absolutely
wanted it--
I wanted to see the news, I
wanted to get the latest
"Times" or "Guardian,"
whatever it is.
OK I've outed myself
as a lefty, fine.
And the end of this journey, of
course, ends you up in an
airport where you are at the
whim of whoever happens to
have the crappy Wi-Fi in
whatever bit of hell you've
ended yourself up in with a
captive portal and all the
rest, right?
So these are hostile network
environments.
And they mediate our lives.
Like I think the work
environment and the home
environment are special cases
of how we interact with the
stuff around us.
And it's in those environments--
the airport,
the tube, the ones that are
really stressful where you're
trying to get some place,
you've got a thing.
Where the heck was I going?
What's this thing I'm trying
to do right now?
I don't remember.
I look at my phone and ff--
right?
It's that environment that we,
as a technology stack, fail at
miserably, largely because we
have built ourselves the
assumption that what
is remote is cheap.
Because everything
is remote, right?
The web is designed around the
idea of the URL, the thing
that is over there that's
cheap to do.
And that little tiny anchor
tag makes it look like
everything is connected to
you all the time, right?
a href is the most innocent
thing you
can possibly imagine.
And at the same time,
the implications
of a href are massive.
It says nothing about
whether or not you
can get to the network.
And the tube gives us a good
window into what it means to
know whether or not you're
online, right?
So we keep getting requests for
a bandwidth property in
the browser, right?
Tell me what my bandwidth is.
Tell me what my available
bandwidth is.
There's no way to
actually know.
So if I show up at a conference
and there's a
captive portal to go get me my
thing, my bandwidth to a thing
which does nothing I want
might be infinite.
Whereas, my bandwidth to all
of the services that I
actually care about
might be negative.
So we find ourselves in
this situation a lot.
And it's very difficult, from
the browser's perspective, to
say anything meaningful about
your connection, right?
Saying something other than "I
can't do anything because
there's no radio turned on
and it's not connected to
anything" is a very difficult
call to make.
So we've put ourselves in a
situation on the web where
we've architected an entire
stack of stuff around the idea
that the thing that's over there
is really cheap, or at
least as cheap as everything
else is.
And the thing that's local
is unreliable, right?
Caches are things that get
evicted, they're things that
you can't trust, they're things
you can't rely on.
And this isn't how we build
anything anywhere else, right?
I would never build a
browser on top of
this technology stack.
And I don't mean that in the
sense that there are things
that you can't do.
I just mean that you would never
put up with the idea
that the Close Tab icon
might be evicted.
That's not a thing that you
would ever put up with.
So let's think through
how we got here.
So imagine a little website
that's a little tiny two-man
agency, two-person agency,
two-alien agency, two beings.
And they're trying to put
together a website.
And it's the simplest thing
that could possibly work.
And if you deconstruct this
layout, it tells you
everything you need
to know, right?
This is really, really simple.
This is static content
effectively.
And it probably will
bit rot, right?
They're probably not going to
change their team website if
they're even moderately
successful because it will
outstrip their ability to
actually build websites for
themselves because they'll be
doing it for clients, right?
OK.
So this is going to be
effectively unmaintained.
And if you look at how it's
built, you can sort of get a
sense for what it takes to
get started on the web.
You have some resources, you
have some HTML files.
And when you really start out,
it's copy and paste.
If you're going to get advanced
from 1995, you'll
eventually configure Apache to
do server side includes.
And you'll change
these to .shtml.
Thank you, very much.
And you'll have your server
side includes for the
navigations and the footers
at the top and the bottom.
And you will have whacked
all that in.
And so now we're starting to see
that there is a repeated
bit of content around some
of the things that we're
addressing with URLs.
So I have a blog, right?
Please don't read it.
It will save you time
and embarrassment.
But that blog is much more
sophisticated than that little
tiny layout for a static
website, effectively, like a
brochureware site, largely
because it's actually-- the
location of my domain,
infrequently.org, has nothing
to do with an individual
bit of content.
It's not addressing some
It's addressing a database
query, a reverse chronological
order query across these
tables, right?
And when we ship this stuff down
to the client, we don't
ship those tables.
We explode a bunch of
that stuff out.
We denormalize it entirely,
serialize it through
templates, and then
spit it all out.
Right?
But if you go look at any
individual article, it sort of
corresponds to one item in
one of those tables.
And then we take all the whole
machinery again, which is the
shell around that little bit
of content that we're
addressing with the URL, and
we explode it all out.
And we ship this huge bundle
of content down, which
effectively wraps the stuff.
And if you look at the
HTML, that's actually
what happens, right?
It's just document and then tons
and tons of stuff around
it, and then this thing that
we were actually putting in
the center of this template
thing, which is what the URL
is kind of actually
pointing at.
When we talk about meaningful
URLs, we tend to mean
meaningful with regards to the
thing that's the primary thing
you, as a user, would
focus on, right?
It's a very subjective view,
because it's about what the
user is experiencing about that
location, about that state.
So if we think about it like
what is the URL actually
talking about, we start to get
this idea that we've done for
a couple of decades now is to
take server side graphs of
state and pre-explode them for
digestion by the client.
And that pre-explosion means
that HTML is something that's
incredibly powerful and,
effectively, display-only.
And it gets really confused, as
soon as you start talking
about doing dynamic stuff.
Because there's that big model
over on the server which is
written in--
at least in the case
of Wordpress--
it's PHP and MySQL.
OK?
These are two technologies
which, without extraordinary
acts of inhuman and inhumane
technology, are not going to
be running in my browser
anytime soon, right?
I'm sure there's a ScummVM that
would run something like
this, right?
But today, we're
not doing that.
And the latency characteristics
haven't been
set up to do it.
So let's imagine the next leap
from little, tiny brochureware
thing to blog, which is
moderately complicated CMS, to
the biggest thing that we can
think of that's still
effectively static content,
infrequently
updated static content.
I submit Wikipedia.
So the question becomes, if
you're building Wikipedia as
an app, or if you're trying to
make it possible for me, while
sitting on a tube, 20 seconds at
a time of connectivity, if
I'm lucky, to go and read an
article and click on a link to
go to the next article, what
is required for us to think
about making that a meaningful
thing to do?
It turns out the thing that you
really require is the help
of the user.
Because it's not possible to
think through this whole
system and say I'm going
to go grab all of it.
Like my blog is relatively
small.
You could maybe fetch it all.
But you couldn't fetch
all of Wikipedia.
I've tried this.
Decompressing this takes about
20 minutes on an i7, a really
ballsy laptop.
Downloading it took a couple
of minutes too.
So think about Gmail, right?
What am I indexing when I
go to one of these URLs?
Or when I go to a music site,
could I possibly download that
entire library?
My Gmail is really,
really full.
I don't want the entire
contents.
In fact, I want some
subset of that.
And I, as the user, am willing
to help you go figure
out what that is.
And as the atomic size of the
media gets bigger and the more
of it that I've got, the more
that pressure builds up on us.
We don't really have a way
of thinking about it.
So the way I phrase this now is
that there's an application
that you'd like to think about,
which is what helps the
browser render content.
And then there's content.
And in the old days--
quote, unquote "old days"--
we try to conflate the two
as much as possible.
We would smush the shell into
the content with server side
includes and CGI, right?
And as we get more sophisticated
and more
dynamic, we have to serve the
shell and think about the
shell differently
to the content.
They're different entities.
So it turns out the offline
problem is actually about
making applications that can
bootstrap themselves.
It's not about this how do I
transparently turn the thing
that I've got into that other
thing over there.
It's about the data model
and where it's split.
Who owns the data and
where does is live?
Am I doing synchronization over
a thing that I've synced
part of to the client?
Or am I shipping a series
of pre-exploded pages?
That's kind of the
core problem that
we have with offline.
So a Service Worker is an
attempt to get us through a
couple of these problems, by
saying that we don't know the
answer for your application.
But what we do know is that
you don't have enough
control right now.
We spent a lot of time
looking through it.
And basically, it's an
in-browser proxy that you can
install from the perspective
of your origin.
And when you do, at some point
later, when it finishes
installing, you'll get notified,
and the ability to
proxy, do whatever you like
with the response, for any
request those documents make.
You get to own the request,
cross-domain, same
origin, you name it.
And it gives you programmatic
control over a series of
caches as well.
So it's relatively simple.
You say, I would like
to register for
one of these things.
And it gives you
a promise back.
Yes, promises are coming
to the [? dome. ?]
You can thank some
people later.
And you can actually compose
stuff from third parties.
You can pull in resources to use
with these cache objects.
And then this addEventListener
for fetches actually gives you
the ability to go and
construct-- you see that
e.respondWith(new
SameOriginResponse there
toward the bottom?
That's actually creating
a response out of
whole cloth, right?
You're just programmatically
saying, this is the content
that you should send back
to this document, right?
That's the idea.
You've never been able
to do this before,
except on the server.
What if we could do this
on the client?
And why can't we, by the way?
You can imagine another
couple of ideas.
I would like to, when
I'm offline, serve
some fall back, right?
Or if I've got pictures of cats
and I would like them to
be responsive cats, I would
like you to, through some
magical API, figure out what
we've already stored about the
client, what we know, the device
pixel width, the aspect
ratio that we probably are
displaying at, the kinds of
things that a document could
tell us while it's populating
the Service Worker.
And then have the Service
Worker respond with the
correct one, as opposed to
trying to figure it all out
preemptively up front
and make CSS do the
heavy lifting for us.
All right.
I'm actually getting
to the end.
So there are a bunch of big
implications for this design.
What does it mean to have real
URLs in these applications,
when we think of a shell
that boots up but
then mediates content?
What does the URL mean?
It means something that's
interpreted by the shell.
Can we build transparent
caching proxies?
The answer is yes.
It's the simplest thing
to possibly do.
You actually just populate a new
thing in this cache object
every time you get a request.
And then suddenly, things
mostly work offline.
Is that good?
Is that bad?
We're not sure yet.
We don't know.
And we don't really have good
synchronization technology today.
There's some work happening.
I know the media guys are
spending a lot of time on
operational transform.
And the Ember guys are
looking at it.
But synchronization technology
is not our lingua franca.
This is not how we have
thought about
building the web.
And it's the sort of thing that
we're going to have to
get good at, if we really bite
off this idea of building
applications that are shells
that boot up to mediate
content, and not simply
documents which happen to be
fully formed things sprung
from the head of Zeus.
So there's a bunch of
open questions.
And I guess it's time for
us talk about it.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: And Alex
is out of time.
Thank you, very much.
Good boy.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: No, the
underground example
is a very good one.
When I was building lanyards,
the underground was the most
convenient place to go and
test a real world offline
situation, because turning some
things onto airplane mode
is not quite sufficient.
But I remember though, it was
with like five mobile phones.
And one of the staff came up to
me and he just stood there
staring at me.
And I looked behind me.
And I was standing in front of
a poster which essentially
said, if you see someone with
more than one mobile phone,
they're probably a terrorist and
you should deal with them.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So first off,
before we go to the first
question, did any of the
panelists have anything to say
about what Alex was talking
about there in the intro?
CALVIN SPEALMAN: I had just
one comment which is, I do
wonder how many people working
on the Service Navigator
Controller--
whatever the eventual name is--
how many are the same
people who built Google Gears,
which I think had almost
exactly the same mechanism for
dealing with offline, just in
sort of a proxy, into
the browser?
Is there a connection there?
ALEX RUSSELL: So it's
a good question.
So Michael Nordman was
on the Gears team.
And he's one of the people who's
helping us implement the
Service Worker.
We've tried at least
twice before--
from the Chrome prospective,
before there was Chrome, it
was Gears, and then inside
of Chrome with
the application cache--
to give you tools to make
things work offline.
And we have failed
miserably twice.
And Gears wasn't what
you thought it was.
So if you go back and you pull
the documentation out of the
internet archive, what
you'll find is that
Gears has a thing called--
oh, what was it?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Local
Server, isn't it?
ALEX RUSSELL: Yeah,
Local Server.
And the Local Server wasn't a
server that you could script.
You couldn't ever give it a bit
of code and say, please go
run this whenever I request
a resource.
That never happened in Gears.
You could give it a manifest, a
declarative format, which is
exactly what we did in the
application cache too.
And in both cases, they were,
I think, like Jake put it at
Edge in London, like playing a
game where you can see the
effects of what you're doing a
couple of turns later, but you
can't actually control
any of it.
And as a result, we don't have
a lot of data about what you
actually need.
We've never given you the
primitives that you need to go
build the stuff you want and
evolve and iterate on that.
And I think there just hasn't
been a lot of exploration,
because it takes a
lot to get going.
And there hasn't been
the ability to
explore these patterns.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think Gears
was essentially the precursor
to Appcache, rather than
the precursor to this
thing we have now.
I think we should go to the
first question and, if I'm
reading right, documents.
It's from some chap called
Andrew Betts.
Never heard of him.
Where are you, Andrew?
Can someone get Andrew
a microphone?
There he is.
[INAUDIBLE]
ANDREW BETTS: OK.
Currently offline data may be
evicted at any time by the
user agent.
Can we have storage persistence
guarantees, or at
least provide hints to the
user agent to tell it to
prioritize AppLogic
over content data?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Yes.
This is a very interesting
question, because the whole
thing about using
it in airports.
If we make a guarantee that yes,
as a user, your data of
when your flight is going to
be will be available to you
offline, the spec does
not currently let
us make that guarantee.
It can chuck all of the data
under a bus whenever
it feels like it.
CRAIG CAVALIER: This
is really important
for us, as a business.
To give a bit of background, I
work with field engineers.
And they work on
oil refineries.
And they write up their
invoices and
their equipment tracking.
We can't have their data just
disappearing on them as
they're writing up these
new invoices.
We don't want to
lose that data.
So that's a really important
problem for us
that we need to solve.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Is this a
problem that you actually
encountered in the "FT"?
Or is this a problem you
encountered, data
disappearing like that?
Or is it just a theoretical
problem?
CRAIG CAVALIER: It's a
theoretical problem, at this
point for us.
MATT ANDREWS: We have real
experience in this,
particularly--
I can't say this on record?
Ah, dammit.
iOS 5, we suspect strongly that,
occasionally, it wiped
our apps in certain
situations.
But not sure.
Can't prove it.
But we have strong suspicions.
[LAUGHTER]
CALVIN SPEALMAN: I'd like to
add that, I think, the most
important aspect of this is how
the user understands where
the data is and when the
browser may evict it.
We can't tell the browser that
they can ever evict something.
Only users should be
able to say that.
We have ways of installing an
app in an implicit way that
the user is invisible to.
And the data should
be tied to that.
So the user might say, this is
an app I want to keep around.
And therefore, they're opting-in
to keep that data.
And then it would be
safe to not evict.
So I think the bigger problem
here is not so much the APIs
we have, but the way
that the browser
presents that to the user.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So to say that
the user has to be responsible
for the removing of data, they
have to be responsible for the
adding of the data as well.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Yeah.
And if the user hasn't said,
I want this app to stay
available and its data to
stay available, then
it's safe to evict.
And so they need to
opt-in to this.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So, Alex?
I'm looking at the wrong
one when I say that.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: So we've
been looking into this for
Firefox OS as well, because the
problem comes up there as
well for apps.
And it's really hard, because
once you get to persistence it
mostly becomes a UX problem.
So we have this sort of concept
of you have temporary
storage which we just
grant to everyone.
We'll just grant you a slice
and you can use it.
And the other concept would
be persistent storage.
But that is much harder, because
the user sort of has
to be aware of it.
But then most users are not
really aware of storage and
how that is allocated through
apps and how that works across
their device.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: It's not
a problem on the
phone though, right?
Because if my phone tells me I'm
low on space, I can go to
the apps menu and it says, oh,
this game you don't care about
is using 200 megabytes.
And this thing you really care
about is using less than that.
So I can throw one of
them out the window.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Right.
Yeah.
So I think we have to evolve
it into that direction.
Yeah.
But the thing is do you ask
the user right up front?
And which apps do
you grant space?
Or do all apps have to ask for
persistent storage or not?
Whenever you hit the UX side of
things with standards, it
becomes a lot harder
to get things done.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Is there an API
or a standard that this
kind of work fits in?
Is it the Quota API?
Is that the plan?
ALEX RUSSELL: Yeah.
So there is a Quota API.
And it does have this idea
of persistent storage and
ephemeral storage.
And right now, persistent
storage is only available in
Chrome for certain file
system calls.
You can't, in a granular way,
opt some bit of your cookies
and your local storage and your
IndexedDB into persistent
storage and then say,
this other stuff I
don't really need.
And there's no clear way, in
the UX, to communicate to
users about what
they're doing.
It feels to me, like Anne was
saying, there's a very clear
missing moment of intent where
you give users the power to
say no, I really want
to keep this thing.
I like this a lot.
I would like to get back
to this easily.
I would like to bless it with
the ability to keep all of its
data around.
And we don't have
that moment yet.
We are missing what is,
effectively, a very small
manifest and then some
UI to let users say,
yeah, I like this.
I want to keep this.
And once users have said they
like it, I don't see why we
should ever be second
guessing them.
I mean, I trust myself to be
mediating the content of my
phone in a lot of
cases, right?
And in many cases that means
throwing out an application.
And I like doing that--
not like getting so annoyed
by an application that I
uninstall it.
But I like the ability to do
that and reason about that at
that level.
MATT ANDREWS: Don't we sort of
have this already with web
apps on iOS, where you add the
web app to your home screen?
So that's kind of similar to
saying, I want to keep this
app around.
I know Firefox, as well, I
think, it asks you, when you
load the web page in Appcache,
whether you want it to stay
around offline.
And you can say no, and
the website will
continue being a website.
Isn't that equivalent?
ALEX RUSSELL: Yeah.
I think that's a great point.
And I think that's kind of the
direction that we all need to
figure out a way to get to.
And someone asked about
the Quota API.
The Quota API is probably
something that we definitely
need to integrate into the
Service Worker design.
We've talked to the folks who
are in charge of the Quota API
about this.
Because it should also be the
case that, when applications
get under pressure, you should
be able to give an application
the ability to say, hey,
I'm about to ask you
for this much storage.
You need to figure out where
it's going to come from.
And if you don't do that, maybe
we evict you entirely.
But one of the nice bits about
the Service Worker design
versus the HTTP cache
today is that it's
not HTTP cache, right?
Once resources are there, unless
you pull them out,
they're there for the lifetime
of the thing.
It'll get evicted as a bundle.
But it's up to you, as an
application, to make smart
decisions about what
you prioritize.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Yeah.
And it's a little bit harder.
Like you can put it on the home
screen, but it doesn't
mean how much storage were
you granted then.
Like it might need 2 gigabytes,
it might need 4, it
might need most of
your hard drive.
And is the user comfortable
with that?
Does the user even know
what that means?
MATT ANDREWS: One of the other
problems we had when we were
developing the HTML app for "The
Economist" was, in IE10,
you can actually configure
exactly how much space you can
give to your web apps.
You can make that
one megabyte.
So for us, that's far,
far not enough.
So we have to detect how
much space we have.
So I think too much control
can also be a bad
thing, quite limiting.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So if you did
this installable app thing, is
that going to replace the number
of toolbars we get for
each permission?
What's that going to
replace it with?
Are we going to get this
Android solution where,
upfront, you get the list of
permissions, and you just
ignore it and click next?
Is that the kind of model that
we see working on the web?
[LAUGHTER]
ALEX RUSSELL: If I had my
druthers, it would be a system
where the user can always
say no, right?
And to the extent that they've
said yes, they've said yes.
But they can change
their mind later.
So the Android model of a bundle
of permissions which
can't be split apart from each
other implies APIs that aren't
allowed to fail, right?
There's only a return true.
There's never some sort
of a failure case.
And I think the web has gotten
a long way on the basis of
APIs that can fail.
Like that's how we adapt,
is the ability for the
environment to just not be
there, or for feature
detection to help us understand
and live within the
contours of whatever
the runtime is.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So I think it's
about time we moved on to
the next question.
And this one's from
Natasha Rooney.
So if we can get Natasha
a microphone?
NATASHA ROONEY: Hi.
Thank you, very much.
So should network information
APIs be extended to include
triggers for a user having less
than optimal connection
speeds and not just offline
or online triggers?
Could this help developer's
courage for content caching?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So this is a
question that came up at the
last Edge Conf.
And this was voted up quite
high in the moderator.
But I also had some people
coming up to me and saying,
this just really went on too
long and was really boring at
the last Edge Conf, this kind
of debate, whether we should
be offering developer
information about the
connection speed.
So as a compromise, I'd like
each of the panelists to
answer the question, making
only a sound.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So in a sound,
should the developer be given
details on the current
connection speed?
ALEX RUSSELL: Neh.
CRAIG CAVALIER: It doesn't
bother me.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: That's
not a sound.
You can leave now.
MATT ANDREWS: [INAUDIBLE].
JAKE ARCHIBALD: That's
not a sound.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Eh?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Eh.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: OK.
That's a good percentage of
the panelists kind of, eh.
But we should have a serious
discussion about the-- we've
got these online, offline
event triggers.
And so how should we be
using them to make
something work offline?
Should we build, assuming the
network is there, and then
fall back using this method?
Or should we build, assume
offline is there?
And you had an example, Alex,
with using offline detection.
ALEX RUSSELL: The online
thing is a lie.
I think that's really what
it boils down to.
It's a dirty, nasty,
terrible lie.
And the only thing that you'll
ever be able to do that's
meaningful is to ping
your service, right?
You'll be able to send a request
out to your service.
And if you get a response back
under deadline-- like let's
say you've got a performance
guarantee
that you need to meet.
And you get a response
back under
deadline from your service.
Great.
So it's over HTTPS.
It's from your service.
Things look legit.
Any other case is failure.
But it's just a giant panoply
of potential failure cases
that would all be online under
some strict definition of I
connected to the radio, and
I got a TCP [? socket ?]
warmed up.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Craig,
Calvin, did you use the
.online in anything
you're doing?
Or did you want that
kind of extra
detection around the network?
CRAIG CAVALIER: We've made use
of the online and offline.
We don't have so many
requirements for the gray area
of not having a decent
amount of connection.
So for us, we tell the user
whether they can sync or not,
based on whether they have
this online or offline.
But as he said, in a lot
of cases, online
is a bit of a lie.
But for our users, when they
have a connection, they have a
connection.
And it's often that they've
come back off of a rig and
they're at a hotel and
they're making use of
the connection there.
So for us, just having the
yes and no is enough.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think we'll
take a question from the
audience from [? Shavasse? ?]
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Just to add,
I think it will also get
easier, once browser's and
OSes get more capable at
detecting captive portals.
And I know, like Mozilla, we're
going to add this to
Firefox, in case the OS falls
through and figuring out if
you're in a captive portal.
And then tell the web pages
they're offline and not give
them a false impression
and stuff.
[? SHAVASSE: ?]
When caching AppLogic rather
than content, is there a way
to cache free JITed code, A, so
that you don't need a JIT
for faster startup, and B, as
JITers gets more intelligent,
so that you can reuse what the
JITer learned about how your
app behaved for the last five
hours of usage, both for
offline and for online scenarios
as a faster startup.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Does anyone
want to take that?
CALVIN SPEALMAN: No.
That actually was an issue that
came up, I know, in the
assembly dot js project.
There is a very bad problem
there with the time it takes
to compile especially
large demos even.
The actual function, parsing,
compiling is all synchronous
in blocking.
So that's the issue that came
up there, not necessarily
being offline or reused, but
just the time it takes and
could it be asynchronous.
And so I know from that that,
right now, the only thing is
parsing it from the
raw JavaScript and
compiling it at the time.
It would be, I think, a really
important thing to look into,
if they're going to look into
asynchronous API, to also have
a way to then reuse
that result.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So back onto
the kind of network state
stuff, if I'm asking the
browser, am I online?
It's going to say, yes.
And what we're going to end up
with is it could just have one
bar or a kind of intermittent
bar of data, which eventually
is just going to take five
minutes to try getting
something from the network
and then ultimately fail.
Anne, is that something that
is solvable as a problem?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: That might be
harder, the case where the
captive portal gives
you a timeout.
But you would have to do
periodic checks or
something like that.
Yeah.
I think it might be there
forever, until captive portals
actually start returning
different status codes.
Like there is some kind of RFC
that makes captive portals
actually part of the network
stack, instead of just a hack.
You would still have some logic
in your application that
detects it as well.
Yeah.
It's hard to get away from,
given the legacy.
MATT ANDREWS: I think a more
analog kind of quality of
connection over the past
X period of time
will be more useful.
But really, I think, most of
the time, as long as you're
implementing error callbacks,
you can always try and fail
gracefully or offer something to
a user first and then fall
back to something else.
I think that's a much
better pattern.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think
we've got a follow-up
question from Natasha.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah.
Sorry.
Ooh.
Gosh.
So just to give a proper use
case from the reason why I
asked a particular question
which might be able to help,
[INAUDIBLE] subscription models
is probably the best
one to go on, which I know is
important for any publications
like "FT" and other
such newspapers.
What if a user who was on a
subscription method and that
meant that they kept out--
say they read 10 articles.
They read that on the tube--
which I'm also a tube user--
so they will read that
on the tube.
They consume that.
And then they violate
their subscription.
They've gone over, right?
So they shouldn't be able
to read any more.
So some trigger has to happen
at some point for it to go
back to the server to
say this user has
gone over their limit.
Don't give them any more.
So my real idea is trying to
understand how that can
happen, because that
has massive
implications for some markets.
Like I'm talking videos, as
well as publications.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So this is
offering the user a different
experience, if they are on
some kind of metered
connection where it's going to
disappear after a certain
points, or potentially bring
a financial situation.
Does the phone even know if the
user is in that situation?
CRAIG CAVALIER: A lot of times
I've found that it's not
necessarily the technology that
has to care about that.
There's usually a business
process around this.
So for instance, if you're in a
banking system, you're going
to a cash point and you
withdraw some cash.
If your spouse has gone to
another cash point and
withdrawn that amount as well
and that would take you over
your overdraft, they've
got this concept of
overdraft in banking.
So they've got a set way
of handling that.
And usually in these business
scenarios, there are business
processes for handling
those cases.
So for instance, in the case of
your videos, I've watched a
couple of videos offline.
Someone else has used
my account to
watch a few more offline.
Then there must be some kind of
consolidation, some kind of
process to pick up those pieces
and then trace that
back to the billing.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Are we
collectively happy with a
mobile site or app sending
us into our overdraft?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I think we're
collectively unhappy
about that even being
a possibility.
Like the whole bandwidth cap
thing is like bullshit and
should be gone at some point.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Well, I've been
in situations where my
phone knows that I'm roaming.
But I've actually managed to get
a deal with the provider
where I essentially have the
same quality and amount of
data that I have at home.
I guess if an app at this point
was to serve me lower
quality content, I'd be a
bit annoyed about that.
I'm being treated as a second
class citizen when I'm not in
that situation.
So I mean, is this going to be
a site per site option to say
can you be easy on the data?
Or should sites just be doing
easy on data by default?
ALEX RUSSELL: I think there was
a billing issue, not so
much about the data that Natasha
was bringing up.
But there's some
non-packet-based metric for
use, right?
So the question I always
ask is, what
is a Wikipedia article?
Is it the text?
Is it the history?
Is it all the images that
are part of it?
Is it the set of things
that it's linked to?
Is it the URL?
It's actually probably a
bundle of actual binary
resources and then some
ephemeral metadata around it.
And so you're talking about
consuming one of those at a
time, right?
So if I'm on "FT" or the "New
York Times," or whatever, and
I'm clicking through, how
do I get to my limit?
And then how do I
enforce that?
Not to go design a solution for
enforcement for anybody,
but you can imagine a relatively
straightforward
sort of soft landing for users
where there's a bit of code on
the client that's watching usage
and then it attempts to
enforce some soft limit with a
cap, with one or two extra.
And then at some point later,
if you haven't synced in N
number of days, then maybe the
content becomes inaccessible.
I mean, those are the sorts of
solutions that folks who have
to implement DRM are doing
today for things like my
[INAUDIBLE]
offline data, right?
You have to show that you're
willing to be part of the
ecosystem for some period of
time, otherwise the device
itself decides to
stop playing.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think
we'll take another
question from the audience.
Henrik, where abouts are you?
Get that man a microphone.
Just throw it.
ALEX RUSSELL: That's a good
question, [INAUDIBLE]
microphone.
HENRIK : So this is back at
the permission model.
It seems like, at the point
you're going offline, you're
making a fundamentally
different type
of app than a website.
There's a distinction
between a site and a
website at that point.
It's very clearly an app.
And you're talking
about requesting
permission for storage.
But also, that's a perfect time
to ask for permission for
other things as well.
So there's this whole
installable model that you're
seeing a little bit in
Android and Chrome
installed apps as well.
Is there standards efforts to
really unify that experience?
Like for example, if I'm going
to do video conferencing, why
shouldn't I be able to ask for
that upfront as a mandatory
requirement?
And if they say no,
then sorry, I
can't install the app.
I mean, whatever.
I mean, that's just
an example.
But unifying that, standardizing
that process,
and seeing that as the
permission point where you ask
for everything that you need.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I feel like I
could sink the rest of the
panel into a discussion of do
apps actually exist as a term?
Or is it just a bit of marketing
fluff like web 2.0?
MATT ANDREWS: Let's
not go there.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: But we're
not going to go there.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I feel
Alex already answered
his question earlier.
Like he said, on the web you
want to feel gracefully for
each of the things.
So you don't want to bundle and
then get the user to give
up his location data, all his
storage, and all those things.
You want to let the user be in
control, which sort of argues
in the way of doing a
per feature grant.
HENRIK: Yeah.
But isn't that always going
to make you a second-class
citizen to the installed app?
ALEX RUSSELL: I don't
think so.
So just to answer directly, I
don't think that makes you a
second-class citizen to the
installed applications for a
couple of reasons.
One, it leaves it up to the
system to mediate the length
and breadth of that
grant, right?
So you can imagine that iOS
versus Android running the
same application.
As long as the API is the same,
they can make different
choices about how often to
prompt someone about a thing.
Secondly, you can imagine this
being a consent and review
kind of a system where users
are always able to see the
list of permissions that are
currently granted to do a
thing, and maybe choose to give
it forever and/or revoke
it entirely.
And as long as the API allows
revocation to happen--
you say you demand this thing,
well, I think it's not
reasonable to demand a thing
at install time.
I think it's reasonable to try
to explain that behavior in
context of use, right?
I click on a link to go do
a thing and you say no?
OK, great.
I did a thing and then we had
a conversation about it.
And then you can tell me
why you need me to do
that thing for you.
It's not fool proof.
And it may train users
the wrong way.
But it's at least a start at
having a conversation about
why you want permissions.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I can maybe
see in a way how it's
second-class from a developer's
perspective.
But I think, from a user's
perspective, it's
a way better deal.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Can we get the
microphone to Kyle Simpson for
the next question?
But first, Matt, you with the
"Financial Times." taking that
stuff offline, some of
that stuff was quite
heavy due to imagery?
MATT ANDREWS: Yeah.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Did you
deal with that in
any particular way?
Did you ask the user within your
app before doing that?
MATT ANDREWS: So when you
first laid out the app,
originally, it was
designed for iOS.
And their limitation in iOS is
you can have 5 megabytes of
[INAUDIBLE]
storage without permission.
So we first gave them 5
megabytes of data, which is
they ask for it, basically.
And then, once they've used the
app a bit or it pinches
their home screen and actually
using it properly, we
then ask for more.
So I think you can definitely
design your applications so
that you have a set number of
mandatory requirements, and
then you add things on.
It starts off as a website.
You can always fall back
to being a website.
All this stuff is extra.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I've just caught
myself on the screen
looking like I'm advertising
the thing I'm drinking.
So I'm going to balance it out
by saying it's actually quite
disgusting.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: We've got a
question now from Kyle.
Ah.
Kyle's over there.
KYLE SIMPSON: So usually, I am
the one who's screaming for
more APIs, more functionality
to be given to us.
But I'm going to flip the table
here and say, going with
the theme that browsers are
generally better at a lot of
these tasks, as a developer of
apps and sites, one thing I'd
really not like to deal
with is the idea
of online and offline.
So one idea that I would just
want to bounce and see if you
think would be possible.
We've talked a lot about
persisting the actual app, the
files that make the app run.
But what about all the
network requests?
Could the browser proxy the
requests that I'm making for
me, and then, when I come back
online, prompt me and say, do
you want to still send
these tweets?
Do you want to still
send these emails?
Because you requested that
a few minutes ago.
That way I, as an app developer,
don't have to think
about those details.
I just make the app, assume
online, and let the browser
take care of it.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: I think,
actually, there's two areas
there that need to be addressed
differently, which
is things and things you do,
keeping the data locally first
and allowing synchronization
to happen
separate from your app.
For example, CouchDB has a
PouchDB layer that will be
implemented inside
the browser.
And you have all your
local data.
And the synchronization happens
as a separate process.
Synchronizing API calls like
tweets and things, I don't
think it makes sense to do
separately or to queue up in
the background, because the user
needs to know that that
hasn't happened yet.
You can't just make the tweet
and say here's my API call.
I hope the browser did it
sometime later, maybe.
You have to tell the browser
or the browser user, this
hasn't sent yet.
This hasn't completed.
They have to know
what's going on.
ALEX RUSSELL: There's a related
issue, which is what
does it mean to get success
back from an API?
Like if I get a 200 response
and the return content is
error, how do I cut the browser
into the conversation
so that it retries?
KYLE SIMPSON: So I was under the
assumption that a browser
knows that it doesn't
have connectivity.
It tries to talk to the radio
and the radio doesn't give it
any sort of response back.
But also there's plenty of UIs
that we do this already.
Like when I'm downloading files,
there's UIs that tell
me the status of my downloads
and let me unpause it.
So I don't understand why the
same sort of API couldn't
present to me, the user,
that here is the
requests that I've made.
And I want to say, yes, these
are OK to make, now that
you're back online, no, that
tweet is not one I want to
send out, or whatever.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: It sounds like
the difference between
adaptive requests and predictive
requests, in terms
of what we expect to get
from the network.
Is that something that
comes into this?
Are we going to have
APIs around that?
ALEX RUSSELL: I think there's
a fundamental difference
between the download case that
you just tried to outline and
these other cases, which is
that, in the download case,
we're talking in terms of a
single resource that the
browser knows everything
about.
The browser knows the entire
protocol for downloading a
file, right?
And in fact, it's the thing
giving you the UI for
downloading the file.
This is a situation in which
were asking the browser to
coordinate with the application
that it's hosting
to talk about mediating
that conversation
about content, right?
It's running the application
and then saying, hey
application, you're
doing stuff.
The user intends
to do a thing.
You're going to tell me what
that thing is and then tell me
how that relates to the
rest of the world.
And we don't have any higher
level semantic equivalence.
There's no way to tell the
browser, oh, this thing is
sending a tweet.
Processors don't know
what tweets are.
These are just different
data types.
One of them is a composite
data type and one
of them is a primitive.
And browsers are OK at
primitives they understand.
But when it comes to composites,
we have to give
applications control.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think
we're going to move
on to the next topic.
The next question is
from Nick Molnar.
Whereabouts are you hiding?
Over there.
Get a microphone over here?
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE].
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Oh.
That's good.
Someone was just going
to the toilet.
I thought they were
asking a question.
Never mind.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Should ask them
them a question anyway.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: That's
a bad omen.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Serve them
right for getting up.
NICK MOLNAR: All right.
So users only expect offline
behavior from apps downloaded
from their app store.
Will initiatives like iOS's
Startup image and Touch icon
ever be expanded to include a
full metadata set suitable for
web apps to finally be included
in app stores?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think this is
a very important question
because, even if we solve all
the API issues, we still have
that user expectation that they
do not think they can go
into the browser, type in a URL
and expect it to work when
they know they have
no connectivity.
So the guys have been building
stuff using the
current set of APIs.
What would you do to let the
user know that, yeah, this is
going to work?
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Well, I first
started looking at these
offline apps in Firefox 3.
So my choice then was I'm just
not going to use this, because
there's no solution.
And the point of that was,
it's been a long time.
We should have solved
this by now.
We do have a mechanism for our
users to keep the access to an
app or a website and to indicate
to the browser that
it's important to them and to
remember to come back to it.
It's the bookmark.
And we have this one
that's barely used.
And it makes a lot of sense
to connect that into the
permissions, into quotas, into
all these things that we need
to remember about a website.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Craig, you
built a specialized app for a
particular set of people.
How did you communicate to them
that, although this is a
browser, this is going
to work, this is
going to work for you?
CRAIG CAVALIER: We go about this
in different approaches,
depending on the different
requirements for hardware.
So one of the nice things about
iOS is you can add apps
to your home screen.
And that becomes kind
of difficult in some
of the other browsers.
I think you can add to
a home screen in
other browsers as well.
Yeah.
It's a bit shaky.
So yeah, it would be nice if
there was some way of saying,
hey, I want to be able
to install this.
I know Firefox have made some
progress in that direction
with the manifest file.
So you can specify things that
your application needs when
you install.
I think having some
standardization around those
kind of processes is going
to help companies like
us make that work.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Matt, your
site was open to all users.
You had to explain to them
that this was possible.
How do you do that?
MATT ANDREWS: Well iOS,
like you say, is easy.
The rest of them,
we just don't.
And unfortunately, this is one
of the reasons why we don't
see that many users on Chrome
for Android, even though the
app works absolutely
brilliantly on it.
And the Chrome Web Store-- you
said there was two ways of
making web apps work offline,
the Google Gaze and Appcache.
Chrome Web Store offers an
alternative approach.
And you can use that to get
your App icon on the
[INAUDIBLE]
menu.
And I think that would be really
nice to make that more
open and accessible
to other places.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Well, now is
there anything in the spec
that's going to make
this better?
Or how can we communicate this
better to users, that the web
will work offline?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: So we've been
looking into the manifest
thing and making that better.
But I think a lot of the
standards, how they evolve, is
like in small, incremental
steps.
So first, we need to
solve this offline
thing and get it right.
And then people can start
building apps.
And then we can start thinking
about how to improve
bookmarks, to make
that work better.
And then, long-term, hopefully,
we can obsolete the
concept of app stores entirely,
because you can just
browse the web and bookmark
things to your home screen and
no longer need those.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Can we get this
right, before we have the
mechanism for users to
realize it works?
Because we don't know we've got
it right, until we've got
users using it and we see the
behavior patterns and we see
the bits of the APIs that
aren't working.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I'll
check on that.
I guess you have to grow
into getting there.
You can't really just design the
whole thing up front and
then present it and
it just works.
MATT ANDREWS: When you say
"getting offline working
right," you mean the terminology
formally called
Navigation Controller, right?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Yeah.
Well, I'm hoping Service
Worker is the answer.
We'll have to find out.
We have to test.
We have to incrementally
evolve.
We're at the prototyping stage
now, so it's early days.
MATT ANDREWS: But from the
user's perspective, as much as
our cache is a bit loathed,
it does kind of work.
I mean, it will give you an
application that works offline.
Can't we not just fill in
that little step to get
that icon on there?
And then it will be compatible
with both?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: So the
problem with Appcache is that
we've got like a universal
no back from developers.
So people don't really want to
experiment with it and roll it
out on their sites.
Yeah.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Right.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: And if
there's no adoption, then we
can't really further experiment
with other things.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Alex, it
seems like the sentiment of
the rest of the panel is that
Chrome for Android's doing
this very badly, where the
installed Home screen is great
for [? us. ?]
Where is it?
ALEX RUSSELL: That's
a great question.
John?
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Are you prepared
to answer this, John?
JOHN: Uh-huh.
Sure.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: We'll get a
microphone to John, anyway.
And he can at least
tell us that he's
not allowed to answer.
ALEX RUSSELL: If I had
my druthers, we would
absolutely have that.
I mean, I think that's
a reasonable
thing to want to have.
I mean, my personal view-- and
I'm not speaking for Google
here-- is that the manifest
destiny of web apps is that
they can do everything
that apps can do.
Everything that your system
application should be able to
do, you should be able to write
as a web page first.
And then you should be able to
transition to a world that's
much more powerful.
And that just depends on getting
users to a point where
they believe that that's
a safe thing to do.
And if that's saying no to
some permissions to get
others, that sounds good, or
asking users to install or
bless a thing, that
seems reasonable.
But yeah.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: John, do have
a comment or no comment?
JOHN: Thank you, Alex.
I think we have a lot more to
do in this space to make web
apps more capable.
We're putting [INAUDIBLE].
We'll see what happens.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Well, we'll take
one more question here
from the audience.
CRAIG CAVALIER: One more
thing to add on that.
Being that Chrome for Android,
the Navigation Controller--
sorry, the installable apps
is only part of that.
And we found that, actually,
Chrome for Android has the
best [? of all ?] of things like
IndexedDB, which we don't
get on other devices
like Safari on iOS.
So we need to have that problem
solved consistently
across browsers because, at the
moment, we have to rely on
things like shims to fall
back to webSQL.
And with iOS 7 and the five-meg
cap that we have for
the user prompt that now--
yeah, it's really important
to get that piece
of the puzzle solved.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Thanks,
for that.
We can declare war now between
iOS and Android now.
That's brilliant.
We're going to take one question
from the audience,
before we move topic.
Eric Sheppard?
Wherever I saw you.
A microphone over here.
ERIC SHEPHERD: This is sort of
a follow up, the flip side of
the payment question
from earlier for
the number of issues.
There are a whole host of other
things that you may want
to know about that, if people
start using the web offline in
large numbers, we're
going to lose.
Third-party networks want to
know things for tracking
purposes, for re-marketing
purposes.
We want to know what people are
looking at so that, when
we're giving more and more
customized recommendations in
e-commerce or article
recommendations in publishing,
those are things we wanted
to know about too.
Are any of the ad networks or
anyone looking into possible
APIs for how to deal with
this kind of stuff?
ALEX RUSSELL: I haven't been
talking to them and probably
should be, with regards to the
Service Worker design.
But I can only talk about
the thing I'm working
on, which is that.
And it allows you to--
a thing I put on the screen oh
so briefly was the import
scripts API, which
allows a worker--
these things are
just workers--
a worker of any kind to just go
out and import some other
script, like a require
call in [? AMD, ?]
something like that, right?
So you can compose behavior from
multiple origins so that,
if you're working with a
third-par;ty, you could
include their offline
handling code too.
And because the service worker
sees requests for all origins,
including those third-party
ones, you can write your
handlers in such a way that
well-behaved service worker
scripts will only pay attention
to the requests for
their origin and do the
right thing by them.
And you can import scripts
from other origins to do
things like handling those kinds
of tracking and counting
when offline.
And they get the ability to run
when you're online too.
So they'll be able to do their
own synchronization.
It does require the global
coordination thing that we
love so much about
Java scripts.
And so we get ES6 modules.
But I think that's
going to be the
state-of-the-art for a while.
It's possible.
It will require care.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: OK.
We're going to move on
to the next question.
And the next question is asked
by Jake Archibald.
Oh, not that guy again.
OK.
Well, this is a bit weird.
So I should probably ask the
question-- oh, John's back.
Hello.
JOHN: This on?
Yes.
We are actually working
on adding [INAUDIBLE]
Chrome for Android--
it's a public commit, so I can
talk about it, excellent--
coming soon, hopefully.
I think that we had an about
flag recently, it's in
[INAUDIBLE].
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Declassified.
Excellent.
OK.
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE]
install?
JOHN: Oh.
And I think Vivian
was asking--
VIVIAN: I'm interested in
knowing if the [INAUDIBLE]
want to have the similar API
like iOS, allow you to have
the API access to prompt
the user to
install on a home screen?
MATT ANDREWS: Yes.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: OK.
I'll take that as the whole
panel's opinion.
[LAUGHTER]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So onto the
question from this Jake
Archibald guy.
I'm going to try and read in
a different accent, so it
doesn't seem super weird.
Maybe that will make it
seem even weirder.
I'll sit over here slightly.
So I'll do an American accent.
I'll try and do your accent.
So currently, if a post fails,
I can stick it in IndexedDB
and post it later, right?
But if the user has to visit
the site later to actually
send that data, how
can I do that?
Is there a better
way for that?
That's a very good
question, Jake.
Yeah.
We're going to put that to the
whole panel right now.
So yeah.
We don't have anything to
do synchronization.
Is there a sync API coming?
Can we do this when the
user's not actually
sitting on the site?
CALVIN SPEALMAN: So I think
that there are background
needs for APIs added in Firefox
OS for things like
push notifications and that
there is a definite
possibility of integrating the
need for those to happen in
the background whenever you
don't even have the tab open
to also be built upon to have
some kind of synchronized
process or cronjobs
for your websites.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Craig,
you have this
specific problem, right?
CRAIG CAVALIER: We do.
I mean, going back to the
question of having it running
in the background, it's kind
of tricky because, firstly,
you've got situations like,
actually, does the user really
want to be syncing when
they don't know it?
I mean, we could be eating up
all of their bandwidth for
roaming, for instance.
So in some cases, it makes a lot
more sense for it to be an
explicit question [INAUDIBLE].
But in other cases also, and
particularly for business
data, you have this process of
making business decisions when
merge conflicts happen.
So for us, we do something
that's kind of similar to a
git rebase when we're
synchronizing.
So we actually can prompt the
user and say, hey, we've
detected that these two events
happened and they conflict
with each other and you need
to take some action.
So that's running in
the background.
That becomes kind of tricky.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So, Alex,
Anne, you guys
are from the future.
What's in the future for us?
ALEX RUSSELL: You have to
do this in his accent.
[LAUGHTER]
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I'm not
sure I can do that.
I think push notifications
will have to be opt-in.
I think background updates for
apps like for your caches and
stuff, we can do if the user
is connected to wireless.
I guess, in that case, we can
assume there won't be a cap,
although, it's not
universally true.
In Russia and stuff, they still
have quite low caps,
even on those kind
of connections.
So there has to be a preference
of sorts.
Like do you want to allow apps
to update in the background?
And it could even be a
preference that the user wants
his apps always up-to-date,
even on 3G or 4G.
And the browser will just, every
now and then, wake of
the worker and give it the
event to start updating.
And then the worker does
its updates and then
it shuts down again.
And when the user next visits
the site, he'll get all the
latest stuff.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So we're going
to go to the audience for the
next question, Jeffrey
Burtoft.
Where abouts are you?
Down here.
JEFFREY BURTOFT: Yeah.
I guess this ties in
a little bit more
with the last question.
So there are a lot of developers
in Microsoft
platform who are developing for
both our store apps, which
are HTML5-based, and then for
the web apps and trying to
bring those closer together.
One of the questions I hear a
lot about web apps is about
the safety of the data that is
stored, which I think tends to
push us more towards developing
in the native space.
What are we doing to make sure
that that data can be trusted,
can be safely encrypted and meet
needs of different type
of developers?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So if we're
storing something like credit
card data or people's contact
information, what can we do to
make sure that other apps
can't sneak in there
and get that data?
Is it something we do already?
CRAIG CAVALIER: I think there
is a certain amount of that.
I mean, you have to be on the
same domain to be able to
access things like
local store.
So there's a certain amount
of security in place.
There's only so much you can do,
I think, with these kind
of devices.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN:
I'm not sure.
Is the question about what
the origin can access?
Or if someone has physical
access to the device, they can
access the local stored data
because it's not encrypted.
So in that case, it depends on
the security characteristics
provided by the OS.
And I think, in all the cases,
browsers default to what the
OS provides and don't have
additional layers on top.
Because if the OS is not
secured, then you're
compromised anyway.
ALEX RUSSELL: It depends on the
threat model, obviously,
but there is an API called Web
Crypto API, which Microsoft is
heavily involved in working
with Netflix and eBay and
Google and a bunch of other
people on this.
And one of the key aspects of
the Web Crypto API is that it
allows you to have wrapped
keys, which is are just
hardware tokens or tokens
protected by the OS which are
not owned by user space code, so
you can't actually see the
key material.
And you can do operations
with that.
So in that world, as long as you
trust the OS, you should
be able to get encrypted content
stored and allow that
to be trusted all the way
through the search chain back
to the server.
And I think that's a pretty
deft answer, actually.
I think it gives you most of
the control that you want,
without giving you most of the
complexity that you would like
not to have.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: And I think
that takes us out of time.
I know the bathrooms at Google
UK are completely out of Wi-Fi
and cellular data.
So it sounds like, if we can get
all this stuff solved, I
can be a lot more productive
than I am currently in my
spare time.
But if you're interested in any
of this stuff and want to
look at the spec as it is
currently, it's github.com/--
ALEX RUSSELL: slightlyoff/--
JAKE ARCHIBALD: serviceworker,
right?
ALEX RUSSELL: serviceworker,
yes.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Excellent.
MATT ANDREWS: When will we
get that in a browser?
ALEX RUSSELL: So I can't speak
for Firefox, but I know that
there's prototypes happening
on the Mozilla side.
And on the Chrome side,
we've built a
prototype which does work.
And we're in the process
of implementing now.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Excellent.
Well, thank you very
much, everyone.
[APPLAUSE]