SCOTT JENSEN: Can we bring up
the QR code for the session?
Or is that something we have
to do next, after the talk?
After the talk.
So then I will save my little
talk for later, then.
We have a very, very good panel
here of people who are
extremely experienced in,
basically, realtime data.
I strongly recommend that
you just read the panel
introduction from all of them.
We've got Henrik Joreteg right
here, John Fallows, Wesley,
who actually did this lovely
onslyde demonstration as well,
which, by the way,
is right there.
And then to my left, we
have-- is it Martyn?
Martyn, Rob, welcome.
Now that we have the onslyde
up, I really strongly
recommend that you guys
take a look at
that and get it started.
As a perfect introduction to
this talk, If you are on an
iPhone, and you bring up that
web page, and it goes to
sleep, you must refresh the
page, because the website gets
closed down automatically--
perfect introduction as
to why we're here.
I also would like to try using
it during this talk.
So as many of you as possible
can bring it up.
We'll ask some questions
along the way.
We'll see how it goes.
But I think right now, we need
a general introduction.
That's what Henrik's here
for, so please.
HENRIK JORETEG: All right,
let's see if I can get my
slides back on this screen
here, maybe.
Here we go.
Hi, guys.
My name is Henrik Joreteg.
I work at a company called &yet,
and I've been building
realtime web apps now for
about four years.
We started out using XMPP, and
strophe.js, and BOSH, and
XMPP, and all that stuff back
in the day, long polling.
Then WebSockets came out.
We started messing with that,
socket.io and the like.
Recently have gotten
really into WebRTC.
I think it's useful, before we
get to into the technical
stuff, to step back a minute and
realize what this really
does in terms of the web.
The web is really about
human communication.
And so these are my kids, and
they love their grandparents.
The problem is, their
grandparents live in Sweden.
For those of you who with a
typical American geographic
understanding, it's far away.
[LAUGHTER]
HENRIK JORETEG: Sorry.
That's low.
I'm sorry.
This is not this
crowd, I know.
So every Sunday, my kids get to
talk to my parents over an
app we built called Talky.io,
that uses WebRTC.
Talky.io is the first time I've
ever built that actually
passed the mom test, meaning
my parents can use it.
What it is is anytime you're on
the same URL, you're in the
same conversation.
That's all there is to it,
so no login, no auth, no
friending, nothing.
And it's using WebRTC.
There's nothing to install.
It just works.
So to me, it just serves as a
very practical example for how
ultimately these realtime
technologies are actually
bringing people together and
helping make the web better.
So let's talk a little
bit about WebRTC.
We're going to cover other stuff
too, but I want to focus
on this a bit, because it's been
a recent focus of mine.
WebRTC really is a lot more
than video in a browser.
It's actually a low-latency
peer-to-peer networking, and
that's really exciting.
So one of the other cool
examples of what you can do
with this technology
is called PeerCDN.
PeerCDN was actually built
by the same guy
who did Google Instant.
But anyway, it's this really
cool concept of where--
it actually uses data channels
to send files to
other current visitors.
So say, for instance, I'm
hosting a simple little video
site right, and I'm actually
hosting my own videos.
All of a sudden, I'm on Reddit
and I'm getting slammed.
So normally, that would be
expensive for bandwidth.
But in this case, the swarm of
people that are gathering on
your site to watch this footage
can actually download
it from each other.
So you kind of create this
almost ad hoc like BitTorrent
type network, which is really
fascinating, and just kind of
an example of what you
do with this stuff.
Also, given recent stuff with
the NSA and with encryption,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera,
I actually think
WebRTC is really important
for the web.
It's decentralized.
It's encrypted.
Yes, maybe there's backdoors.
Who knows?
But ultimately, this is stuff
that we should be doing, and
it's a big win for the web.
So how are we doing so far?
Well, let's start
with a story.
A year ago, we built att.js.
att.js was kind of a
demonstration used at CES by
AT&T to demonstrate making and
receiving actual phone calls
in a browser using WebRTC, which
was cool we got it to
work, but with way
too many caveats.
It actually required running a
certain modified version of
Chromium that the Ericsson
team was maintaining--
not ideal.
It's gotten better.
So if you look at this, here
what we actually have is a
Nexus 4 running Firefox Nightly,
a Nexus 7 running
Chrome for Android, and then a
desktop running Firefox Stable
and Chrome Stable,
all in the same
conversation at the same time.
It's gotten better.
It's available now on some
mobile devices, and
interoperability is improving
for voice and video.
Sweet, so we're good.
We can all go home.
We should just use
this, right?
Nope.
WebRTC is still quite finicky,
and if you try to do anything
with it, you've probably
discovered this.
So just to give an example,
here's what you have to do to
set up a video call right
now between two users.
So first of all, getting
user media-- it
sounds really simple.
You request access to
their camera and
their microphone, right?
You'd think.
The methods are still prefixed,
which is fine.
I mean, that's to be expected.
They throw very different
error types.
So in Firefox, the error handler
that you give it will
give you a string back.
In Chrome, it will give you
an error object, as
it's supposed to.
But neither quite follows the
spec as far as telling you
what went wrong.
So in addition, specifying
constraints for like, hey, I
want a smaller video, is
available with limited support
in Chrome, and not at all in
Firefox at the moment.
Screen sharing, which is
actually really important for
replacing something like Skype
or Google Hangouts, is
available in Chrome, but it's
behind a flag, very hard to
detect error types,
requires HTTPS.
So even if you're running local
host, and if you don't
have your own self-signed cert
or something, it'll just fail
silently, and you
won't know why.
So as a result, what do we do?
We create abstractions.
So we wrote a getUserMedia
module to handle that part.
Attaching a media stream--
so once you request media, you
have this stream object, and
it's your job to then attach
that to, say, a video element
or an audio element.
This has gotten better.
The APIs are more similar now.
But you have to convert
into a blob URL,
attach it as a source.
In Chrome, you set
autoplay to true.
In Firefox, you attach
it and call play.
Point is, there's differences.
And often, you want to mute the
user's own video so they
don't echo back to themselves,
et cetera.
So again, now that's another
thing that should be simple
now has become another module
that we're making.
So beyond that, a thing that a
lot of people don't understand
about peer-to-peer is
ultimately, you have to have
some mechanism for the two peers
to discover each other.
It's not like we just magically
know each other's
external IPs and we can just
send stuff directly.
And this is not in
the spec at all.
It's purposely left out, so
it's totally greenfield.
I actually think that's good.
But that means as a developer,
you have to
do a lot more work.
You have to help the users
discover each other.
You have to help them figure out
how to pass data messages
directly to another user, which
is now something that's
necessarily in the
tool belt of the
average JavaScript developer.
So now you need some kind of
server technology as well to
be able to handle this.
With socket.io, it's not hard,
but it's still something
that's new for a
lot of people.
In addition, you have to do
some level of capabilities
detection for certain things.
So for example, if you do screen
sharing from Chrome, it
won't appear for
a Firefox user.
But there's no way that
you would know that
programmatically without
specifying through the
signaling channel that hey,
you've got users in this chat
who are actually on Firefox.
So there's just a few
oddities like that.
So then we write a
signaling server.
So peer connection-- so
this is the mother.
This is the thing that
does it all.
This has some quirks as well.
So first of all, the
prefix, which is,
again, to be expected.
I don't think that's
a bad thing.
CreateDataChannel--
so this is the data stuff that
we're going to talk about.
This is extremely finicky
at the moment.
So you have to pass a very
specific set of options to
create a reliable channel versus
a unreliable channel.
It's supposed to be reliable
true or false, but that
doesn't actually work
in either browser.
As I was just talking to Kyle
about, there is an upload
limitation in the default
settings for Chrome.
So in order to actually get this
to work, if you want to
pass a file around, you have
to actually modify the FTP
that you send--
tricky stuff.
So anyway, we write a
wrapper for that.
Other challenges--
data channels are currently
not at all interoperable
between Chrome and Firefox.
You can only do one video
stream per connection.
And all of this is just--
there are other browsers
that will do this.
So it's not going to
get any better.
WebRTC is also unique in that--
this is actually the
first time I know of where
browsers have to speak
directly to each other.
There's no intermediary.
So once you set up a signaling
channel, they better be
interoperable.
That's a whole new level of
spec compliance that's
required in order to
make that work.
And I can only imagine how
interesting it will be if
Microsoft and Internet
Explorer decide
to do this as well.
So I wrote a library called
simpleWebRTC.
Just basically, you provide
a container for local, you
provide a container for remote
videos, and when it's ready,
you join the room
and it works.
Makes a bunch of assumptions,
but this is the kind of stuff
you need in order to actually
make this approachable.
There's alternatives,
obviously.
There's PeerJS, focused on data
channels, OpenTok, and
there's another guy who's done
a bunch of interesting
experiments.
I'm kind of running
out of time here.
Anyway, the big thing I think
that's really important is
tinkerability is actually what
drives adoption of new
technologies.
So we like to play with new
stuff, but not everybody does.
So in the same way that jQuery
made the DOM accessible to
lots of people, socket.io
made WebSockets
accessible to a lot of people.
Abstraction libraries such
as simpleWebRTC--
I don't care if it's that or
something else-- but hopefully
makes it accessible to
more people as well.
And we really just need more
open web hackers to really get
into this stuff and build
things with it.
If not, it's going to be
relegated into one of these,
like, hey, this would have
been nice, and it never
actually worked.
I really think that if you have
haven't been playing with
WebRTC, get in there, built
stuff with it, make it happen.
It's phenomenal technology.
It just needs people
to make it work--
so file bugs, feedback,
improve APIs, push for
interoperability.
We made a little site with
a compatibility chart.
We're also piping kind of
feedback data from actual
humans about the quality
of the connections.
But I encourage you
get involved.
Let's make the open web even
more awesome with WebRTC.
Thanks, guys.
[APPLAUSE]
MALE SPEAKER: OK, first as a
test, can we bring up the
moderator screen again?
OK.
I want to see.
We have 40 people connected
right now.
Let's just do a quick test.
How many of you would
be lying if you said
you liked the talk?
This is a test.
It was a logic question, guys.
Work with me here.
Excellent, good.
I just wanted to see if we
got lots of numbers.
That's all I wanted to see.
So OK, now that that's working,
I would like to
follow what Steve said, which
is to have each person take
about 60 seconds to say any
comments, things you'd like to
add on Henrik's introductory
talk.
So if we could start
with Martyn.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Is
this working?
So Henrik's done some great work
on WebRTC, and it's very
interesting, especially
the data channel
stuff, in my opinion.
But I think we shouldn't
forget about other
technologies.
WebSockets, it's only
two years old.
It's only just now becoming
really available in a lot of
browsers, and there's a huge
amount of stuff we can do with
a TCP connection
to the browser.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
Rob?
ROB: Yeah, I mean, there's not
a huge amount to add to that.
But from my point of view, I
think what's most interesting,
particularly with WebRTC,
is the use
beyond audio and video.
So I'm keen to discuss a little
bit more into those use
cases, perhaps games, the CDN
stuff, just hearing a little
bit more about what's next.
I mean, we have the
implementation today, and
there's issues with that.
But what could we do next
to make things better?
MALE SPEAKER: Excellent.
John?
JOHN FALLOWS: I agree with the
point made earlier about other
technologies being highly
relevant here.
I think they're each set out to
solve different problems.
And the talk about the point
about signaling channels, I
think going through a server
intermediary, technologies
like WebSocket are ideally
suited to that.
And WebRTC, of course, is
ideally targeted at the
peer-to-peer direct
connectivity.
So I see it as a very powerful
blend of technologies as the
web evolves going forward.
MALE SPEAKER: And Wesley?
WESLEY: Yes.
The centralized part
is a little--
we've got to get past that.
But for instance, for this tool,
all the remotes you're
holding your hand, it would be
cool if we pull up WebRTC to
use the mic.
And that way, you wouldn't have
people running around
handing mics out.
So there's so many use cases,
so many possibilities.
MALE SPEAKER: Excellent.
OK, I think we'd like to move
to our first question.
I think that's Andrew Betts,
if you'd like to--
do we have a microphone
for Andrew?
ANDREW BETTS: I've actually
got the lapel mic,
so I should be fine.
I've got 100 notes here, so
just bear with me second.
So WebSockets and other
realtime protocols are
commonly blocked by corporate
proxies and content inspection
firewalls, and that's a
particular problem for the
customers we have at the FT.
How much is this stifling
adoption, and what
can we do about it?
MALE SPEAKER: Would anyone
like to take that?
JOHN FALLOWS: So I think, just
taking a little step back into
history, when WebSocket was
first added to the HTML5
specification, it wasn't
even called WebSocket.
It was called TCP connection.
And when we saw that show up, we
decided to hop on that and
try to improve the protocol to
make it web-centric and bring
HTTP to bear, so it
was actually a
web-compatible handshake.
And the reason that we did that
was to avoid tripping
over some of the problems we've
seen before on plugin
technologies getting defeated
by corporate firewalls.
So we felt that was a huge step
in the right direction.
Now, even given that, we still
find situations where even
though all the traffic might be
over port 80 and 443, even
with recrypting firewalls and
things like that, that they
can still intercept.
But it's definitely a much
better situation
that it used to be.
And in our particular case at
Kaazing, we've implemented
some heavy lifting on the
emulation side to even be
resilient in those situations.
Initially, we wrote the
emulation stuff to kind of
precede the adoption of the
standard so we could get
started with socket
architectures
over five years ago.
But moving forward, it tends
to become something that's
still there to support older
clients, but also to address
that any intermediaries that
might be getting in the way.
MALE SPEAKER: Are you saying
it's not a problem, or it's
easy to work around?
JOHN FALLOWS: On the vanilla RFC
support for the protocol,
encryption is a big help.
But even in those situations,
there can be intermediaries
that will decrypt and recrypt
on the critical path and can
still intercept.
And then there's also many
WebSockets that don't want to
be encrypted for other
reasons, in terms of
performance and things
like that.
From our perspective,
we've seen it be an
issue in the wild.
For non-compliant browsers
trying to do emulation, we
found ways in our emulation
technique to address those
shortcomings.
MALE SPEAKER: Any
other comments?
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I'll just
make one little comment.
I would say for this
kind of audience,
there's very little barrier.
You can jump on with
WebSockets.
But if you really want to
address all use cases, as John
says, SSL does help.
But you need to think about
other fallback strategies.
One of the things that would
really help, and which we
maybe could think about, is we
do, at Pusher, a lot of work
to try to reuse successful
transports, again.
But we don't really have enough
information about the
browser's network connection
to always able to make good
connections.
So maybe that's something that
we can talk about later, how
we can discover--
like in the responsive images
discussion this morning, we
were saying that the browser has
more information than the
web application.
This is a case where the web
application could do with some
more information, really.
MALE SPEAKER: And the audience
clearly likes that comment.
One of the--
[LAUGHTER]
MALE SPEAKER: That
was awesome.
Keep that up.
That was awesome.
One of the comments on the
Google Monitor said that TLS,
actually, is an effective
way around this.
Any comments on TLS being
a useful thing?
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Yeah,
John just said that.
We find that.
But unfortunately, there
are examples.
I mean, for us, we've had
schools, for example, and they
often block SSL.
And there, you've got a kind
of pretty bad situation.
MALE SPEAKER: Do you
have any comments?
Do you want to move onto
the next question?
HENRIK JORETEG: Well, this
problem is very relevant to
WebRTC as well.
The whole concept of punching
through a firewall to get
something that you can push
directly to an end user is
actually really difficult.
And this is something that the
likes of Apple and Skype have
spent lots and lots of money
trying to solve.
And I would really love to see
some of these technologies be
more broadly available.
There's a few open
source projects.
There's a server called stund.
But a lot of these are really
difficult problems, and I wish
that there were more openly
well-documented solutions to
dealing with this, rather than
having to, as a blog post that
came out yesterday did, actually
try to decrypt what's
going on with Facetime, and
what they're doing to
multiplex ports, and
all kinds of stuff.
This is not my area of
expertise, but I know there
are people here who are really
good at this stuff.
And please, please
share your work.
This stuff is needed in order
to make WebRTC good.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
The next question is
up by someone--
is it Gus [? Gusenz? ?]
If we can get him
a mic, please.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
There seems to be some
functional overlap between
WebSockets and WebRTC.
When should you use
one or the other?
HENRIK JORETEG: I
can take that.
So the fundamental difference
is WebRTC is designed to be
peer-to-peer.
So WebSockets, if you're going
server-to-client, that's a
better use for that.
I think really where the
comparison comes from is the
fact that once you've
established a data channel,
it's largely the same API.
Beyond that, they're different
technologies.
So if you're going peer-to-peer,
WebRTC.
If you're going through a
server, then WebSockets.
MALE SPEAKER: Go
ahead, please.
ROB: I was just going to say,
one of the other main
differences as well is, again,
looking at beyond just video
and audio, say for example
multiplayer games.
WebSockets and WebRTC are
incredibly different because,
one's UDP and one's TCP.
So you have unreliable data
connections and reliable data
connections, which just allow
for a very different way of
doing multiplayer
communication.
You just cannot do a
twitch-based multiplayer game
using WebSockets, because you
have to wait for things to
come through.
But WebRTC is allowing us to
technologies that we've been
using in native environments
MALE SPEAKER: Do you want
to jump in on that?
HENRIK JORETEG: I was just going
to say, the support is a
little flaky for reliable and
unreliable data channels.
But it's part of the spec to
include both, so hopefully
that becomes easier to use.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: One of the
things I would think that
we're likely to see as the
unreliable data channels
become reliable is that
actually, people will want
implement this on
the server side.
And so to be able to communicate
with a game server
via UDP from a browser is
a pretty big thing.
JOHN FALLOWS: Yeah, I think
that's a great point.
And also, I think we touched
on it earlier as well about
using WebSocket server-centric
strategies for signaling and
setup around WebRTC is another
interesting variant.
One other thing I would mention
as well in deployments
in certain industries,
obviously, the security
boundaries of these things
often crop up.
So it's a very interesting
challenge to address some of
those boundaries of where the
trust boundaries reside
amongst the users and amongst
the server, in a consistent
manner across both
technologies.
MALE SPEAKER: Isn't there a
perception that this is like a
classic web thing, where we've
got one standard that doesn't
quite work, so we come up
with another standard
that overlaps a bit.
And it's just kind of confusing,
because they kind
of are somewhat related.
Or can we really say that
there's a pure vision of each
one of these things, and
they can both be
parallel and it's OK?
JOHN FALLOWS: As I said earlier,
I think these are
complementary technologies
that create a powerful
combination as we
move forward.
And I think they have
well-suited
purposes in each way.
I also think that there's
certain issues, like the
ability to successfully
navigate through these
firewalls and proxies on the
WebRTC side, that in some of
the fallback cases for WebRTC
for reachability, WebSocket
can potentially lend
a hand there too.
MALE SPEAKER: Cool, excellent.
We have another question,
then, from [? Mateas ?]
[? Kelzman. ?]
AUDIENCE: My question is, will
WebSockets protocol replace
server-sent events
in the future?
Why must we have both specs if
WebSockets can accomplish the
same tasks that SSE
does and more?
MALE SPEAKER: I think
that's another
example of possible overlap.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I can take
this if you like.
MALE SPEAKER: Please.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I would say
server-sent events is a very
simple protocol.
And so I think that drives a
lot of adoption early on.
But I think what we'll see,
especially as the WebSocket
spec gets more widely adopted,
and a lot of some of the
missing features become
available-- for example,
encryption is currently possible
with server-sent
events, but not WebSockets.
[?
HENRIK JORETEG: Bidirectional.
?]
MARTYN LOUGHRAN:
Yes, of course.
They're an extra
functionality.
But I think the question is,
for just the use cases that
one would currently use
server-sent events, what's
likely to happen?
For example, multiplexing is
another thing that might allow
people to use a single
connection to address many use
cases on the page.
JOHN FALLOWS: Just to add to
that, thinking back to when we
were working on the spec on this
stuff, comment was the
flavor of the day when
server-sent events was being
standardized as a way to
effectively standardize
comment behavior several
years ago.
And around that time, WebSocket
was starting up too,
so this exact question
came up during
standardization process.
And apart from the points that
have been made already, one of
the overarching arguments that
was left was that by having a
simplified interaction with
server-sent events, it created
a surface area where the browser
had more control over
the actual behavior.
And the idea was that on mobile
platforms, this might
actually allow the same
abstraction to be re-targeted
at mobile-specific solutions
that didn't necessarily
involve making a traditional
HTTP request over a
traditional TCP connection,
and getting a stream of
information coming
back down it.
So there are different
implementation strategies for
the abstraction.
If the abstraction is left
high, the versatility of
WebSocket obviously means that
you can cover that use case
and many more.
MALE SPEAKER: And Wesley, you
actually had a comment earlier
when we were talking about
possibly SPDY push.
It just adds to this layering.
WESLEY: Yeah.
So the way we send data to the
client, there's bidirectional,
there's WebSockets, there's SSE,
and now we've got HTTP
2.0 coming out.
And right now, what we can
implement is SPDY.
And that's available in node and
Jetty and other servers.
So we've got these three options
to choose how to push
data to the client.
And so with HTTP 2.0, is it
going to be WebSockets
layered over SPDY?
Is that going to be
the approach?
Or is it going to be pure
WebSockets, or is SPDY going
to have a mechanism to do
bidirectional push and then
also receive messages
on one channel?
That was kind of my question,
which I don't
know the answer to.
HENRIK JORETEG: Are there any
HTTP 2 experts in the crowd?
That would be really
interesting.
MALE SPEAKER: Don't be shy.
JOHN FALLOWS: Based on what I've
seen so far with SPDY,
I'd expect it to play out where
HTTP and WebSocket go in
parallel over the same enveloped
SPDY connection as
at least an option.
Because to keep WebSockets out
of that would be to create
additional resource hog on the
client end server connection
from the TCP endpoint.
So it seems like a very natural
consequence of having
selected an HTTP handshake that
gets started on WebSocket
to let them all play
nicely together.
MALE SPEAKER: Cool.
Any other comments people
want to make about this?
OK.
Christopher [? Frolik, ?]
you've got a question number
four coming up.
AUDIENCE: So the WebRTC spec
has driven centralized
solutions [INAUDIBLE]
et cetera to a decentralized
problem.
What we do to bring
up secure, fully
decentralized solution to bear?
HENRIK JORETEG: That's tricky.
Because ultimately,
you have to have
some discovery mechanism.
There are some attempts--
I forget the name of
the developer now.
There's a project where
basically you end up copying
and pasting SDP blobs back and
forth over whatever mechanism
you choose.
It could be email, it
could be whatever.
And it still uses STUN, ICE, and
TURN to actually connect.
And with firewalls, I don't
see that going away.
I mean, I don't know how
to solve that problem.
I would love to see
a solution.
MALE SPEAKER: I want to make
sure we also encourage people
to ask questions.
We're running through our
questions just fine, but feel
free to just jump in and
get on the delegate
list if you'd like.
Does anybody want to add
anything to that question
about centralized servers?
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I suppose one
of the questions is, when do
you need a decentralized
solution and when you do not
need a decentralized solution?
I mean, I'm not quite clear
on what exactly you mean.
What are the benefits that
you'd want to see from a
decentralized solution?
AUDIENCE: So the first example
that comes to mind is video
collaboration.
So my family and I, we've
all got smartphones,
high-resolution cameras in our
pockets, and we'd like to be
able to shoot and collaborate on
video together in realtime.
And the overhead in trying to
figure out where we are out
and back down to each other
seems like a lot when you just
want a simple way to connect
people that want to.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: OK, that's a
perfect example for WebRTC,
when you need that super
low-latency and UDP kind of
style communication.
It makes perfect sense.
HENRIK JORETEG: Well, in theory,
STUN and ICE should
help you locate and figure out
that they are, in fact, on the
same network, and then be
able to connect the two.
It's not a complete solution,
but it's something.
AUDIENCE: Sure, so just to
antagonize that point a bit,
if we're all independently
connected, say via mobile
data, so we're not on the same
network, and we're using just
a plain vanilla web app, there's
no clear path to a
central server, necessarily,
in a quick
and easy-to-use way.
HENRIK JORETEG: Right.
Now you're talking about
connecting devices they really
are not on the same
network at all.
And that's a whole different
type of problem, I think.
I mean, I think that
would be awesome.
But I don't know quite
how that--
I don't know how to
fix that one.
MALE SPEAKER: Kyle, actually, I
believe has got a question.
Let's make sure that
he gets a mic.
Is he sitting over there?
This is a delegate, so
can you make sure
you get him up there?
AUDIENCE: Hi.
So it seems like there's
two major reasons why
centralization still happens.
The first one's discoverability,
obviously.
If we don't have any way for
two different people to get
hooked up on a blind date,
then they don't know what
restaurant to show up at.
So somebody has to introduce
the two.
But that seems like that should
be solvable through
other bands.
Like, there's been other
peer-to-peer networks-- music
sharing, and BitTorrent, another
things like that.
It seems like there should be
ways to solve that problem.
But there's another problem,
that one of the reasons why
people centralize stuff
is because they
want to bill for it.
So when companies are creating
products around this stuff, if
we truly completely
decentralized, and everything
was peer-to-peer, nobody would
know that that was happening,
and nobody could make
a buck off of that.
So how do you see that attention
happening, where we
do want to get rid of
centralization, but we don't
want to not be able to charge
for it, for instance?
HENRIK JORETEG: I can
comment on that.
So in my opinion, the telecoms
of the future are Google,
Facebook, and the like.
The old traditional telecom
system is likely
not to stick around.
Somebody didn't like that.
[LAUGHTER]
HENRIK JORETEG: But really, I
mean, if you think about it,
the reason phones are so
successful and they're so
prevalent is because
I can call anybody.
I have an AT&T phone.
I can call somebody
on Verizon.
Why can't I call somebody
from Google+
from my Facebook account?
The whole concept of federation
does not currently
really exist in a broadly
accepted way in the web.
And I think the reason
is no one's pissed.
I mean, that's something that
if it was retroactively
imposed on--
[LAUGHTER]
HENRIK JORETEG: Now
people are pissed.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: So get to why web
standards is a bunch of
really, really great people
getting together.
HENRIK JORETEG: I guess.
I don't know.
So I don't know.
I mean, I think that's why
there's kind of this whole
silo effect going on.
MALE SPEAKER: But is
WebRTC architected
to solve that problem?
HENRIK JORETEG: Yes.
MALE SPEAKER: Isn't that
part of the issue?
It is solved?
HENRIK JORETEG: Yeah.
I mean certainly, it's providing
just a very base
level of technology, as far as
the communication piece.
But in order to actually connect
the two, you need
other technologies on top.
You need the discoverability
piece.
You need the addressability.
You need a strong identity
so you can say,
I am a Google user.
You can reach me at my Google
account, that sort of thing.
So WebRTC is one
of the pieces.
It's not all of it.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: And the great
thing about WebRTC is that
it's enabling all the web
developers in the world.
It's removing a huge number of
barriers from being able to
actually innovate
in that space.
For too long, we've had desktop
applications that have
not been able to.
ROB: I think the discoverability
side of things
as well is a big problem,
because right now, it's just
sort of, like you said,
up to the developers
and stuff like that.
And there's so many
ways to do it.
I mean, you could manually paste
these blobs and stuff,
which is stupid, but
you can do it.
But I mean, there are ways
that we need to--
we need to look at how to better
solve those kinds of
problems as well, like pairing
devices or things like that.
It's not always two people that
are trying to connect.
It might be one person trying
to connect two devices.
So for example, I might be
trying to connect a mobile
device to a TV to remote
control it.
The discovery mechanisms for
that are going to be
incredibly different than
connecting to people who have
full control over processing and
can just join a chat room
or something.
So those are the kind of
problems I want to see solved
[INAUDIBLE].
And people are kind of
approaching that, and there's
a few solutions with trying to
replicate things like Apple
Bonjour and stuff in the
browser, and requesting that
from the browser vendors.
But there's not been
significant
traction on that yet.
MALE SPEAKER: Well, it sounds to
me like there's going to be
a whole topology of
applications.
Like, an awful lot of websites
could just put in video chat
to our tech support line.
That will be a trivial thing for
them to do, because it's
entirely within their
own stack.
Then it's about getting
bigger.
And are you trying to say that
we need more standards for the
bigger to happen?
HENRIK JORETEG: I mean, these
things have existed
for quite some time.
XMPP is extremely stable and
extremely well-used.
And it's not something that
web developers like, but
they've gotten really good at
solving these problems.
And there's some efforts
underway, two specifically.
One is stanza.io, which is
basically the attempt to give
a clean JavaScript
API to XMPP.
And another one is XMPP-FTW,
for the web.
And thinking of things like
browser ID as a potential
alternative to be able to
provide that strong identity
piece, because once you have
that, addressability actually
becomes fairly simple
in terms of--
yeah, once you know
how to reach you.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: But these
solutions are all very
heavyweight solutions, right,
all the XMPP, even if it has a
nice JavaScript API one day.
I think what Rob's talking about
is just saying, well,
you've got two devices
next to each other.
Can they just make a little
chip, or some video
communication, or something
like that to
discover each other?
ROB: I think we're kind of
seeing people approach those
problems, and very, very
slightly at the moment, like
the whole idea of using audio
to connect two devices.
MALE SPEAKER: Boris Smus
did an ultrasonic demo.
Right, exactly.
ROB: Yeah, so there's people
already exploring, and
potentially not exactly in
this area, but there are
solutions around right now.
We've got a solution for pairing
Bluetooth devices and
stuff like that.
There's methods and means.
I think we've not seen people
use them just yet.
And we will, as people
start using WebRTC
beyond audio and video.
And that will just
come in time.
MALE SPEAKER: We've got a
question waiting from David,
actually, from the audience,
David Stickner.
And then we'll go to
Natasha's question.
AUDIENCE: We see a rise of
security issues where people
are actually trying to open too
many TCP connections to a
web server, and are actually
killing the web server by
opening too many TCP
connections.
So people tend to actually
remove keepalive to avoid this
kind of issue.
Where do you think about
WebSockets and security for
this kind of problem, and
how can we solve this?
JOHN FALLOWS: Well, one of the
things that was put into the
spec towards the end of its
finalization of the standard
was a clarification on what's
the maximum upper bound on the
number of WebSockets that can
hit a server at a time.
And it was unspecified, so we
want to get that cleared.
And at the time, a decision was
made to not limit it, but
also to add a caveat to that,
that only one handshake could
be outstanding to
the same target
server at the same time.
So from a browser invocation
standpoint, spinning up lots
and lots of WebSockets in rapid
succession would give
the server an opportunity to
intercept and potentially
detect repeated attempts, and
therefore mitigate that.
In general, I think that
things like SPDY as an
envelope, which we touched on
earlier, underneath these
things, tends to mitigate
some of that at the
physical TCP layer.
And also, having higher level
abstractions on top of the
WebSocket going forward, that's
more of a publish and
subscribe, or an event-driven
more architectural approach to
things, allows you to partition
up the universe of
addressability so you don't just
think of it as connecting
directly to the thing you want
to speak to, just because
that's the end of
the WebSocket.
Once you're attached to the
architecture, then you can
reach a whole myriad
of services
through that same channel.
MALE SPEAKER: The next question
is actually quite
high-level about WebRTC
in particular.
Natasha, if we can give
you that one?
AUDIENCE: Thanks.
This question's from an
anonymous sender.
Bandwidth throttling, especially
for multiple HD
video streams, is extremely
hard to do properly.
Is there any risk that WebRTC
will vary greatly by
implementation?
MALE SPEAKER: Most likely, I'm
assuming this is about--
one-to-one is one thing.
Viewing one-to-four,
one-to-five, I think it gets
to be much harder.
And are we going to see possibly
it just fall over
because Firefox doesn't do it
as well as, say, Chrome?
HENRIK JORETEG: This is
actually, in my opinion, is
two problems.
One is--
so for example, Skype, what
they will do, from what I
understand, is they will elect
the strongest connection.
And it's not just connection.
It's about the ability
to encode and decode
video really quickly.
So you need a strong device and
strong connection to be
able to serve as a
rebroadcaster.
And currently, that's part
of the spec, but it's not
really there yet.
Like, if you take a media
stream from one user and
attach it to another, it
just doesn't work.
And that's absolutely crucial
for the stuff to be able to be
usable for handling these other
interesting network
topologies.
Mesh is only good for so many,
because you're uploading your
video to each person that you're
connected to, and so is
everybody else.
So your upload bandwidth becomes
a huge bottleneck.
MALE SPEAKER: Didn't
you say that WebRTC
doesn't throttle down?
HENRIK JORETEG: So yeah, there
needs to be control mechanisms
for adjusting bandwidth, and
they just are not in place, as
far as I can tell.
Nothing I've tried has worked.
MALE SPEAKER: I actually was
working at a videoconferencing
company, and that was probably
the biggest aspect of our
secret sauce was to throttle
bandwidth properly.
So if WebRTC isn't thinking
about it, it seems like it's
heading for a bit of
a train wreck.
HENRIK JORETEG: I don't think
it's not thinking about it.
I think it's just the
implementations
aren't quite there yet.
That's my impression.
I've kind of raised it to some
of the Google folks who are
working on this stuff, and
that's the answer I get back.
It's like, yeah, we know
this is a thing
we've got to deal with.
And I mean, Google Hangouts,
they're well aware.
There's a low-bandwidth
mode for that.
And we need to be able to do
the same kinds of things
without re-requesting a
smaller video size.
We need to be able to just
adjust them based on quality
and lost packets.
ROB: This kind of problem,
as well, particularly the
one-to-many kind of the
bandwidth problem is
applicable in games as well.
So that's where the background
is from my point of view.
But if you're building
multiplayer games, you're
quickly going to come
over that problem.
And it's not something you can
necessarily avoid in that
circumstance, because you have
to be communicating out to
these multiple players
in a game.
But people have solved these
problems before, and there are
ways to reduce the amount of
information you're sending.
So for example, in a game, you
don't send updates for people
that aren't necessarily
in your vicinity, or
something like that.
So it's not always a
technology problem.
It's just a creative way of
thinking about how the data is
being sent to all the different
people, and are you
sending it to the
right people?
There may be 100 people in the
game, but there might only be
two that are actually applicable
and need the
updates that you're sending.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Another
separate point to that is, I
think we might need to--
it's only very early days
in terms of peer-to-peer
connections on the web.
So if you look at--
historically, you'd have clients
like Skype that are
open for many hours, unstable
broadband connections.
What happens, for example, on
battery life on a mobile
device, when suddenly you've
got four different
connections, and it's sending
the data four times, sending
the video to four different
clients.
And you said earlier
about strong peers.
Is that actually realistic
on the web?
I mean, are tabs open
long enough
for that to be realistic?
I don't know the answer to
these questions, but--
WESLEY: It's a big push too.
I mean, you have around 50
people connected here all day
long, using a WebSocket
connection.
And I mean, let's see,
my battery life, I've
got about 25% left.
So I mean, this is
the same thing.
I mean, people are connected.
They're using this protocol
all day long at this
conference, and it's draining
the battery.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: And that's
one-to-one to a server, right?
What happens if it's one-to-many
with a WebRTC data
connection?
WESLEY: RIght.
HENRIK JORETEG: It also takes
a lot of power to encode and
decode video that fast, and
to do with multiple
people at the same time.
So that's a huge drain
on power right there.
I know my laptop fans start
going crazy when I'm testing
with five people, so
it's a big problem.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: This seems to
be back to the discussion this
morning about images
for realtime data.
Do we need to change the way
data is delivered for someone
who's battery constrained,
versus a PC?
WESLEY: Yeah.
I could see the same thing for
responsive video, essentially.
ROB: Again, this comes
back to games.
These kind of problems are being
solved in games in the
way you throttle the
communication depending on the
bandwidth capabilities of each
person, and stuff like that.
So there's a lot of lessons
we can take
from things like games.
And this is why I'm so adamant
on not focusing so much on
audio and video, although
yes, that is the
use case right now.
Some of the problems that we're
approaching are being
solved or being look
at in other areas.
And I think it's just
interlinking the two and
trying to combine them and
come up with a solution.
MALE SPEAKER: But I am surprised
that maybe as a web
community, we always wring our
hands a little bit about
saying everybody, and
inclusiveness, and so forth.
And Sugar Crush doesn't give
a damn about battery life.
It's like, you want
to play it?
Then just plug the
damn thing in.
And no, I'm not saying
that's correct.
But to a certain extent, the
native community washes their
hands of this a little bit.
Are we trying too hard?
Just saying.
[LAUGHTER]
HENRIK JORETEG: I think enabling
mobile is really,
really, really important,
because I think certain things
don't matter, obviously.
Like, if you're playing some
hard core game, you're not
going to be sitting there
forever, maybe.
But to not take it into
consideration when these are
the actual physical hardware
limitations that we're dealing
with I think it is selling
ourselves sort.
JOHN FALLOWS: Yeah, and I also
think it's important that
you've got things and place to
avoid accidentally doing it.
So we want to make sure that
developers aren't accidentally
draining the battery.
I mean, if it's a deliberate
decision, that's one thing.
But if they just happen to be
on the end of a bandwidth
connection that's a little less
capable, we want to be
able to react to that.
ROB: I think we're getting the
APIs to play with this kind of
stuff as well now.
And actually, I'm not seeing
people implementing this yet,
but for example, using the
batter API, and actually if
the battery level is at a
certain point, changing the
way you're communicating
and stuff like that.
MALE SPEAKER: Excellent
point, yeah.
My point, by the way, wasn't
to seriously say we don't
care, but to say it is
interesting that some apps
don't care.
And we just do seem to be a
little holier than thou
sometimes, which is actually
good to have that aspiration.
JOHN FALLOWS: And I think that
may very well just be the
difference between thinking of
it in a platform perspective
versus thinking of it as an
application perspective.
MALE SPEAKER: Yeah.
Actually, question number
six I think
we've already answered.
I believe Steve Thayer
has a question.
He needs a microphone.
AUDIENCE: Actually, I think it
was Rob who's actually just
touched on this.
WebRTC seems to have focused
more on the audio video
streams, and data channels
are a special case.
Shouldn't all peer-to-peer
communication just be data
streams where the different data
types can be interpreted
as appropriate?
ROB: I mean, not all
peer-to-peer is--
how do you mean?
Like, should they all
be the same, like
they're just data channels?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
I mean, I think the
question was--
yeah.
The question was sort
of saying--
I'm just trying to find a
a way to rephrase it.
Why are we focusing--
most of the panel has just
purely been talking about
audio and video.
But audio and video are
just a type of data.
Right, OK, it has specific
characteristics.
Why is the focus purely focusing
on those, rather than
just coming up with a more
generic data channel?
HENRIK JORETEG: Quick one liner,
I think it makes a
better demo, which is
why it landed first.
That's my opinion.
It's also kind of a special
case in certain ways
that you have to--
you're trying to negotiate
encoding types, et cetera.
But yeah.
Fundamentally, I
agree with you.
I think peer connections,
you're still
doing the same thing.
You establish a single
peer connection.
You add and remove
data channels.
You add and remove video
and audio channels.
It's still one peer
connection.
At least that's the way it's
written in the spec.
So hopefully, it's actually--
yeah, I don't know.
Go ahead.
ROB: Generally, yes.
They are types of data.
But the media streaming is
incredibly different, and much
more complicated than just
sending basic data across.
So there is a reason why
they are separated.
But I really do think that the
data channel side of things,
like sending generic non-audio,
non-video kind of
data is where WebRTC has an
incredible amount of strength,
and where we're not really
focusing on yet.
So right now, we're not
exploring that too much.
But I am very interested to
see how that is explored,
because audio and video, yeah,
is the interesting thing.
And that's kind of why WebRTC
was created, and that's the
exciting thing.
Imagine being able to call
Skype from a browser.
That's an incredible use case.
But it's now, where do we
take that technology?
What's next?
And I think the data
channels is where
that's sort of hiding.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Of course, as
far as I understand, there's
some thought of bringing in
other kind of media streams,
not just audio and video.
What about temperature
information or sensor
information?
I don't know if anything's
happening there.
I don't really know.
But I've heard it mooted
as a possibility.
MALE SPEAKER: Well actually,
there was one comment I wanted
to make, which is that so often,
we expect these specs
to perfect.
And if they're not perfect, we
get really upset at them, and
like how bad the web
is, and so forth.
But shouldn't we just maybe
cut WebRTC and maybe the
others a little bit of slack,
and say, maybe to your point,
what can we do as a community to
kind of exercise things and
then get some feedback?
What can we do to do that?
HENRIK JORETEG: I mean,
definitely, I would suggest to
everybody in here if, you
haven't started playing with
this stuff, it's phenomenally
just--
it's very, very--
I mean, I hate the word
disruptive, but it's a
ridiculously disruptive
technology.
I mean, I seriously built my
own telecom to call my mom
with in Sweden.
I mean, come on.
Like, I'm not supposed to
be able to do that.
This is the kind of power
that it provides you.
And I would love to see
everybody here really get in
on hacking on this stuff.
MALE SPEAKER: Steven?
AUDIENCE: I guess just on that
last point, just what he said
there, if we could quickly poll
the panel, you saying
this is awesome.
What other use cases would the
panel have if you could each
nominate a use case for WebRTC
of something cool that you'd
like to see that you think that
this technology enables?
MALE SPEAKER: Excellent
question.
Can we just go through?
WESLEY: Video conf-- no.
[LAUGHTER]
WESLEY: Yeah, I mean, it would
be cool if the remotes that
you guys are using, like I said
earlier, you could just
pull up getUserMedia and
you wouldn't have
to hand you a mic.
You could just speak
to your phone
microphone and be broadcast.
So that would require looking
up to the A/V here.
It would require writing
the code to
handle the binary data.
But yeah, and then there's
a lot of geolocation--
like, in-room geolocation.
Like, there's been a lot of
investments made in companies
doing this lately where you
actually can find devices in
the room with much greater
granularity using a
geolocation API.
So with WebRTC, you could
say, OK, I know this--
I guess you would have to have
some centralized mechanism.
But you could find out all the
people that like the color
blue, and then you would be able
to pull up a video chat
with them in this room using
that newer technology.
So there's complementary
technologies, I guess, that
would be required for that use
case, but that's an idea.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
John?
JOHN FALLOWS: Yeah, I think just
enabling the internet of
things, machine of things
kind of stuff.
Because a lot of times with a
centralized model, we assume
that even though these devices
may be talking to one another,
that they're actually able
to potentially mediate or
coordinate against a connected
server system.
So you know, just not having to
rely on that always being
around, but still blending
these two worlds together
seamlessly.
I think that's a tough challenge
to do well, but just
raising the abstraction a little
bit so it makes these
things easy.
And get it out of the
developers' hands for trying
to solve all these
complex problems.
At Kaazing, we call these
things the web of things
instead of the internet of
things, because we think that
a lot of challenges that we
see in trying to connect
together those IP or lower level
protocols with WebRTC
that we don't actually see so
much in WebSocket because it's
web centric is achieved by
raising the bar a little bit
and connecting everything
together at the web level,
instead of thinking at
the internet level.
So we say web of things.
MALE SPEAKER: Cool.
Henrik?
HENRIK JORETEG: I would love
to see peer-distributed
rebroadcasting.
Why couldn't I pull up my phone
and be able to stream
something just off my phone
to the entire internet?
If you have a proper
rebroadcasting ability where a
peer could relay that feed, you
could basically turn every
person on the planet with
a smartphone into a news
reporter capable of live
broadcasts, which is
phenomenal.
And again, that's video and
audio, but I think that
particular one's really
interesting.
Of course, you could do the
exact same thing with any
other type of data.
Examples--
sheesh.
I can't think of anything
off the top of my head.
I've been too focused
on the video stuff.
MALE SPEAKER: Cool
ROB: I've got to say, I mean,
the simplest one is games and
how that's going to completely
change now.
You've got UDP and
unreliable data.
But the second one is the web
of things, like these
interconnected devices and
actually having the non-human
interaction, and devices
talking to each other.
Like, that's where it gets
really interesting.
We have phones powered
by JavaScript.
The entire operating system's
written in JavaScript.
That's incredible.
We now have Arduino-like devices
powered by JavaScript
and stuff like that.
And how are things going to
change, and how could we use
WebRTC to link those devices,
and what does that now allow
us to do that we couldn't
do before?
Using web technologies that
already are interoperable with
all of the other things that we
have available to us, like
the hardware APIs, and just
all of the other web APIs,
that's where things get very,
very interesting.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Yeah,
I think I would just
reiterate that point.
I mean, it's enabling.
It's disrupting the control.
And when you need an
ultra-low-latency connection
between two objects, it's now
possible for web developers to
build those things.
So you have a control
surface for a
quadracopter or something.
You can now build that
in a web browser.
It's amazing.
MALE SPEAKER: But is that going
to be an issue that not
too many Arduinos can be running
Chrome right now?
ROB: Right.
MALE SPEAKER: So how do
we get WebRTC into
these lower-level devices?
ROB: Someone needs
to build it.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
I mean, I just want to make sure
I was following what you
said, because what you said
is great, but there's no
immediate way for us to
do that, correct?
HENRIK JORETEG: This is a room
of developers, right?
Somebody can do it.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I mean, this
is partly why we're asking
about WebRTC on the server
and things like that.
Once you get it into things like
node.js, then this is--
MALE SPEAKER: Yeah, that
would be huge.
I think we have a few
minutes left, and
Christopher's been patient.
We'll do him, and then,
I think, you, OK?
Christopher.
No, that Christopher.
AUDIENCE: Sorry.
I apologize if I sound
like a broken record.
But as soon as you said enabling
technology, I'm
brought back again
to the idea of
decentralizing the solutions.
I mean, you think of dissident
suppression, say in Arab
Spring, and the raw potential
that exists in the phone to
directly connect people.
Without a central network
connection, that isn't possible.
Or emergency response--
as earthquakes, hurricanes
take out centralized
communications, it seems like
the technology exists to help
solve these communication
problems.
MALE SPEAKER: Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: But that's really
just a comment.
ROB: I mean, that's a really
interesting problem.
And that's something--
I mean, I've not developed for,
but I've been thinking
about a little bit.
And the whole idea of creating
sort of mesh networks out of
nowhere using these technologies
is incredibly
powerful, like the ability to
then spread communication
amongst an ad hoc local
network is crazy.
You have to get at the actual
connecting the two devices
together problem.
But if we can solve that, then
what you can actually do with
that is incredibly powerful.
WESLEY: It's kind of like the
only way you could do that now
is to carry around some external
antenna with you with
an extra power supply, and
create your own network.
I mean, that would have to be
like standard issue, or
emergencies.
Yeah, I mean, that's today.
But your phone cannot power that
kind of transmission and
that kind of findability.
MALE SPEAKER: And you've
been patient.
One more question?
AUDIENCE: It doesn't seem that
you need a web browser in
order to have WebRTC.
You could always do it through
node or through and JavaScript
on-chip device.
MALE SPEAKER: It's a simple
matter of programming.
ROB: It just doesn't exist
at the moment.
HENRIK JORETEG: There have
been some efforts.
There's actually a node WebRTC
library that I attempted to
bind to libjingle.
And I don't quite know
the status of that.
It hasn't had much activity.
MALE SPEAKER: I think we've
got the wrap-up, so
thank you very much.
If you liked the session,
please give us a vote.
And if you don't, just
don't give us a vote.
WESLEY: Whoever's writing the
script to do 50 votes, go
ahead and up that to 100.
[LAUGHTER]
MALE SPEAKER: Awesome.
Thanks very much.
[APPLAUSE]