PAUL IRISH: All right, so I'm
really excited about this.
Edge Conf is kind of like the
focal point of a discussion
around using cutting edge
technologies to build amazing
user experiences.
But I think the elephant in
the room is it's great to
learn all about all these new
technologies, but what about
older browsers, browsers that
are less capable that cannot
take advantage of some
of these things?
So this session is an
opportunity to kind of discuss
some of those challenges that
we've had for a long time and
what we can do about them now.
We have a really powerful
panel up here, so let me
quickly introduce everyone.
Over here to my right
is Shwetank Dixit.
He has been on the Opera
Developer Relations Team and
Open Web Team for a while now,
working a lot on compatibility
of all sorts of sites.
So whether they have willy-nilly
reg x's that are
blocking Opera and such.
Also, a member of the web
education community group and
the mobile web for social
development group at the W3C.
To my left, Tomomi Imura.
So she has been kind of fighting
for the mobile web
for a long time, ever since 2005
when she was leading the
mobile yahoo.com.
TOMOMI IMURA: [INAUDIBLE].
PAUL IRISH: Yahoo.com?
M.yahoo.com, yes.
Also, was using [INAUDIBLE]
to great success, trying to
wrangle all sorts of kind of
tricky little mobile devices
coming over there.
Worked at webOS and
is now at Nokia.
Cool.
On her left is Edd Sowden.
Edd works for the Government
Digital Service and the GDS
finished a big, huge redesign
of gov.uk, a kind of much
lauded, progressive enhancement
redesign bringing
all of the UK's government
online.
And they're now continuing to
bring more departments online.
They've done a really good job
kind of presenting the best
way to do progressive
enhancement and documenting
kind of their strategies
and methodologies.
And also, providing a very
transparent development process--
blogging, documenting,
guidelines everywhere, really
fantastic job.
And our opening speaker,
Tom Maslen.
Tom is the Tech Lead for BBC
News Visual Journalism and has
been leading the client-side
team for the mobile BBC News
team for a while.
Has been kind of a [INAUDIBLE]
based developer, knows browser
performance and JavaScript
extremely well.
And also, a while ago, worked on
the team that built an open
source [INAUDIBLE]
JavaScript library.
So--
TOM MASLEN: Small
part of that.
PAUL IRISH: Blast
from the past.
All right, cool.
So Tom, if you want to take it
away, that would be great.
TOM MASLEN: Hi.
Hello, and can I
have my slides?
Hi.
Hello and welcome to the
introduction talk Legacy
Clients by me, Tom Maslen.
Or, as I think this talk should
really be called, yay,
I'm so excited there's going
to be five versions of
Internet Explorer for me
to support next year.
I'm 34 years old.
Back in my arrogant 20s, I saw
myself as a bit of a Han Solo,
flying around the office, saving
princesses' websites,
fixing bugs.
My job used to be easy.
I had four rendering engines to
support and yet, I also had
to worry about accessibility.
But writing my code semantically
fixed that.
And I also had to concern myself
about SEO, but that's
essentially accessibility
for search engines.
So my semantic code
sorted that, too.
This was a time when we could
all afford to be little Han
Solos quickly putting
sites together.
But then in 2007, all that
changed when Steve Jobs
invented the bloody iPhone.
Shit got more complicated.
Suddenly, we had mobiles with
very slow connection speeds
and phones with different size
screens, new types of
interactions.
Smartphones started to appear
with pathetic little
processors and tiny amounts
of RAM that run
my code really slowly.
And PPK also pointed out that
there was like a hundred
different vendors of web
kits to support.
But all of these problems were
nothing compared to what was
about to wash over us--
an avalanche of devices.
Being confident little
Han Solos
wasn't good enough anymore.
Instead, we've all had to become
intelligent, clever
Spocks who can balance all of
these issues against getting
our job done correctly.
As developers, this is the
biggest problem that we have
today, balancing agility--
getting the stuff
done quickly--
versus robustness--
getting the stuff done right.
Now, in this paradigm that we
find ourselves in, it's very
easy to concentrate on this
issue so much the we forget
about boring, old issues like
supporting IE7 and 8.
I can test in IE8 and 7 using
a virtual machine on my Mac,
but it's really hard.
Oh, sorry, but it's
really hard to do.
The experience is slow and the
dev tools are terrible.
Trying to get IE7 dev tools to
do I1 is like asking a wookie
that's wearing boxing gloves
to wipe my bottom clean.
It's a terrible situation that
normally ends up covering you
in something.
Some bugs I just give up on
because it's not worth
spending the time required
to fix such a small--
fix a problem for such
a small audience.
It raises questions about
whether we should actually
support these browsers.
I'd argue that sometimes
it depends.
While the challenges surrounding
client support
have increased, web development
itself has become
more popular.
It's entered the mainstream.
Everyone from schoolchildren
to contestants on "The
Apprentice" are now
making web pages.
And the act of making a web page
is actually pretty easy.
Build something, look at it in
your browser, there you go.
It's done.
It's very fast.
But as I've just shown you,
the practice of web
development is the complete
opposite.
It's actually really
hard to do right.
Anyone can pick up a book or
read an article online that
teaches you how to make a web
page, how to write HTML or CSS
or JavaScript.
These things are hard to master,
but they're easy to
start doing.
What is hard to learn though,
is how to scale your website
up from a single user, ie
yourself, to a larger audience.
These things here, they help
you to scale your audience.
But learning them
is much harder.
Because to understand these, you
have to change the context
of your thinking away from
what's in front of you.
As a developer, I often
find myself having to
defend these things.
But ultimately, the web
isn't about these.
They're important, but we don't
do accessibility for the
sake of accessibility.
And we don't make sites fast
or SEO friendly or work
without JavaScript because
it's nice.
What we're trying to
achieve, our actual
end goal, is ubiquity.
We want as many people as
possible to see our site.
The web should be inclusive,
not exclusive.
I mean, nobody would build a
shop that only the dwarf from
"Game of Thrones" could
get into, right?
Shops have doors that are wide
and as tall as possible.
Websites should be the same.
An easier way to think
of ubiquity is to
call it browser support.
When people talk about web
browser support, they think,
well, how far back
should we go?
IE6, IE7.
In the website versus native
apps to beat, the reason why
website wins is because
apps are binary.
They either work
or they don't.
An iOS app works on
an iPhone, but it
doesn't work on an Android.
However, your site will
work on both.
And even better, if you build it
properly, it will work to a
certain degree on pretty
much anything.
It's the ubiquity of
the web that wins.
So to go back to the original
problem I defined, this job is
also harder because the problem
is continuing to
increase in complexity.
And we have to balance that
against getting stuff done
fast and robustly.
What we shouldn't do is fight
that complexity with ever more
complex solutions.
People who build responsive
websites that are really just
a collection of smaller
websites within it are
creating more problems
for themselves.
When a problem grows to a
certain size, the problem
changes into something else.
And to survive, you have to
change how you think as well.
We did that at BBC News.
We turned the problem of browser
support upside down.
Instead of thinking about how
far back we should go, we
decided to support everything.
We call this technique
cutting the mustard.
The responsive site has a very
basic core experience that has
a simple layout, is
very fast, and is
delivered to all browsers.
The core experience is good
enough to allow everyone to
consume the news.
On top of this, we built an
enhanced experience using
JavaScript and modern CSS.
It has a complex layout and
is very functional.
This is only delivered
to modern browsers.
It's conditionally loaded by
checking for the existence of
specific features.
All the browsers that cut the
mustard have great JavaScript
and CSS support.
They have fast rendering engines
and a less buggy.
This technique is robust because
it supports a massive
amount of browsers.
It's also agile as you're
building the enhanced
experience using modern
coding practices.
But IE7 and 8 only get
the core experience.
Now, this might be good enough
for you if these browsers
don't bring a significant
amount of traffic.
Or, you might decide that these
browsers need more than
just the core experience.
How do you do that?
Well, with two ways.
We can edit the cuts the
mustard test to load an
alternative JavaScript
specifically
just for IE7 and 8.
We can then cherry pick what
features the enhanced
experience we give them,
like a two-column
layout or video support.
We also need to give these
browsers a CSS.
With mobile first CSS, IE7 and
8 only render the smallest
view because they don't
understand media queries.
But with a CSS preprocessor, you
can output a version of a
site style at any defined width
specifically for these browsers.
The panelist Edd Sowden has
already implemented this for
the UK government website,
and here's one example of
how you can do it.
Instead of writing media queries
directly into your
SAS, use this mix-in instead.
Then, make a new SAS file that
sets a variable with the width
value that you want IE7 and 8 to
render the desktop view to.
Import the main SAS file into
this and it will render out an
alternative desktop-only
version of your
CSS into a new file.
You should add the legacy IE
style sheet into the page
using a conditional comment.
Now, however, you have to be
careful now, as IE7 and 8 will
be exposed to your modern CSS
and there's lots of selectors
and properties that you
need to watch out for.
If you're unlucky, you may
find IE7 and 8 will be
rendering your modern CSS onto
the page in a way that reminds
you of how Donald Trump's hair
renders itself onto his head.
So to summarize, how do you
support legacy clients?
I'd say don't think about
stretching your code across an
ever-increasing browser
support list.
The problem is only ever going
to get more complex.
And you can't keep up
by making an ever
more complex solution.
If you keep thinking like a
Han Solo, eventually this
problem will get
on top of you.
Instead, I think the best
way to solve this
is with team work.
Use the solid base of
progressive enhancement as a
springboard for your JavaScript
and treat each
feature on your website like in
an away mission, deciding
when to send these agent
browsers to the fore.
So that's enough from me.
Let's chat about it.
[APPLAUSE]
PAUL IRISH: Very nice.
EDD SOWDEN: I'm sorry--
TOM MASLEN: Gee, thanks.
PAUL IRISH: Thank you
very much, Tom.
That was great.
So we'll go to our
first question.
Our first question delivered
by [? Hakim ?]
there.
AUDIENCE: Hello?
Anonymous question, why should
there be a stigma attached to
not supporting older clients?
If a developer knows their
audience and they all have the
latest clients, what's
the problem?
I think that should be why is
there a stigma attached and
not why should there be.
So I'll rephrase it.
PAUL IRISH: So Shwetank, do
you want to take this?
Why should there be--
why is there a stigma
attached to not
supporting older browsers?
SHWETANK DIXIT: There is,
but there shouldn't be.
Mainly because when it comes to
older browsers, there's a
lot of reason to actually
support older browsers because
there's a lot of times in which
the user cannot update
their browser.
Whether it's because the system
administrator doesn't
allow it or because many times
the user doesn't know what a
browser is.
So if you say update your
browser, it's like, how could
I update my browser?
I don't know what it is.
So that's one thing.
Second things are that sometimes
people know what a
browser is.
They're fully aware of
how to update it, but
they don't want to.
Sometimes it's because they're
using a phone and they have a
very crappy network and they
might use a proxy browser
instead of something which is
like a full-fledged browser.
And proxy browsers are tricky
as we'll see later on.
Sometimes, people have very
limited data plans.
I know people in Europe
who have 30 MB
data plans for a month.
And if you exceed that,
then you'll get
charged very, very highly.
So there's multiple reasons why
and genuine reasons why
you should support older
or proxy browsers.
And there shouldn't be any
stigma attached as such.
We all like to play with the
greatest and the most
cutting-edge stuff.
But the realities of the
world is we need
to deal with everyone.
And sometimes there's also
what's called regulation, or
some laws regarding
accessibility and stuff like
that as well, which need to
be considered as well.
PAUL IRISH: So I wonder if--
so the second part is if we do
know what your clients are, if
you're looking at analytics
and numbers and they're
indicating that you're OK on
dropping support for IE6 and
7, and potentially
8, is that fine?
TOM MASLEN: I think it depends
on the context of the content.
I think if you're making a
government website, then there
definitely is a stigma
because these
services are like mandatory.
They have to be viewable
by anyone.
But if you're making an
application, like Gmail, then
probably not.
Because somebody with
IE7 won't give
you that much benefit.
PAUL IRISH: Edd, is there
legal legislation that
requires the accessibility
to old browsers?
EDD SOWDEN: So the only legal
legislation or legal things
that exist for older browsers
are accessibility.
You can be sued for not having
accessible website.
But that's up for the user to
determine what accessible is.
The stigma that we have-- this
industry seems to have this
horrible stigma with,
oh, you can't drop
support for old browsers.
You can't drop support.
You got to go back to the
question, what is supporting
an old browser?
Supporting an old browser for
most of us means that we're
going to test in it.
So that's not support at all.
That means you're testing
in these browsers.
Supporting in actually, if
anyone has a problem, you'll
go and fix it for them,
like that's support.
So if someone has a problem
using your website, yeah, you
want to help that person out.
But there shouldn't be
any stigma attached
with helping someone.
Because if you want to spend
time making sure ahead of time
that those people won't have
problems, then that's how you
spend your time.
PAUL IRISH: I see.
TOMOMI IMURA: The one problem I
see is that, OK, let's say,
maybe by the statistics, each
companies the services
[INAUDIBLE] and maybe they just
decide to drop IE support.
And sometimes they're doing
it in the wrong way.
I mean, they try to--
like a sniff in the user agent
or something and try to
eliminate all the IE which
seem to be old.
But many time, they're like
doing the wrong way.
So let's say, I work
for Nokia and I use
the Lumia phone regularly.
And my browser choice-- well,
it's not my choice, actually.
It comes with the operating
system.
And it's IE 10.
And oftentimes I see the
site like, oops, sorry.
You have to update
your browser.
It's like really, it's IE 10.
It's pretty decent and I believe
that service, so sites
should work.
But I think they're just try
to sniff it out mistakenly.
And try to suggest to me to
upgrade a browser or just
download some other browsers.
But the thing is, like he
was saying, we don't
always have a choice.
Users don't always have the
choice, so that's something I
have to remind--
people have to remind.
PAUL IRISH: So I guess on the
topic of support, support is
kind of a--
it is the verb that we always
use in this discussion.
And it implies that it
is a binary decision.
You either support
it or you don't.
And I think for many of our
development cycles, our
development approach support is
kind of this sliding scale.
And so Tom, with cutting the
mustard, when a browser falls
into unsupported, they get
a core experience?
TOM MASLEN: So there
is no unsupported.
The idea is that everybody is
supplied a core experience.
Everybody gets the content.
But the content, the way it's
displayed is very simple.
So if there is additional
content on the home page of
the BBC News site, for example,
like analysis and
features, that's available
but you have to
click it to go to it.
So the experience is very basic,
but you still get all
the content.
But then with a premium version,
we'll just go and
fetch all of that content
and put it straight into
the page for you.
PAUL IRISH: And is the
difference in your case, the
amount of testing between core
and the premium experience?
I imagine you are not as
actively testing the core
experience?
TOM MASLEN: No, the core
experience is so simple it's a
single column.
We don't add any functionality
into the page.
Yeah, so that's going to pretty
much render on anything.
PAUL IRISH: I think Andy Clark,
a well-known developer
in the UK, a while
ago released a
universal IE6 style sheet.
And the idea here was basically
a style sheet that
had very good-looking
typography, but destroyed all
the layout, killed all your
floats, just kept it all in a
single column.
And the idea was give that to
IE, give them nothing else.
The content is there and it's
accessible, but you can forget
about the visualness of
the rest of the site.
And I think that's kind of a
nice way for something to go
unsupported.
It's basically to fall into a
pit of accessible content.
EDD SOWDEN: So having an IE6
style sheet which has
virtually nothing is kind of the
approach we took for one
the large sections of gov.UK
because we used the approach
that Tom was mentioning during
the intro with using mobile
first, and then sending specific
IE style sheets for
IE6, 7, and 8.
But IE6, they don't get any
layout because layout is added
on desktop.
So IE6 just gets a mobile view,
so it's a single column.
It's basically got typography
because
that's all that it gets.
TOM MASLEN: I think it's
a benefit as well.
Because people with IE6
or IE7 probably
don't have a good computer.
And so the fact that it's so
simple means it will render
like five or six times faster
than other experiences.
TOMOMI IMURA: [INAUDIBLE].
And as long as users can get
what they want, experience is
not killed.
SHWETANK DIXIT: I think that's
a good strategy because
there's so many sites which
either support it or just send
an error message saying that,
OK, this site is not supported
and that's it.
The user cannot do anything
about that.
So I think that's a very
important thing that you don't
block anyone.
You at least serve them
the core experience.
The first part of that
question was if
you know your audience.
And it's really difficult to
know your audience in a very,
very accurate way.
Even if you know using your
statistics and analysis what
are the browsers which are
coming through, there are
times in which you get a mention
on the front page of
Reddit, or you get slashed
audit, or any influential news
website mention you and then
you'll get this whole stream
of traffic which is completely
unpredictable.
So even that premise of that
question that you know your
audience is flawed.
PAUL IRISH: So I think it's a
good time to move on to the
next question.
This one to be asked by
John [? Follows. ?]
AUDIENCE: So this is an
anonymous question.
What's the best way to make
legacy clients a visible part
of the development process?
PAUL IRISH: So I think this
is both visibility on the
developers side to understand
what is necessary to give them
what you plan to give them.
And also, potentially on the
executive side, to better
understand what from a
development cost perspective
is included here.
TOM MASLEN: So at the BBC News,
once we-- we made the
responsive site, but it was
a small team that did it.
And then, eventually we fanned
it out to the rest of the
department.
And so we've had to go through
a training process with
everyone as they become engaged
with the product.
So we've got the designers
thinking about the core
experience as well.
And they're thinking about
progressive enhancements, so
they start off with the core
experience, and then they
progressively enhance it and
make the better version.
The problem that we find is
that many people just
associate the core
basic experience
with a very thin layout.
What they find harder to do is
to probably try and understand
that the core experience could
be any width, and the premium
experience could be
any width as well.
PAUL IRISH: I also wonder,
included on this, I think,
there is a visibility of the
perceived experience between
legacy clients and
modern clients.
And one of these parts is
performance, certainly.
So just rendering a page or any
sort of interactivity, the
more modern browser, it's going
to be quite a bit more
responsive.
Is there a good way to kind of
demonstrate the difference
between the user experience of
someone on an older client
versus a newer client?
And is that something that the
executive team wants to see
and understand?
TOMOMI IMURA: Maybe
I would say--
[INAUDIBLE]
UI or I would say UX using
some Ajax-y type of
interaction.
And that works, probably
wonderfully on latest,
greatest browsers.
Chrome and desktop [INAUDIBLE]
works nicely.
But yeah, they show
the same UI.
And let's say, like older mobile
browsers, or could be
Android, older Android
and stuff.
It's [INAUDIBLE]
look really janky or maybe
even it fails.
EDD SOWDEN: A lot of it's
managing expectation, though.
People on the older browser,
people on IE6 who are stuck on
IE6 in their corporate
environments, they'll be used
to an internet which is not
quite like the internet the
rest of us use.
So while, like for me or for
you, browsing a website in IE6
will feel painfully janky and
painfully horrible, it's--
they're kind of almost
expecting that.
And people aren't left on these
browsers because they
want to be there.
They're there because those
are the browsers they have
because corporate IT has said
that's what they've got.
So it's all a case of managing
expectation for those guys.
Those people, if they know
they're getting a janky
experience, they come
into that knowing.
I have colleagues who
have IE6 as their
browser on their machines.
And they know it's going
to look crap.
And they joke with me,
like is this supposed
to look that bad?
And it's like, yeah, I think
the developer picked that
color for you.
It's like, no.
They I know the internet's
horrible.
SHWETANK DIXIT: I mean, the
thing is just to add, or maybe
even remove from your point,
they might be used to it when
they're working.
But for sure, they're using the
internet at their home or
on the mobile, in transit or
something, so they know what
the internet--
what the real internet
is like.
And it'll be even more
frustrating for them to see
the internet as it is
in the wild on IE6
all the time at work.
EDD SOWDEN: Go and sit
next to them at work.
Their lives are a pain
at work, anyway.
They know.
PAUL IRISH: Calvin [INAUDIBLE],
something to add?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Actually, I was going
to ask something
but you've just said.
But I wanted to ask
specifically,
is there a way to--
if people have these different
experiences at work and at
home, they know your site's
different when they're
accessing it at work.
And something might be missing
functionality that they're
used to at home.
Is there some strategy we can
take to make them not
frustrated at us seeming like
they're suddenly hitting a
broken version of the site
that they were used to?
EDD SOWDEN: Well, I think this
comes back to the approach
with cutting the mustard.
You make sure they can
get the content
they need to get still.
While it will look different, it
will feel a bit different,
as long as they can achieve
the goals that
they need to achieve.
It's the best you
can do for them.
PAUL IRISH: True.
What I'm hearing from both of
you is that there is kind of--
both strategies include a
degraded experience for older
browsers in some way.
And that seems to scale
pretty well.
But that does mean that we do
have at least two experiences.
And so if we are in a situation
where you have
someone that is seeing both of
those experiences, is that
going to be a problem?
TOM MASLEN: I think that's fine
because we can't-- like I
said in the talk, we can't make
a premium experience that
works across the whole spectrum
of browsers because
polyfilling and mobile internet
connections are so
hard to marry up together.
PAUL IRISH: Yeah.
So it has to be good enough
because there's no other way.
TOM MASLEN: No.
SHWETANK DIXIT: Yeah, it's
better than just showing them
that, oh, your browser's
not supported by--
it's at least better
than that.
TOM MASLEN: I guess-- sorry, the
one caveat to what I just
said is that if you do
server-side detection and
sniff for old browsers,
which is probably--
because normally people when
they talk about UA sniffing,
you think about, oh, is this a
mobile device or is this a
desktop device?
Whereas, I think now we should
probably be thinking about, is
this an old browser
or a new browser?
I think that'd be
an interesting--
PAUL IRISH: In your case, would
it be, does this browser
cut the mustard versus
[INAUDIBLE]?
TOM MASLEN: Yeah, you could
do that on the server
if you wanted to.
TOMOMI IMURA: Right.
Like the old browser that
doesn't support JavaScript, or
doesn't understand JavaScript
feature detection, then you
have to rely on the
server side.
PAUL IRISH: All right,
I'd like to move
on to the next question.
This one comes from
Dustin Caston.
Dustin's up here
in the purple.
AUDIENCE: Hey, so what as a
community can we do to help
the holdouts of legacy clients
such as the government and IT
departments?
EDD SOWDEN: Nothing.
TOM MASLEN: That was
my answer as well.
I was going to say nothing.
EDD SOWDEN: So I did a little
bit of research kind of around
this point before I came.
The saying Paul said to me
earlier, I've built a thing
which takes your Google
Analytics and splits out
browsers with graphs.
You can see browser
usage over time.
PAUL IRISH: It's called
browser matrix.
It takes in your Google
Analytics account and then
just charts the trend lines for
a browser [? merger. ?]
EDD SOWDEN: Paul said it'd be
really cool if it could show
future trends.
So I went and had a look because
I'm a nerd at IE6's
and 7's trend lines on gov.UK.
They're going down.
IE6 lost half a percent in
the last six months.
TOM MASLEN: What
percent was it?
EDD SOWDEN: It's gone from just
over one to around half.
TOM MASLEN: Is that at any
particular time of the week?
EDD SOWDEN: So it can also show
you stats on a day by
day, seven day rolling basis.
And during the week,
6 is above that.
And at weekends, it's
not really there.
PAUL IRISH: But I guess the
question is like, like IE8
would be a better case.
EDD SOWDEN: Like those guys,
they're going down.
They're going to get there.
And from the government
perspective, like working in
government, everyone is
painfully aware in government
that we're tied into these
horrible contracts that
require us to have IE6.
And everyone's working to
try and get out of them.
No one is trying to stay
in that world.
There's not much a development
community can do to help that.
And on gov.uk, we have a browser
bar that pops up if
you're on an old browser that
says, try and upgrade, which
hilariously when we-- we won a
design award earlier this year
and a whole collection of the
screenshots that were in news
article, you could see
that browser bar.
It made us smile that these
people writing reports for
fairly large magazines
online still use
old browsers as well.
But in terms of government
and massive
corporates, very aware.
We're trying to get rid
of it internally.
PAUL IRISH: Question from
the audience, Daniel.
AUDIENCE: So we always want
all our users to be happy.
And I looked at some numbers
and we have IE--
all of IE is like 8%
of our traffic,
maybe 4% of our traffic.
IE8.
But is it worth spending the
effort versus things like
developer happiness
and retention?
PAUL IRISH: It sounds
like it's not worth
the effort for you.
It sounds like you're
doing well.
TOM MASLEN: I'd say
it depends.
Those old devices might bring a
lot of traffic to your site.
But do they bring a
lot of revenue?
PAUL IRISH: I think that's
something that it's--
I don't know that we've seen a
lot in the way of business
metrics that are segregated by
browser or by connectivity or
by the performance load
time of the site.
But I think it's worth looking
into kind of how those
technical metrics of the site
and of those users translate
into their success
on the site.
I guess to get back to Dustin's
question, we're
talking about what our community
can do to help
legacy clients.
So Google Apps dropped support
for IE8 last November.
And Google Analytics Dashboard
is dropping support for IE8 in
a few months.
Google has a policy of only
supporting the most recent and
the last version.
And so Google's being kind of
aggressive in this and saying,
you just have to upgrade
in order to use it.
You can't use Google
Docs on IE8.
But is there anyone else that
is in a position where they
can help move this forward or
were you just in a case where
we are just waiting for those
trend lines to naturally go
down over the course of years
as we did with IE6?
EDD SOWDEN: Internally
in the UK government,
I'd love to say more.
But there is work going
on to fix it there.
But yeah, it's still--
there are people trying.
SHWETANK DIXIT: One more thing
that I wanted to add was a lot
of these things are decided
at the contract level.
Sometimes what happens is--
I can at least talk about
the Indian government.
Sometimes what happens
is they don't make
the government websites.
They sometimes send it out
to a contractor who
makes it for them.
And usually, things
are decided when
the contract is signed.
And if there's a clause saying
that, OK, IE6 will be
supported, it has
to be supported.
So one of the things is to, as
a web developer, if you're
vying for that contract, to
argue at that level before
signing that yes, I will not
be supporting these things.
I might be supporting
the newer versions.
And the second thing I wanted to
mention was this problem is
exacerbated by the fact that
many people who were in
government weren't really tech
savvy that much for a while.
They didn't really know about
browsers and stuff like that.
But with newer devices coming
in, people are having iPhones
and iPads and stuff like that.
They still might not know what
a browser is or not care, but
they know that, OK,
whatever I'm--
this website that I'm signing
the contract for, it has to
work on my iPad, for example.
So they're more focused on
those things, on devices,
rather than the older
browsers.
So that mind shift is happening
a little bit.
But once again, as web
developers, before signing the
contract you have to
see it and be very
careful about that.
EDD SOWDEN: Talking of
contracts, all contracts that
the UK government signs now
cannot have anything which
even hints at vendor lock-in or
device or browser lock-in.
Anything that hints at a
specific version has to be
removed before contracts can
go out for tender because
nothing like that's
allowed anymore.
PAUL IRISH: Comment
from the audience.
Mary from O'Reilly.
AUDIENCE: Hey, so just going
back to we were talking
earlier about how frustrating
it is for your coworkers if
they have one browser version
at home and one browser
version at work and those
types of scenarios.
I think we might be referring
to very specific portion of
the world in that those are the
people who are very tech
savvy, who have the latest and
greatest things, who--
yeah, bigger and newer
is better.
But what about the rest of the
world that updating your
browser is scary, because it
means all of a sudden you
don't know how to
use it anymore.
So there's people who
consciously make the choice to
not update because of that.
TOMOMI IMURA: Your moms.
AUDIENCE: I'm sorry?
AUDIENCE: Well, OK.
So yeah, that's an example.
My mom does that.
But I mean, it's a
legit scenario.
And by eliminating the ability
for them to view your website,
you're basically telling
them they don't matter.
PAUL IRISH: Yes, I think change
aversion is real for everyone.
And in a lot of cases,
browsers and
website features as well.
My take here is that a lot of
it is up to browser makers
themselves to make transitions
as smooth as possible.
EDD SOWDEN: We're good
now because the
problem was always IE.
Or, more like corporate IE.
So people would build corporate
intranets and they
would rely on ActiveX.
And that's why we're in the
situation where there's so
many corporate desktops
that can't upgrade.
TOMOMI IMURA: Yeha, I was going
to mention that, too.
Many times you can't just
download, install any browsers
on your computers.
You have to ask IT
guys to do that.
So obviously, probably that's
where a lot of legacy IE is
coming from.
So if you're working for the
web services for, like
enterprise and such,
this is something
like really huge issue.
And you have to really
[INAUDIBLE]
browser stats and what your
people are using.
PAUL IRISH: So I want to move
onto the next question.
But before I do, I want
to get Jeffrey
Burtoft from Microsoft.
Since we are talking about IE a
lot, its be nice to get his
comment here.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, thank you.
So first, to defend
Microsoft here.
One thing I want
to make sure--
and I do that proudly.
Because one of the things I
want to make sure that we
understand is that Windows
XP that runs
IE8 was a great product.
And that's why people
still use it.
So any time we build great
products, we're going to have
to deal with legacy browsers
because they're
going to stick around.
So if you look at a parallel to
iOS, so we just stopped--
or Apple just stopped
supporting, was it 3GS?
With updates, which means that
iOS 6 is the last version
they'll ever see.
But those phones are going
to continue to be around.
And they'll become
a legacy platform
that we have to support.
So when we have good products
that are going to stick
around, it's something that
we need to plan for.
So these type of discussions
will always be relevant.
PAUL IRISH: I think in this
case, our situation is that
Windows XP is a great product,
but the problem there is that
users of IE on Windows XP
don't have an ability to
upgrade their browser to
the next version of IE.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So that's something
that's clear.
If you are on that platform,
there's two different things
that are going to cause you to
stay on older versions of IE.
One is it's your environment,
whether it's because you don't
want to upgrade or you
can't upgrade.
Or, the fact that with IE, you
can't upgrade passed IE8 if
you're on Windows XP.
So at Microsoft, we
use JavaScript.
We use our JavaScript
engine, HTML5, in
a lot of our products.
And so whether it's writing apps
for Office or in embedded
or in Xbox or in Windows 8 apps,
all of that can be done
with a JavaScript engine.
So there's definitely a coupling
there that makes us
have to draw some lines in the
sands as to where we can
update and where we can't.
There's reasons behind it, I
guess is what I would say.
PAUL IRISH: Sure.
And I guess we can close this IE
discussion for now with the
end of support date for Windows
XP is April 2014?
AUDIENCE: That's right.
PAUL IRISH: So that trend line
that we're watching for IE8
may potentially drop down more
substantially at that point.
EDD SOWDEN: So there's a whole
nother dark world which no one
talks about, talking about
like old IEs and the fact
there are other things which
we have to support which no
one talks about, and they're
old screen readers, screen
reading technology.
PAUL IRISH: Edd, before we move
onto screen readers, I
want to get Alex Russell's
comments here.
AUDIENCE: Hi, thanks.
Alex Russell.
One of my first projects at
Google was a product called
Chrome Frame, which was
necessitated because you
didn't do what you just said.
Microsoft didn't take
care of the legacy.
It was Microsoft's
responsibility to do that, and
instead Microsoft chose not to
invest in making sure that
users of Windows XP could
continue to use modern
technology.
So having done the cleanup work
for you, I just need to
make the point that
you didn't.
[APPLAUSE]
PAUL IRISH: This is going
to get exciting.
For the moment, we're going to
move on to the next question.
This one [? Matias ?]
[? Kauzman. ?]
AUDIENCE: Hi, my question is
for how long is it worth
polyfilling features for legacy
browsers and taking the
hit in performance or
dev productivity?
What factors should influence
the ultimate choice to seize
support for a legacy client?
PAUL IRISH: Yeah, so in a lot
of cases, our method of
dealing with older clients that
don't support a certain
capability is polyfilling
them.
We started out with the JSON
2.js, JSON polyfill.
And we've managed to polyfill
many, many things.
These polyfills do have
performance costs, not only in
the bytes that we have to send
down the wire in CSS and
JavaScript but also in
runtime performance.
So performance of polyfills
is a concern.
And what are the other aspects
that could help influence the
choice to--
seize support might not be the
right words, but change the
support level.
TOM MASLEN: So maybe a good
example is with animations.
So a couple of years ago, people
would do JavaScript
animations.
And now, we try to see all
animations with CSS.
And we just say, well, if you
don't have that CSS feature,
you just get a janky
animation.
I'd say that's fine.
I don't have a problem with
people in IE getting janky
transitions.
TOMOMI IMURA: I'm not sure
about jankiness.
If you want to have some
animation but it doesn't work
in some browsers, I
think you have to
just kill the animation.
I think not moving
at all, it's far
better than janky animation.
PAUL IRISH: If you want to say
janky, unless you mean like
binary, like it's closed
than it's open.
But with a more modern browser,
you can [INAUDIBLE].
TOMOMI IMURA: [INAUDIBLE].
EDD SOWDEN: Although, I guess
an issue that is not so much
with polyfill.
Something I've seen recently
where I made a panel appear
and I gave it a nice
animation.
It worked lovely in iOS.
But when I checked it on
an Amazon Kindle Fire--
it had a great browser.
It supported the feature.
But it was really janky because
the hardware just
couldn't keep up.
TOMOMI IMURA: And not
just the hardware.
Actually, in the Amazon Kindle,
the Silk browser is a
proxy browser.
Well, maybe a marketing term
is like cloud accelerated
browser, whatever that is.
Yeah, so that is keep in mind.
It's not like all JavaScript
is forced to work in some
WebKit, works [INAUDIBLE]
you want in a proxy.
PAUL IRISH: But I guess when we
talk about legacy clients,
there's a few reasons why we
use the term "legacy." And
that does happen to usually
refer to them being old.
But I think the reason that we
don't embrace them and love
them is because they
may have bugs.
They're probably slower than
what we're used to and they
lack features that we want
to use, that we're
interested in using.
So it's not necessarily that
they're old, but they aren't
good as what we want.
And I mean, is it worth forming
a policy around how to
change your support level
for browsers?
What's your take on
this, Shwetank?
SHWETANK DIXIT: I think,
ultimately, there's going to
be so many variations that you
should stop with the mindset
of supporting or not supporting
those kind of
browsers or not.
You should just go with the
thing of progressive
enhancement and feature
detection.
Because what will happen is you
say that, OK, I'm going to
support this old browser.
But ultimately, what will happen
is you'll get more and
more devices.
Nowadays, we get devices which
are running a very good
version of Android, but
are less than $100.
So even though they're running
like a very, very nice version
of WebKit, for example, the
performance is such that it
really makes them almost
like a legacy
browser in many cases.
So how do you define a legacy
browser is going to become
more and more muddled because
a browser with a very, very
nice phone can behave like a
legacy browser if the network
connection sucks.
And there's a lot of smartphones
coming up with
good version of WebKit,
but very underpowered.
TOM MASLEN: It's
a strange time.
So you've got like a Nokia C5
that's an entry level phone.
It's got a really bad processor
and RAM, but it will
have a really good version
of WebKit on it.
So it will render the
page really well.
And then you can compare that to
an iPhone 5 that has Opera
Mini in it.
So the capabilities would be
less, or you would at least
get a static version
of the site.
It's a very bizarre issue
to try and solve.
I don't think there
is a magic bullet.
TOMOMI IMURA: Actually, in the
Modernizr web page, in the
documentation set, just because
you can use polyfill
doesn't mean you should.
I think I say that in aside.
PAUL IRISH: It's true.
TOMOMI IMURA: Yeah,
so it's really--
developers have to decide what
you want to really support.
Many times, like a fancy UI will
be really nice, but do
you really care in
some browsers?
I mean, like round
corners, really?
You don't always need this.
You can't always
drop certain--
especially if it's just UI
prettiness you can drop it.
PAUL IRISH: But I guess the
other part of this is that
there are some features, there's
a set of features that
you cannot let degrade
gracefully.
WebGL, getUserMedia, Web Audio
API, many can't be polyfilled.
And so what is the responsible
way in defining a browser
support policy when you're
dealing with
features of this sort?
Where you're providing an
experience that competes with
something on a native platform
and it's not content based.
TOM MASLEN: So you
mentioned WebGL.
I can give you an
example there.
On the BBC News, we've started
doing WebGL content now.
We've got the Mars, We had the
Mars lander 3D object.
So if you had WebGL supported,
you could spin it round and
zoom in and stuff like that,
and it was really nice.
But then, there's no
polyfill in that.
So what other browsers
would get is an image
gallery of the 3D model.
So we wouldn't try to polyfill
the content.
We offered an alternative
content.
PAUL IRISH: OK.
I'd like to move on to
the next question.
John [INAUDIBLE], if you
could, would love--
thank you.
AUDIENCE: So I took this
question, because
I don't like it.
So I didn't want
it to be asked.
The question was roughly that
they felt that you could get
away with supporting browsers
that did not have JavaScript.
And I feel that that
is not the case.
That for most content websites,
you need to support
clients that do not
have JavaScript.
But to spin it into a more
legitimate question, what
about web applications where
you're not dealing with
strictly content-based?
I feel like most of you are
dealing with content, where
it's like here's
a news article.
Here's some information
you want to read.
Obviously, in that case, there
shouldn't be a barrier between
you and reading that.
So but what about a whole
application that is built and
very JavaScript-centric, should
you be making a fall
back for that?
I know if you want to use
Gmail and there's no
JavaScript, you fall back to
this form-based thing.
And I have no idea how well
that's maintained, but that's
got to be someone's sad job.
But I mean, like I assume not
everyone wants to be doing old
HTML tables and doing
the forms.
So is that a legitimate thing?
Should people be worrying
about that for their
applications?
PAUL IRISH: Tom?
TOM MASLEN: I'd say it's always
best to create an
experience that doesn't just
immediately fail when
something goes wrong with
the JavaScript.
So I think Gmail is a great
example that you point out.
So it's something that
is a service.
It is purely functionality.
But then, I think we should
just make the experience--
there's a great--
oh, in fact, I'll let
you say this.
So I read on the GDS website
about why you should make
progressive enhancement
with JavaScript.
Do you get what I'm
talking about?
EDD SOWDEN: No.
TOM MASLEN: OK, so Edd said that
build your applications
like an escalator instead
of a lift.
Do you get me now?
Was that you that said that?
EDD SOWDEN: I don't think
I wrote that.
TOMOMI IMURA: Was it Jake?
I remember reading this
about elevator.
TOM MASLEN: I read it
on the GDS site.
So somebody said if an escalator
breaks, the worst
thing that's going to happen
is it's going to turn into
some stairs so you can
keep walking up it.
But then if you're in a lift
and it breaks, then you're
stuck in the fucking lift.
There's nothing you can do.
And it's the same with
JavaScript applications.
PAUL IRISH: Well, I guess
there's a certain--
there's plenty of JavaScript
applications, the diagramming
tool and IM client, like many
of these rely on real-time
data cannot be done with
page refreshes.
And so some of these do require
JavaScript further
interactions.
EDD SOWDEN: Jake wrote a good
blog post on this recently.
PAUL IRISH: Yeah.
Jake, would you like
to comment on how--
EDD SOWDEN: But as you couldn't
see, Jake was waving
quite madly.
AUDIENCE: I'm kind of perching
on the stairs because I was
actually on the way
to the bathroom.
So you caught me just
at the right point.
Any website that has a loading
bar is a missed opportunity,
is a missed opportunity to serve
the content directly
without JavaScript and
then get JavaScript
in there to do it.
And Gmail is an example
of that.
Gmail should have URLs.
I should be able to bookmark a
page to a particular email.
And when I hit that, I should
get that content on the page,
and then JavaScript can come
in and add the rest.
I mean, it is just a series
of tabs and forms.
It doesn't need to depend on
JavaScript for first render.
PAUL IRISH: But the Gmail Web
App also has URLs that are
permanent linkable for
all messages as well.
SHWETANK DIXIT: One thing I
wanted to mention, just to
repeat which matches this use
case is you have JavaScript
applications heavily reliant
on JavaScript.
But you also have these phones
which are coming up which will
have browsers which support
JavaScript.
But these are underpowered
phones in which it will be
actually better for them to
get a version without
JavaScript than to get a version
with JavaScript but
which runs really,
really slowly.
So in those cases, it might be
better for them to get a
lighter version of the page.
And the other thing is search
engines-- once again, if you
have like single page
applications, you can run node
and PhantomJS and use a
solution with that.
But I still think that it would
be better to just have
something which can be run
without JavaScript.
PAUL IRISH: I suppose in the
search engine optimization,
it's a balance of what's
easy for you.
But certainly, if it's important
for you to have that
content available to
search, you need to
find a way to do that.
Either through progressive
enhancement or through a
complex server-side
rendering farm.
TOM MASLEN: The other side of
the argument is making an
application that purely relies
on JavaScript is probably a
lot faster.
So I would say if you're trying
to get something up and
running fast, if you're
prototyping, if you've got
deadline issues, then
that is an option.
You can do that.
However, I would always try to
make something a progressive
enhancement.
So in the slide where
I spoke about the
things that were nice.
So accessibility, SEO, working
without JavaScript, usability,
all those things
are idealisms.
And on their own, they're
probably not great arguments
that you can go to your manager
and say, hey, this
doesn't work with screen readers
because your boss will
probably turn around and
say, I don't care
about screen readers.
But when you add them all
together, they create
something bigger.
And that's the whole
point of the web.
And all of those things, if you
develop with all of those
things in mind, then you're
kind of developing in the
current of the web.
You're swimming with the web as
opposed to swimming against
it, which is what I think is
like applications that are
purely JavaScript are swimming
against a little bit.
So you can make things that are
purely JavaScript, but I
think it's better and you get
added benefits by building
things in a progressive
enhanced way.
PAUL IRISH: Matt [INAUDIBLE],
I see you have a comment.
We're going to have to make this
very quick, but I want to
get your voice here.
AUDIENCE: Sorry, somebody says
accessibility and I go crazy.
I just wanted to
add onto this.
And I think BBC is a great
example of this, that the
users of assistive technology
are not like legacy or
down-level users either.
If you have something, like data
visualization or chat or
anything interactive, those are
still things that you need
to make accessible whether or
not you're going to serve them
to legacy clients.
Everybody is expecting that.
They have the latest assistive
technologies.
They have the latest browsers
like everybody else.
And it's important to decouple
them from like, well, we'll
just serve them the text-only
site because that's the same
[INAUDIBLE]
they've had since the '90s.
PAUL IRISH: Yep, 98.4% of
screen reader users have
JavaScript enabled from
recent [INAUDIBLE]
survey.
But guys, I think we're
out of time.
Thank you very much to our
panelists for joining us up
here and thank you, guys.
[APPLAUSE]